<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>cybersecurity on Engineering Health</title>
    <link>https://engineering.cerner.com/tags/cybersecurity/</link>
    <description>Recent content in cybersecurity on Engineering Health</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 29 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://engineering.cerner.com/tags/cybersecurity/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Infusing a Culture of Cybersecurity within Cerner Engineering</title>
      <link>https://engineering.cerner.com/blog/culture-of-cybersecurity/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://engineering.cerner.com/blog/culture-of-cybersecurity/</guid>
      <description>With October being Cybersecurity Awareness month, we thought it would be a good time to reflect on some of the things we do in engineering to educate our associates and infuse security into our culture. We have over 28,000 associates worldwide supporting hundreds of solutions with millions of lines of code. Each associate has a specialization, such as software development, system support, and consulting. Keeping everyone up to date on the latest in security is a difficult task.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Girl Scouts earn Cybersecurity Badge at Cerner</title>
      <link>https://engineering.cerner.com/blog/girl-scouts-cybersecurity/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://engineering.cerner.com/blog/girl-scouts-cybersecurity/</guid>
      <description>As a software engineering executive from Colombia, I thought that the best way to honor Hispanic Heritage Month (September 15-October 15) was to help the local Girl Scout Hispanic troops earn one of the new cybersecurity badges. October is Cybersecurity Awareness Month, having the activities nearing October seemed very fitting.
Girl Scouts has been focusing on STEM badges for all ages with several new initiatives in the past couple of years.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
