<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Engineering Health]]></title>
  <link href="http://engineering.cerner.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://engineering.cerner.com/"/>
  <updated>2017-09-27T08:55:09-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://engineering.cerner.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Cerner]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Jwala Joins Cerner's Open Source]]></title>
    <link href="http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/jwala-joins-cerner-open-source/"/>
    <updated>2017-09-27T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/jwala-joins-cerner-open-source</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>Introducing Jwala, a Resource Manager for the Apache Community</h3>

<p><a href="http://tomcat.apache.org/">Apache Tomcat</a> and <a href="https://httpd.apache.org/">Apache httpd</a> are hardened, scalable, and reliable open-source solutions. Widely adopted, these solutions are commonly used to host and load-balance Java applications.</p>

<p>Configuring and managing a small set of elements is relatively easy, but once you start scaling out your application and platform, things get complicated. Questions such as &ldquo;How do I update the heap or database pool-size across hundreds of Java Virtual Machines (JVMs)?&rdquo; arise. Although commercial solutions exist to solve this and other similar problems, an open-source solution was not available &ndash; until now.</p>

<p>Originally designed and developed to accommodate Cerner&rsquo;s complex topologies, Jwala was developed to automate deploying our web applications here at Cerner. Now Cerner is donating Jwala as open source. Making contributions to development communities is an important part of Cerner&rsquo;s engineering culture. We love it when we&rsquo;re able to give back to the community, and we&rsquo;re sure you&rsquo;ll love Jwala!</p>

<p>A Cerner platform based on Apache Tomcat and Apache httpd, Jwala enables the configuration, deployment, and management of logical groups of Tomcat JVMs load-balanced by Apache web servers.</p>

<p>With Jwala you can configure, deploy, and manage your large-scale Tomcat and Apache httpd topology at an enterprise scale. You can create and persist definitions of Group instances that include web applications, JVMs, web servers, and other resources, and expose them through a RESTful interface, Jwala&rsquo;s REST API, to perform management operations on the group.</p>

<p>Jwala utilizes a defined file system structure and Secure Shell (SSH) agents on each machine to manage running Tomcat instances on remote servers. Jwala&rsquo;s application deployment model knows how to request current status from each Tomcat and httpd instance. Jwala also is able to update each instance as changes are made to the configuration and allows maintenance operations to be executed from a central console. Last but not least, Jwala maintains an audit log of all the operations or changes performed on any of its managed resources.</p>

<p>So, if you are someone in development, operations, or management looking for an easier way to configure and manage a large Tomcat topology, <a href="https://github.com/cerner/jwala">check out Jwala</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Engineers Overseas for SMART and FHIR (FHIR DevDays 2016)]]></title>
    <link href="http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/engineers-overseas-for-smart-and-fhir/"/>
    <updated>2017-09-21T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/engineers-overseas-for-smart-and-fhir</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In a <a href="http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/engineers-on-the-road-for-smart-and-fhir/">previous post</a>, we discussed the need to provide education around our ecosystem and implementation of the <a href="http://hl7.org/fhir/overview-dev.html">FHIRⓇ</a> and <a href="http://docs.smarthealthit.org/">SMARTⓇ</a> standards for developers and how we did so at our annual Cerner Health Conference. That same week, we were also a part of <a href="http://www.fhirdevdays.com/">FHIR DevDays</a>, which included a track entitled &ldquo;Apps in the EHR.&rdquo; We worked alongside track participants who were seeking to integrate their apps in a variety of EHRs, including Cerner.</p>

<p>FHIR DevDays is a conference put on by <a href="http://fhir.furore.com/">Furore</a> in Amsterdam. This year, over 250 participants from all over the world gathered to attend tutorials given by FHIR community leaders in the mornings and participate in hands-on sessions in the afternoons.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2017-09-21-engineers-overseas-for-smart-and-fhir/Devdays_2016.jpg"></p>

<p>Cerner co-led the &ldquo;Apps in the EHR&rdquo; track. This track was comprised of roughly 20 people from across France, Germany, Ireland, Israel, Italy, Netherlands, Norway, Spain, Switzerland, the United Kingdom, and the United States. <a href="https://twitter.com/JoshCMandel">Josh Mandel</a> kicked things off with a tutorial on <a href="http://smarthealthit.org/">SMART</a> and how to <a href="http://docs.smarthealthit.org/">get started</a> building cross-vendor applications. Afterward, we met with track participants to show them how to get plugged into Cerner&rsquo;s sandbox and ecosystem. We started out by covering our <a href="https://code.cerner.com/">documentation launchpoint</a>, registering applications in our <a href="https://code.cerner.com/developer/smart-on-fhir">code console</a>, and going over our <a href="http://fhir.cerner.com/">technical documentation</a>. For those who didn&rsquo;t come to the conference with an existing application to work on, we provided a <a href="http://engineering.cerner.com/smart-on-fhir-tutorial">tutorial</a>. With those tools in hand, they were ready to get to work!</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2017-09-21-engineers-overseas-for-smart-and-fhir/hands-on.jpg"></p>

<br />


<p><img class="center" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2017-09-21-engineers-overseas-for-smart-and-fhir/hands-on2.png"></p>

<p>Over the course of the three afternoons, we assisted people as they used SMART and FHIR for the first time, but also people with experience in FHIR who were looking to get their technical and business questions answered about integrating with Cerner.
Several of the projects were plugged into multiple sandboxes. The developers shared that once their app was working in one sandbox, it was easy to plug into others, which is exactly how it should be!</p>

<p>When we gave our closing presentation, we actually had some technical difficulties loading up the slides. Little did we know that <a href="https://twitter.com/grahamegrieve">Grahame Grieve</a>, the original architect of FHIR, snapped a picture and would use it shortly in his <a href="https://vimeo.com/192190127">closing keynote</a> on FHIR’s future.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2017-09-21-engineers-overseas-for-smart-and-fhir/closing-keynote.jpg"></p>

<p><a href="https://twitter.com/fhir_furore/status/799626324927053824">With this image on screen</a>, he stated: &ldquo;[to us:] Well done. [to the rest of the audience:] Next time somebody in your acquaintance tells you that certain vendors aren&rsquo;t invested in interoperability, I want you to think about this. That&rsquo;s part of what the FHIR community is about, alright? Cerner and Epic on the stage together. It&rsquo;s not special anymore, even. It&rsquo;s great!&rdquo;</p>

<p>FHIR DevDays is Europe&rsquo;s biggest FHIR conference and many attendees don&rsquo;t typically make it to the tri-annual HL7 Working Group Meetings that focus on the formation and evolution of the specification. We were pleased to be a part of that gathering and to work alongside people interested in engaging with Cerner. But, we were also encouraged by the comments Grahame and others gave as they expressed appreciation that Cerner would be present and show our interest and dedication to the standard. We look forward to being back at DevDays 2017 this November to lead tracks on SMART &amp; FHIR and CDS Hooks.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[ShipIt IX Day: Summer 2017]]></title>
    <link href="http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/shipit-ix-day-summer-2017/"/>
    <updated>2017-09-11T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/shipit-ix-day-summer-2017</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2017-09-11-shipit-ix-day-summer-2017/shipit-day-ix-6.jpg"></p>

<p>There is no better way to end summer than with ShipIt Day! We kicked off our ninth ShipIt Day on August 10th, with more than 75 Cerner associates signed up. Nineteen different teams worked for 24 hours straight to complete their projects. For those unfamiliar with the event, ShipIt Day is a 24 hour hackathon for internal associates to create something innovative, usable, and value-adding. This was the second ShipIt held at our new <a href="https://www.bizjournals.com/kansascity/news/2017/02/10/get-a-sneak-peek-inside-cerner-s-new-innovations.html">Innovations Campus</a>. Associates love using our new campus for ShipIt because of the game rooms and collaboration spaces! One new addition to this quarter’s ShipIt Day was the scavenger hunt. Participants were given a list of crazy tasks to accomplish within the 24 hours. Some tasks included spoon feeding a fellow team member, completing the obstacle courses around the outdoor walking trail, and finding binary codes around campus and decoding them. Shoutout to the winners of the scavenger hunt: the Jumpy Woodchucks team!</p>

<div align="center">
  <img class="center" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2017-09-11-shipit-ix-day-summer-2017/shipit-day-ix-1.jpg">
  <sub>Teams were given lots of snacks and drinks to keep them fueled for the next 24 hours.</sub>
</div>




<div align="center">
  <img class="center" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2017-09-11-shipit-ix-day-summer-2017/shipit-day-ix-3.jpg">
  <sub>Collaboration is key to a successful project.</sub>
</div>


<p>For dinner, we brought in some of the biggest pizzas Kansas City has to offer from Pizza 51. By dinner time the participants were ready to chow down and give their brains a break. Dinner entertainment included <em>School of Rock</em> and <em>Futurama</em>.</p>

<div align="center">
  <img class="center" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2017-09-11-shipit-ix-day-summer-2017/shipit-day-ix-11.jpg">
  <sub>Chaos ensued as everyone runs to grab some pizza!</sub>
</div>




<div align="center">
  <img class="center" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2017-09-11-shipit-ix-day-summer-2017/shipit-day-ix-2.jpg">
  <sub><i>School of Rock</i> was played during dinner.</sub>
</div>


<p>Associates stayed overnight and worked around the clock to ensure their projects would be complete by presentation time. However, sometimes you just need a nap.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2017-09-11-shipit-ix-day-summer-2017/shipit-day-ix-4.jpg"></p>

<p>Presentation day is always an exciting one. After 24 hours of hard work, the teams have 4 minutes to show off their product to their peers and a panel of rock-star judges. A special thank you to Brian Wallace, Amon Woolridge, and Greg Whitsitt for judging this round.</p>

<div align="center">
  <table>
    <tr>
      <td align="center">
        <img class="center" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2017-09-11-shipit-ix-day-summer-2017/shipit-day-ix-9.jpg">
        <sub>We always start presentation day off with bagels for breakfast from Panera.</sub>
      </td>
      <td align="center">
        <img class="center" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2017-09-11-shipit-ix-day-summer-2017/shipit-day-ix-12.jpg">
        <sub>The Prize Table.</sub>
      </td>
    </tr>
  </table>
</div>


<h3>Team Bravo Avocado</h3>

<p>ShipIt Day IX teams brought their A game. The projects get more intricate and more impressive each time around. ShipIt Day is a great way to show off the talent we have at Cerner. Team Bravo Avocado, made up of Thomas Clay, Jacob Zimmerman, Jan Monterrubio, Max Schroeder, and Elisha Boozer took first place! Judges were impressed by their live demo and humorous presentation style.</p>

<blockquote><p>Our project was an enhancement for Millennium Java services that removes certain required pieces of server implementation by adding custom annotations. Consumers will no longer have the same restrictions from traditional service generation (i.e. defining a generation file, method naming), because the annotation processor will generate that for them. Also, the framework can bind the structured request/reply objects to an annotated object of their choice. These annotations remove lots of redundant code and gives consumers more time to focus on what matters.</p></blockquote>

<div align="center">
  <img class="center" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2017-09-11-shipit-ix-day-summer-2017/shipit-day-ix-8.jpg">
  <sub>Team Bravo Avocado with the Golden Keyboard.</sub>
</div>


<h3>Team E=MC Hammer</h3>

<p>Second place went to team E=MC Hammer, made up of Kyle Lipke, Nimesh Subramanian, James Boyd, Mahesh Sampekatte, and Megan McConnell.</p>

<blockquote><p>For ShipIt IX, our team E=MC Hammer built a tool that looks up and publishes Millennium OAuth keys. This tool was created to be an easy-to-use, easy-to-search, and updateable source of truth for all those that request and use Millennium OAuth keys. We set up an api that hosts only the data we wish to present, in a read-only &ldquo;MAP&rdquo; so users understand the structure of the data. We had a blast on the project and would recommend attending a ShipIt day yourself!</p></blockquote>

<p>Judge Greg Whitsitt noted that their project was:</p>

<blockquote><p>&hellip;applicable across teams, solves a problem many face. A great idea and great execution.</p></blockquote>

<div align="center">
  <img class="center" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2017-09-11-shipit-ix-day-summer-2017/shipit-day-ix-7.jpg">
  <sub>Team E=MC Hammer.</sub>
</div>


<h3>Team Jumpy Woodchucks</h3>

<p>Team Jumpy Woodchucks, made up of Hans Perera, Nathaniel Owen, Ann Dickey, James Thomas, and Pramoth Murali took third place. Their project was Chamberlain:</p>

<blockquote><p>Light notification system for all your notification needs that decorates your desk. This system currently supports alerts for Microsoft Outlook, Crucible, and Millennium domain health. Designed to be highly customizable and a project for teams to learn about electronics and use of Makerspace.</p></blockquote>

<p>Judges commented that this project was what the heart of ShipIt Day is all about.</p>

<div align="center">
  <img class="center" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2017-09-11-shipit-ix-day-summer-2017/shipit-day-ix-5.jpg">
  <sub>Team Jumpy Woodchucks.</sub>
</div>


<h3>People&rsquo;s Choice Awards</h3>

<p>We had a packed house for ShipIt Day presentations. Associates could watch live in the Assembly or catch it on the livestream website.  One of the best parts of ShipIt Day is letting the audience join in on the fun and vote for their favorite team name, best presentation, and favorite project. Congratulations to the following teams&hellip;</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Favorite Team Name</strong>: 🌝 &ndash; Venkatesh Sridharan, Ian Kottman, Anthony Ross, Karthik Nimmagadda, and Abhi Mahabalshetti</li>
<li><strong>Favorite Project</strong>: Message Therapist &ndash;  Siddhartha Dutta, Ashish Nair, Noah Benham, and James Lawson</li>
<li><strong>Best Presentation</strong>: Bravo Avocado &ndash; Thomas Clay, Jacob Zimmerman, Jan Monterrubio, Max Schroeder, and Elisha Boozer</li>
</ul>


<div align="center">
  <img class="center" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2017-09-11-shipit-ix-day-summer-2017/shipit-day-ix-10.jpg">
  <sub>The Assembly during presentations.</sub>
</div>


<h3>Summary</h3>

<p>Each ShipIt Day, we see a handful of ShipIt &ldquo;veterans.&rdquo; It is always interesting to hear our associates take on the 24 hour event. Ian Kottman, a software engineer on the Population Health Genomics team, has a lot to say about his experience participating in ShipIt Day.</p>

<blockquote><p>I recently got to take part in one of my favorite events at Cerner: ShipIt Day. This was my fourth ShipIt and I was excited about the project my team had come up with. My team had named ourselves 🌝, which is one of the team member&rsquo;s favorite emoji. We planned to add a UI to a tool we created last ShipIt to manage access to Cerner&rsquo;s Makerspace. Our primary goal this time around was to have fun and win the coveted cheeseballs.</p>

<p>In the short 24 hours we had our team went through all of the stages of a typical software project: design, implementation, realization we overestimated, shedding unneeded features, and finally getting something working. Partway through the day we ran into issues getting Chrome to run in a Docker container and there was a brief incident involving internationalization breaking our error page, but after many whiteboard sessions and late night sodas we completed a working product. We even managed to have time for a few hours of sleep before the presentations. When it was all said and done we had accomplished our goal: we won cheeseballs for best team name! All in all, we had an excellent time collaborating and developing a tool that will be used for a long time to come. I&rsquo;m already thinking about what to work on next ShipIt&hellip;</p></blockquote>

<p>ShipIt continues to be a great way for associates to work on something they haven’t had a chance to work on, build relationships within different organizations, and most importantly, enjoy themselves. ShipIt Day IX was a great success. The projects were creative and have potential to be built upon and used in Cerner’s everyday work flow. We are already looking forward to our next ShipIt Day in December!</p>

<p>If you are interested in learning more about other ShipIt Days, see these earlier posts:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/shipit-day-viii-spring-2017/">ShipIt Day VIII Spring 2017</a></li>
<li><a href="http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/shipit-vii-day-winter-2016/">ShipIt Day VII Winter 2016</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=iqTp0dmLgUk">ShipIt Day Winter 2016 Highlight Reel</a></li>
<li><a href="http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/fall-2016-shipit-day/">ShipIt Day Fall 2016</a></li>
<li><a href="http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/spring-2016-shipit-day/">ShipIt Day Spring 2016</a></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Continuous Delivery for DC/OS With Spinnaker]]></title>
    <link href="http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/continuous-delivery-for-dcos-with-spinnaker/"/>
    <updated>2017-09-08T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/continuous-delivery-for-dcos-with-spinnaker</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last fall our team (<a href="https://github.com/mtweten">Mike Tweten</a>, <a href="https://github.com/TrevinTeacutter">Trevin Teacutter</a>, and <a href="https://github.com/zsura">Zameer Sura</a>) started working on the problem of automating <a href="https://mesosphere.com/product/">DC/OS</a> deployments in a way that wouldn&rsquo;t require multiple teams to duplicate effort and tie themselves directly to DC/OS APIs.  While DC/OS certainly makes the act of deploying an application much easier than anything we&rsquo;ve used previously, there are still many different ways you could choose to layer on deployment strategies and integrate with continuous delivery systems. Additionally, there may be lots of teams with very similar needs in this space and there are certainly more efficient uses of their time than making them all solve the same problems.  Furthermore, while DC/OS is a good choice today we need to make sure that we don’t become locked in and can change our mind in the future without a big impact to those teams.</p>

<p>Being an engineering team, naturally our first approach was to try to write a service to manage a simple set of deployment strategies with an API that we could reimplement over other resource schedulers (like <a href="https://kubernetes.io/">Kubernetes</a>) in the future.  However, after producing a prototype we really started to grasp that we were taking on a much bigger task than we should.  Our API could handle some basic pre-built deployment workflows, but if it wasn&rsquo;t flexible enough for teams we&rsquo;d need to continue to adapt it.  In addition, we would still have to work out how it would integrate with CI/CD tools like <a href="https://jenkins.io/">Jenkins</a>, and we&rsquo;d have to do a lot of that work again each time we wanted to support another resource scheduler as a deployment target.</p>

<p>At this point we decided to take a deeper look at <a href="https://www.spinnaker.io/">Spinnaker</a>, a continuous delivery platform that was open-sourced by Netflix.  It had originally been developed to orchestrate AWS deployments and had expanded to other providers like Azure, OpenStack, and more recently Kubernetes was added as the first container based deployment target.
Spinnaker allows for building deployment pipelines that can be triggered by things like Github commits or Jenkins builds and can then run stages to do things like start other Jenkins jobs, deploy new versions of an application, scale up or down applications, and disable old application versions.  With these capabilities we would be able to use Spinnaker to provide a consistent deployment abstraction while still providing the flexibility to handle deployment workflows that we didn&rsquo;t build ourselves.</p>

<p>The only minor problem was that it didn&rsquo;t support DC/OS, our preferred deployment target. After taking some time to dive in and get familiar with the details it quickly became apparent that adding support for DC/OS would be much easier than continuing to build our own system, especially since we had already become familiar with the DC/OS APIs while developing our prototype.  Not only would we then gain the flexibility to allow more deployment strategies than we originally anticipated, but it would also buy us integration with Jenkins and the ability to convert pipelines over to Kubernetes without much effort.  We checked with the Spinnaker community to make sure that no one was already working on DC/OS support and also with <a href="https://mesosphere.com/">Mesosphere</a> (the company behind DC/OS) to make sure they weren&rsquo;t planning to do it.  When both of those came back negative we began working on the project in earnest, with the goal of building something that would benefit not only Cerner but also the entire Spinnaker and DC/OS communities.</p>

<p>This was the first time that any of us had tried to contribute significant changes to an established open-source project so there was some adjustment and learning along the way.  We initially created our fork of the necessary repositories to our internal Github with the plan to finish the project before making anything visible publicly. Instead, we found that we wanted to more easily be able to share things with Mesosphere since they had agreed to give us any guidance we might need.  It also became apparent that it was too easy to commit things like config that referenced internal resources, or comments that referred to our own <a href="https://www.atlassian.com/software/jira">JIRA</a> issues.  If we kept going that way we were only going to make more work for ourselves cleaning those things up when it came time to submit our changes.  By moving our development to repos in <a href="https://github.com/cerner">Cerner&rsquo;s Github organization</a> we were able to solve both of these problems at once.</p>

<p>In spite of moving our code into the public Github we still maintained an insular development approach, determined to get everything just right before submitting a perfect polished gem to the upstream project.  In hindsight, we should have been less concerned about trying to get everything right all at once and submitted more incremental changes.  We thought it would be easier for everyone not to have to deal with our messy work in progress, but after our first pull request for one of the services ended up with over 130 files and a history of 100+ commits we realized that it&rsquo;s too much to expect the maintainers to review so much at once, especially when they may not be that familiar with DC/OS.  Ultimately, they wanted us to carve up that massive patch anyway so it would have been less work for us to do it from the start.</p>

<p>After completing this effort we&rsquo;ve found that we get even more benefit from Spinnaker than we initially expected.  Spinnaker also helps us manage deployments to multiple DC/OS clusters, use <a href="https://github.com/Netflix/chaosmonkey">Chaos Monkey</a> to test the resiliency of our applications, and even to deploy DC/OS itself on AWS. We&rsquo;re pleased to announce that our contribution has been accepted by the Spinnaker maintainers and is now <a href="https://www.spinnaker.io/community/releases/versions/1-3-0-changelog">available for anyone to use</a>.  The Spinnaker community has been great to work with and helped us by answering questions and inviting us to participate in the discussions with other companies that have contributed major functionality to Spinnaker.  This is an exciting opportunity to contribute something back to the open-source community and we can&rsquo;t wait to see where it goes from here.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Structure Matters: How Cerner Handled Too Much Health Data in HBase]]></title>
    <link href="http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/structure-matters-how-cerner-handled-too-much-health-data-in-hbase/"/>
    <updated>2017-08-28T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/structure-matters-how-cerner-handled-too-much-health-data-in-hbase</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>Background</h3>

<p>In order to manage the health of populations, Cerner builds data-driven solutions built on top of its <em>HealtheIntent</em>&#8480; platform. The platform transforms and standardizes data across disparate health systems. The data is then used in algorithms that aid healthcare providers and hospitals in managing and monitoring health both at a person and population level.</p>

<p>The Reference Record is one of the core components of the HealtheIntent platform. It represents the data known about a person&rsquo;s health from a particular source of healthcare information. Downstream components in the platform aggregate information across multiple reference records to understand the full picture of a person&rsquo;s health.</p>

<p>To create the record, the system performs both batch and stream processing. Some sources send the data to HealtheIntent once a day or once a month. That data is processed in batch, using Hadoop MapReduce jobs. For sources that send the data as streams of updates in near real time, we rely on a homegrown near real time framework that sits on top of Apache Storm. Both the pipelines persist their processed data in HBase tables.</p>

<p>For the data processed in batch, we write all the data about the person from a given source to the HBase table as one HBase row. We refer to this as a wide table. The HBase Rowkey is the source identifier followed by the person identifier: <code>/source:&lt;id&gt;/person:&lt;id&gt;</code>. Each row could have multiple columns, one per each healthcare entity like allergy, medication, procedure, etc. Another thing to note is this table is salted for better distribution of data across regions. That means a given person&rsquo;s data will be in a single region since it&rsquo;s all in one row, but the data for a given source will be distributed across the HBase cluster.</p>

<p>For streaming sources, we use a different table approach. We have a tall table, where each healthcare entity is written separately. The Rowkey in this approach would be built from the source identifier, person identifier, entity type, and then individual entity identifier. This allows the system to manage the information flowing from the stream more efficiently.</p>

<p>To make sure that the consumers of the record don&rsquo;t have to know whether the data is coming from a streaming or batch source system, we offer a Crunch-based extract API that is capable of reading from either table structure. The API provides a single, consistent representation of the data.</p>

<p>The purpose of this post is to discuss what happened when a single person in our system received a little too much healthcare over the course of her fake life.</p>

<h3>The Investigation</h3>

<p>We were bringing a new source of healthcare data onto the HealtheIntent platform using our batch processing pipeline. In the midst of this work, a small number of MapReduce jobs started failing. Our failure monitoring triggered and notified us that something wasn&rsquo;t right.</p>

<p>We turned to the logs to investigate the failures. We saw this (not very informative) message:</p>

<blockquote><p>Task attempt_xxxx failed to report status for 601 seconds. Killing!</p></blockquote>

<p>Our first assumption was that the issue was related to memory, but we profiled the job and found that the heap utilization looked fine.</p>

<p>Querying across all the logs, we were able to see two key pieces of information. One, a job was more likely to fail if it was reading from a particular source of data, and two, failures were correlated with alerts on slow response times in HBase. Drilling deeper into our logs, we were able to find that sure enough, we were timing out trying to read from a particular region in HBase.</p>

<p>The next obvious step was to look at region metrics. We found the region had grown in size to 115 GB on a cluster configured to have a max region size of 10 GB. More logs showed the table had stopped compacting and splits weren&rsquo;t working due to a 30 GB row in the table.</p>

<p>At this time, anything trying to read that row was failing, but some large writes were still succeeding. There would be attempts to bulk load new data to the region, but the loads would invariably fail due to the large row. When the job ran again, it would attempt to write the same data, over and over. Occasionally during these attempts, some of the data would get written to the region. This process piled more and more data onto the region, and the region wouldn&rsquo;t split.</p>

<p>As the region was growing, the situation got worse. As previously mentioned, we salt the row keys to distribute data across the cluster. Jobs interested in other source data were also reading from this region, so we started seeing failures in other jobs. Then in the midst of our investigation, we saw more HBase region servers start failing. Then HBase bulk loads in other MapReduce jobs were also failing. We knew we had to get rid of the row and split the region.</p>

<p>As some team members worked on a plan to deal with the row, others moved on to answering the question, &ldquo;How did this one row get so big that the bulk loads started failing?&rdquo;</p>

<p>With healthcare data, it&rsquo;s possible to imagine diseases that might lead someone to have so many encounters and activity within a single healthcare system that we could get to a gigabyte of health data about a person. However, we had never seen anything near this large before. It was a pretty significant outlier.</p>

<h3>Getting Rid of the Alternative Fact</h3>

<p>We decided to delete the person&rsquo;s data. However, the person had grown so large, this proved difficult. (The naive approach to deleting a row in HBase failed spectacularly.) Splitting was also not possible.</p>

<p>We needed a better plan. First, all reads and writes to the region had to stopped. This meant suspending all jobs that any potential to read or write. Since several teams depended on our data for their processing, we started by notifying all our downstream consumers. Then we stopped all reads and writes to the affected region. We copied the affected Hfiles to a new table. This allowed compaction (and as a result, deletion) to succeed. Cleaning up this one bad record brought the region size down to 2 GB from 200 GB. As part of this process, the table was disabled and the compacted Hfiles from the fixed region were copied back to the old table before it was re-enabled.</p>

<h3>Damage</h3>

<p>When we stopped all the jobs loading into that table, we had a stale data period for downstream processing. Reports that needed the data showed old information during the length of the incident investigation and mitigation. The good news is that our near real-time algorithms such as our Sepsis alerts and readmissions risk assessments were built on top of the stream processing system which was not impacted by this incident.</p>

<h3>Prevention</h3>

<p>In our postmortem for the incident, we reviewed what we could have done better before, during, and immediately following the situation. A quick win for us was to add HBase region size monitoring &amp; alerting. It is still reactive, but would help us react faster and minimize the duration of the event.</p>

<p>Ultimately, the root of the problem is that we have an approach that encourages a lot of data to accumulate in a single row. We had a design flaw. While this patient was outside the realm of anything we&rsquo;d seen before, it wasn&rsquo;t outside the realm of possibility. To quote an oldie, but goodie from Frederick Brooks, &ldquo;Our first response should be to reorganize the modules&#8217; data structures.&rdquo;</p>

<p>This event made us realize our batch and streaming representations of the data need to converge. That is the path we&rsquo;re now taking which will introduce its own set of challenges, but we&rsquo;re confident this will land us in a more stable, scalable place.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Managing Splunk's Knowledge]]></title>
    <link href="http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/managing-splunk-knowledge/"/>
    <updated>2017-07-14T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/managing-splunk-knowledge</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When we first were given access to <a href="https://www.splunk.com/">Splunk</a> we were excited about all the functionality it could provide our team to help us monitor and debug our applications. We created alerts to email us if our applications are logging errors, dashboards to show health or metrics of our services, and field extractions as well as tags to make searching easier. As we created more and more of these Splunk knowledge objects we started to have issues. For regulatory and validation concerns, we have several Splunk instances that represent different environments. This required us to copy and paste or duplicate the Splunk knowledge object we created in one environment to all the others. This became very tedious and we saw all sorts of problems. Objects were only copied to some Splunk instances, updates were sometimes lost, and permissions weren&rsquo;t consistent or someone would forget to make their object publically viewable. We set out to look for a solution.</p>

<p>After we couldn&rsquo;t find anything that could easily help us we created a tool called <a href="https://github.com/cerner/splunk-pickaxe">splunk-pickaxe</a>. splunk-pickaxe is a Ruby gem that provides a command-line interface for synchronizing a directory or repository of Splunk knowledge objects written as files to a Splunk instance. So now when a developer creates a new Splunk object, they would create and test it in our Splunk dev instance and then open a pull request to our Splunk Github repository with the object&rsquo;s configuration or contents . Other developers review the changes before it gets merged and automatically pushed out to all our Splunk instances using our splunk-pickaxe tool and <a href="https://jenkins.io/">Jenkins</a> our continuous integration engine. This simplified things and provided consistency on these Splunk changes. We were also able to more effectively review the Splunk objects for efficient and proper Splunk usage.</p>

<p>The tool grew in popularity at Cerner and currently supports many Splunk objects:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://docs.splunk.com/Documentation/Splunk/6.6.2/Viz/Aboutthismanual">Dashboards</a></li>
<li><a href="https://docs.splunk.com/Documentation/Splunk/latest/Alert/Aboutalerts">Alerts</a></li>
<li><a href="https://docs.splunk.com/Documentation/Splunk/6.6.2/Report/Aboutreports">Reports</a></li>
<li><a href="http://docs.splunk.com/Documentation/Splunk/6.6.2/Knowledge/ExtractfieldsinteractivelywithIFX">Field Extractions</a></li>
<li><a href="http://docs.splunk.com/Documentation/SplunkCloud/6.6.0/Knowledge/TagandaliasfieldvaluesinSplunkWeb">Tags</a></li>
<li><a href="http://docs.splunk.com/Documentation/Splunk/6.6.2/Knowledge/Abouteventtypes">Event Types</a></li>
</ul>


<p>Check out the <a href="https://github.com/cerner/splunk-pickaxe#getting-started">Getting Started</a> section to try it out and feel welcome to <a href="https://github.com/cerner/splunk-pickaxe#contributing">contribute</a> any ideas or improvements.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[You May Not Be a Polyglot, but Your Code Needs to Be]]></title>
    <link href="http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/you-may-not-be-a-polyglot-but-your-code-needs-to-be/"/>
    <updated>2017-07-07T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/you-may-not-be-a-polyglot-but-your-code-needs-to-be</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last October, I had the privilege to speak at <a href="https://ghc.anitaborg.org/">Grace Hopper</a>, the world&rsquo;s largest gathering of women technologists. It was impressive to see 15,000 fellow female technologists gather together to share their experiences and technical expertise. To look into the audience, and see a room full of other female engineers was a great experience!</p>

<p>My talk was titled, You May Not Be a Polyglot, but Your Code Needs to Be (<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=923ac4CSqsw">previously presented at Midwest.io</a>).
One definition of the term polyglot is &ldquo;composed in many languages.&rdquo; During my talk, I discussed common misconceptions about writing code for global audiences, and I provided tips to help position engineers for success in these types of projects.</p>

<p>Having worked in engineering, translation, and localization for more than over a decade, I have seen first-hand how projects struggle through the globalization process. A properly globalized solution is generally achieved by ensuring the appropriate internationalization, localization, and translation steps have taken place; however, as developers, we have misconceptions that make this process more costly and less effective than it needs to be.</p>

<p>To help set the stage, I began my talk by speaking in Spanish. I love watching the audience react to my comments, as I usually say something silly during the introduction, so those who understand react one way, while others in the audience tend to look puzzled.</p>

<p>One of the most common misconceptions when coding for a global audience is the infamous statement: &ldquo;I&rsquo;ll NEVER need to do this.&rdquo; The most common rationalization for this misconception is that in the U.S., we only speak English, however, one in five U.S. residents speaks a foreign language at home. This is a record 61.8 million residents who speak languages other than English. Of these residents, 25.1 million (41 percent) told the Census Bureau that they speak English less than very well. Additionally, data from 2013 shows that there are seven languages with at least one million speakers in the US. These languages were Spanish (38.4 million), Chinese (three million), Tagalog (1.6 million), Vietnamese (1.4 million), French (1.3 million), and Korean and Arabic (1.1 million each). By only serving one audience, we are ignoring many customers and consumers of our solutions.  Even in my adopted hometown of Kansas City, 6% of the population speaks Spanish as their primary language.</p>

<p>Another common misconception is that internationalization and  localization are the same. Here are some definitions according to the Word Wide Web Consortium (W3):</p>

<blockquote><ul>
<li>&ldquo;Internationalization is the design and development of a product, application, or document content that <strong>enables</strong> easy localization for target audiences that vary in culture, region, or language.&rdquo;</li>
<li>&ldquo;Localization refers to the adaptation of a product, application or document content to meet the language, cultural and other requirements of a specific target market (a &lsquo;locale&rsquo;).&rdquo;</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>

<p>I like to think of their relationship more like this: <strong>i18N + L10N == G11N</strong></p>

<br />


<p>While the W3 notes, &ldquo;some people use other terms, such as globalization to refer to the same concept&rdquo; as internationalization,&ldquo; I see the appropriate execution of internationalization and localization together as providing a globalized solution.</p>

<p>Among examples of appropriately globalized solutions, TripAdvisor is one I like to highlight because it has a broad user base, and many of its users don&rsquo;t realize it is used by others around the world in their own language. The following Trip Advisor elements help provide a positive user experience:</p>

<ul>
<li>Flexing dates to show in the appropriate locale</li>
<li>Removing content that is not available in the target language (newsletters are a good example)</li>
<li>Accurate currency conversion</li>
<li>Allowing for text expansion to avoid truncation</li>
<li>Flexing logos and the brand to ensure that it is appropriate for the locale</li>
</ul>


<p>Another common misconception when creating globalized applications is that once something has been internationalized and translated, it can be shipped. The best way to highlight the folly of this perception is to look at some marketing mishaps. Below are some of my favorite ones:</p>

<blockquote><ul>
<li>A famous detergent from the Middle East, is white as snow, so it is called by the word for snow in Farsi. This doesn&rsquo;t work well when it is referenced in English-speaking countries. In Farsi, the word for snow is barf.</li>
<li>I also have a personal story. I come from a tropical country, and my native language is Spanish. When I first moved to the United States, I realized that I was not genetically engineered to be in the cold, dry weather of a Kansas City winter. My skin was itchy, and I desperately need some good hydrating lotion. My friends at school recommended something called Sarna. I was convinced they were trolling me because in Spanish, Sarna means <em>Scabies</em>.
I have endured more than a dozen Kansas City winters, and I still can&rsquo;t make myself use that lotion, because I can&rsquo;t get over the name.</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>

<p>Translation alone is not a solution. The translator must be proficient. In a previous position I was frequently asked how long it takes to learn a language. I was fighting the misconception that anyone who has taken two years of a language could translate. After failing to articulate why that was a misconception, I found a wonderful tool, thanks to the Foreign Language Institute and the Interagency Language Roundtable (ILR), who created a scale that is a set of descriptions of abilities to communicate in a language. One important aspect of this scale is that it is accurate when the evaluations are done by native speakers. It was originally developed by the United States Foreign Service Institute (FSI), and is still widely known as the FSI scale. It consists of descriptions of five levels of language proficiency.</p>

<ul>
<li>Level 1: Elementary</li>
<li>Level 2: Limited Working</li>
<li>Level 3: Professional Working</li>
<li>Level 4: Full Professional</li>
<li>Level 5: Native or Bilingual</li>
</ul>


<p>Then the scale estimates how long it takes to achieve that level of proficiency when a student is immersed learning the language at least six hours a day and at least five days per week. It then breaks down the languages by groups based on their difficulty:</p>

<p>&ldquo;Easy&rdquo; languages are French, German, Indonesian, Italian, Portuguese, Romanian, Spanish, and Swahili:</p>

<ul>
<li>8 weeks (240 hours) to achieve level 1/1+</li>
<li>16 weeks (480 hours) to achieve level 2</li>
<li>24 weeks (720 hours) to achieve level 2+</li>
</ul>


<p>&ldquo;Hard&rdquo; languages are divided into the following groups.</p>

<ul>
<li>Group 2: Bulgarian, Burmese, Greek, Hindi, Persian, Urdu.</li>
<li>Group 3: Amharic, Cambodian, Czech, Finnish, Hebrew, Hungarian, Lao, Polish, Russian, Serbo-Croatian, Thai, Turkish, Vietnamese.</li>
<li>Group 4: Arabic, Chinese, Japanese, Korean)</li>
</ul>


<p>To learn these languages, you must spend the following time:</p>

<ul>
<li>12 weeks (360 hours) to achieve level 1/1+</li>
<li>24 weeks (720 hours) to achieve level 1+ /2</li>
<li>44+ weeks (1320+ hours) to achieve level 2/2+</li>
</ul>


<p>Taking a language for two years (usually college or high-school) is simply not enough to achieve the appropriate level of proficiency needed to translate. Even native speakers are not effective at translation. Becoming proficient in a language is very challenging, and cultural aspects are important as well.</p>

<p>Additionally, brain activation patterns identified by the University of Turku in Finland show extensive activation of the brain during non-native language use, specifically, the left dorsolateral frontal cortex, which is associated with lexical search, semantic processing and verbal working memory. Brain activation patterns were clearly modulated by direction of translation, with more extensive activation during translation into the non-native language, which is often considered to a be more demanding task. These are not the same patterns used when speaking a language, though, as different brain connections need to exist.</p>

<p>Machine translation has become more effective in the last few years, but only language experts should leverage it as part of their toolset. Translating something into a language you don&rsquo;t understand is a recipe for disaster. Simply go to an online translation tool, put in a phrase, convert it to another language, then convert it back.  Chances are, the original does not match the twice-translated phrase.</p>

<p>If you are relying on professional translators, another common misconception is that translation can simply happen overnight. The truth is it CAN happen, just NOT well. A professional translator can usually translate about 2000 words per-day. If they are doing localization testing as well, you have to budget about twice the time for the regression test plans to be completed, as words will iteratively need to be changed as context is understood within the software.</p>

<p>Now that I have covered the most common misconceptions with internationalization, localization, and translation, the next portion of this blog will focus on practical tips.</p>

<p>As a developer, it is imperative that you understand your global strategy and what outcome the business is trying to accomplish. You don&rsquo;t want to invest a lot of development time making sure you can handle Right-To-Left languages or those that are double-byte if your business isn&rsquo;t planning on going to those markets.</p>

<p>Creating appropriate partnerships with language providers is key to successfully globalizing software, as they can help handle many aspects of the globalization process from translation to localization. Speaking to companies who are already globalizing their software is a good way to find good providers.</p>

<p>If you have to use free online tools to translate something internally (where the quality doesn&rsquo;t need to be high), make sure you understand the licensing of the tool. Some free tools will own your content once you run it through their translation engine.</p>

<p>Including internationalization as part of your development process is a key aspect to globalization success. This means it should be included in:</p>

<ul>
<li>Design, including user interface design (UX)</li>
<li>Estimates</li>
<li>Testing</li>
<li>Deployment</li>
</ul>


<p>Localization testing is a new step that should be included in your process, which requires language experts to be involved. From a development perspective, there are a lot of existing artifacts that can be leveraged in this process, such as regression and feature test plans. It is always helpful if those artifacts can be separated into those that have UI changes or not.</p>

<p>Localization testing will likely focus on language changes and impacts to the UI. A byproduct of localization testing is that other types of defects might surface. Having a good process so that bugs can be reported and tracked is key.</p>

<p>If you are just starting down the road of internationalization, be sure you don&rsquo;t reinvent the wheel on how to do it. Programming languages usually have well-documented libraries that can be used. If you are already internationalizing and working with a localization team, make sure you are commenting your code to provide clarification to the translators. Below is an example of a popular localization tool:</p>

<div align="center">
<img src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2017-07-11-you-may-not-be-a-polyglot-but-your-code-needs-to-be/polyglot.png">
</div>


<p>Once you have incorporated all the steps for localization into your process, it is important to understand that your text changes will now have financial impact as they will affect translations. Translation memories are commonly used by translators, and any change to the source text will trigger a new translation to be required.</p>

<p>Translation companies typically charge per word. The average cost per word in 2012 Common Sense Advisory&rsquo;s 2012 survey of more than 3,700 suppliers in 114 countries, using 220 language pairs, found that the average per-word rate for translation for the 30 most commonly used languages on the web is around 13.4 cents. The more impactful implication to your process is that text changes will trigger your localization testing cycle as it will be important to verify the new translations are correct in context.</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s discuss some quick principles that you should be able to apply regardless of what programming language you use.</p>

<p>Don&rsquo;t concatenate strings. Language order matters with translation. Instead of doing this:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='javascript'><span class='line'><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="nx">div</span> <span class="nx">style</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="s2">&quot;font-family: monospace&quot;</span><span class="o">&gt;</span><span class="kd">function</span> <span class="nx">getDescription</span><span class="p">()</span> <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="kd">var</span> <span class="nx">color</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nx">getColor</span><span class="p">();</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="kd">var</span> <span class="nx">element</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nx">getElement</span><span class="p">();</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="k">return</span> <span class="nx">color</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="s2">&quot; &quot;</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="nx">element</span><span class="p">;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="p">}</span><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="err">/div&gt;</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Do something like this:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='javascript'><span class='line'><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="nx">div</span> <span class="nx">style</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="s2">&quot;font-family: monospace&quot;</span><span class="o">&gt;</span><span class="kd">function</span> <span class="nx">getDescription</span><span class="p">()</span> <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="kd">var</span> <span class="nx">color</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nx">getColor</span><span class="p">();</span>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="kd">var</span> <span class="nx">element</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nx">getElement</span><span class="p">();</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">return</span> <span class="nx">getLocalizedString</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="s1">&#39;elementDescription&#39;</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="nx">color</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="nx">element</span><span class="p">);</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="p">}</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nx">elementDescription</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="p">{</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">}</span> <span class="p">{</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">}</span><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="err">/div&gt;</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Refraining from concatenating strings allows lthe localization professional to ensure that grammar is appropriately represented in the language. If you concatenate strings you will be forcing someone to say something like:</p>

<p>&ldquo;House Red&rdquo; instead of &ldquo;Red House.&rdquo;</p>

<p>Speaking of names, be mindful how you use them in an application. Build appropriate abstraction and flexibility. Names can cause headaches in localization because first names aren&rsquo;t always first, people can have multiple last names, and middle names might not be there at all.</p>

<p>I have a personal story about this. When I went to file my marriage license, we had a very interesting conversation with the clerk. He asked me what was my middle name. When I said that I don&rsquo;t have a middle name, he said the system had it as a required field. I suggested that he enter a space&hellip;after about 15 tense seconds he confirmed it had worked. This was in early 2000, and I hope things have changed, but since government moves at the speed of snails, I doubt it has.</p>

<p>My final tip to better handle localization is to always use the FULL locale, that is, both language and country code to allow for maximum flexibility and to budget more time than what you believe you will need for your project. This last tip sounds very lame, but experience has taught me that chances are you won&rsquo;t do it. Engineers tend to be very optimistic on their estimates, and generally fail to allocate sufficient time.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[ShipIt VIII Day: Spring 2017]]></title>
    <link href="http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/shipit-day-viii-spring-2017/"/>
    <updated>2017-05-17T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/shipit-day-viii-spring-2017</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2017-05-17-shipit-day-viii-spring-2017/pic0.png"></p>

<p>ShipIt Day VIII was held on April 20 and 21st. Seventeen teams made up of internal associates had just 24 hours to create something innovative, usable, and value-adding. This quarter&rsquo;s ShipIt Day was held at our new <a href="http://www.bizjournals.com/kansascity/news/2017/02/10/get-a-sneak-peek-inside-cerner-s-new-innovations.html">Innovations Campus</a> in the Link Conference Center. We were excited to get to utilize the space for this event. Another awesome addition to this quarter&rsquo;s ShipIt Day was our new game rooms. We hosted a Donkey Kong challenge and the winner (<a href="https://twitter.com/russ_starr">@russ_starr</a>) received a five-pound gummy bear!</p>

<div align="center">
  <table>
    <tr>
      <td><img src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2017-05-17-shipit-day-viii-spring-2017/pic1.png">
        <br />
        <sub>The start of a long day for participants!</sub>
      </td>
      <td><img src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2017-05-17-shipit-day-viii-spring-2017/pic3.png">
        <br />
        <sub>Donkey Kong.</sub>
      </td>
    </tr>
  </table>
</div>


<p>Participants were given loads of snacks, the most important being Monster Energy Drinks!</p>

<div align="center">
  <table>
    <tr>
      <td><img src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2017-05-17-shipit-day-viii-spring-2017/pic4.png"></td>
      <td><img src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2017-05-17-shipit-day-viii-spring-2017/pic5.png"></td>
    </tr>
  </table>
</div>


<p>After a long day of hard work, everyone was ready to eat extra big pizzas from Pizza 51. Eleven big pizza&rsquo;s and one hundred and ninety-six breadsticks were surprisingly enough to feed the hard working brains.</p>

<div align="center">
  <table>
    <tr>
      <td><img src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2017-05-17-shipit-day-viii-spring-2017/pic6.png"></td>
      <td><img src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2017-05-17-shipit-day-viii-spring-2017/pic7.png"></td>
    </tr>
  </table>
</div>


<p>After dinner, it was back to work for the teams. Later on in the evening, we played movies including Rogue One and MST3K. Participants also battled for the top Donkey Kong score.</p>

<div align="center">
  <img src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2017-05-17-shipit-day-viii-spring-2017/pic8.png">
  <br />
  <sub>Watching movies while working on projects.</sub>
</div>


<p>Friday, April 21st rolled around and by 9:00am the teams were getting antsy to present their projects. Since this was our first ShipIt Day at the new Innovations Campus, we were able to utilize the Assembly space.</p>

<div align="center">
  <img src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2017-05-17-shipit-day-viii-spring-2017/pic9.png">
  <br />
  <sub>Old school advertising for ShipIt Day Demo&#8217;s- chalk!</sub>
</div>




<div align="center">
  <img src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2017-05-17-shipit-day-viii-spring-2017/pic10.jpg">
  <br />
  <sub>Prize table</sub>
</div>


<p>ShipIt Day VIII brought to life some incredible projects. Team Freudian Ship, made up of Kate Young, Erin Dorpinghaus, Courtney Ground, Chris Farr and Sean Albery, took first place (and the golden keyboard!) with their project.</p>

<blockquote><p>The Intellectual Property (IP) Analytics team is tasked with managing a data warehouse. This includes ensuring that data updates take place in &ldquo;jobs.&rdquo; When a job fails it results in stale data and this can impact thousands of associates. This project took advantage of <a href="https://aws.amazon.com/">Amazon Web Services</a> by connecting tasks associated with managing the database to a voice command <a href="https://developer.amazon.com/alexa">Alexa</a> skill which results in the ability to manage the database from anywhere the user has an internet connection. To put it in perspective, the database admin will now be able to ensure that the database is up to date without even getting out of bed in the morning. A simple voice command to an <a href="https://www.amazon.com/All-New-Amazon-Echo-Dot-Add-Alexa-To-Any-Room/dp/B01DFKC2SO">Amazon Echo Dot</a> (which each of us won as a prize) will result in the restarting of failed jobs and even logging JIRA tickets to begin the troubleshooting process if needed.</p></blockquote>

<p>ShipIt Judge Dan Stocksick was impressed with the project, &ldquo;Great use of consumer products into our ecosystem.&rdquo;</p>

<div align="center">
  <img src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2017-05-17-shipit-day-viii-spring-2017/pic11.png">
  <br />
  <sub>Team Freudian Ship with the coveted Gold Keyboard!</sub>
</div>


<p>Second place went to team Flowalva (Wuchen Wang and Dhruv Patel).</p>

<blockquote><p>Our ShipIt project was a traffic visualization system for web services supporting Millennium. In this project we used Splunk API to collect the data from services and visualize the traffic between nodes in using <a href="https://github.com/Netflix/vizceral">Netflix&rsquo;s vizceral project.</a></p></blockquote>

<p>Judge Jason Heiting was impressed. &ldquo;Very neat visualizations.  Intuitive UI for navigation.&rdquo;</p>

<p>Last but not least, was third place winners, Flying Mongoose (Cihan Kaynak, Matt Stramel, Mahesh Acharya, Taylor Clay).</p>

<blockquote><p>We created a cross platform mobile app which can be used by a pharmacy technician while picking up and scanning medications at the pharmacy to refill <a href="https://www.cerner.com/solutions/automated-dispensing-cabinet">Cerner&rsquo;s RxStation</a> cabinets. Prior to this project, an RCP based desktop app was running in a PC mounted on a cart with an attached barcode scanner and label printer. This type of bulky setup was reducing the mobility of the technician.</p></blockquote>

<div align="center">
  <img src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2017-05-17-shipit-day-viii-spring-2017/pic12.png">
  <br />
  <sub>The Assembly was crowded with associates watching presentations.</sub>
</div>


<p>Part of the ShipIt Day fun is livestreaming the presentations and allowing our associates from all over to participate by voting for their favorite team name, favorite presentation and favorite project. The winners of the categories are as followed:</p>

<ul>
<li><p><strong>Favorite Presentation</strong>: <em>Sip It</em> &ndash; Patrick Gross, Adam Tibbs, Mario Perez, Robert Cornett, Trey Peek</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Favorite Team Name</strong>: <em>CHAPPiE</em> &ndash; Karthik Nimmagadda, Manidee Gattamaneni, Venkatesh Sridharan, Prasanth Chakka, Wendell Wolfe</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Favorite Project</strong>: <em>Freudian Ship</em> &ndash; Kate Young, Erin Dorpinghaus, Courtney Ground, Chris Farr, Sean Albery</p></li>
</ul>


<div align="center">
<img src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2017-05-17-shipit-day-viii-spring-2017/pic13.png">
  <br />
  <sub>People&#8217;s Choice Winners with the coveted cheeseballs!</sub>
</div>


<p>ShipIt continues to be a great way for associates to work on something they haven&rsquo;t had a chance to work on, build relationships within different organizations and most importantly, enjoy themselves. Ian Kottman, an engineer on the Population Health Genomics team, has participated in multiple ShipIt Days. The reason: &ldquo;I enjoy getting the time to create something that will make someone&rsquo;s life easier.&rdquo; Carlo Filipelli, system engineer, also agrees, adding on, &ldquo;ShipIt is great because it allows associates to work on interesting projects that they might not be able to get to during normal work hours. It fosters innovation and new ideas that would typically get overlooked in our busy day to day jobs. It is also a conducive environment for learning, collaboration, and having some fun!&rdquo;</p>

<p>Thank you to all our participants and a special thank you to judges Jason Heiting, Justin Morrison, Dwight Sloan and Dan Stocksick.</p>

<p>Mark your calendars: ShipIt Day IX will be held in July 2017. If you are interested in learning more about other ShipIt Days, see these earlier posts:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/shipit-vii-day-winter-2016/">ShipIt Day VII Winter 2016</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=iqTp0dmLgUk">ShipIt Day Winter 2016 Highlight Reel</a></li>
<li><a href="http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/fall-2016-shipit-day/">ShipIt Day Fall 2016</a></li>
<li><a href="http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/spring-2016-shipit-day/">ShipIt Day Spring 2016</a></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Influyendo en Una Generación De Jovencitas De Habla Hispana]]></title>
    <link href="http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/influyendo-en-una-generacion-de-jovencitas-de-habla-hispana/"/>
    <updated>2017-05-11T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/influyendo-en-una-generacion-de-jovencitas-de-habla-hispana</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Cuando no están trabajando, Denisse Osorio de Large, Directora de Cerner en Desarrollo de Salud Poblacional y Steven Large, Director sénior de Desarrollo de IP, quienes están casados, tienen como pasión crear una generación joven motivada por la tecnología y mostrarle a la misma el amplio mundo de oportunidades existentes en el desarrollo de software. Además de dar su tiempo como voluntarios en la comunidad promotora del área de ciencias, tecnología, ingeniería y matemáticas (STEM), contribuyen a organizar la conferencia de desarrollo de Cerner (DevCon) y realizan presentaciones en conferencias, Denisse y Steven disfrutan trabajar con niños de la comunidad de habla hispana.</p>

<p>El año pasado, Denisse, originaria de Colombia y cuya lengua materna es el español, y Steven, quién habla español, organizaron dos eventos de codificación ofrecidos específicamente a familias de habla hispana en colaboración con la agrupación <em>Girl Scouts</em>, niñas exploradoras. Los objetivos de estos eventos de &ldquo;Pastelitos y Programación&rdquo;, <em>Coding and Cupcakes</em>, consistieron en ofrecer un entorno seguro e incluyente para que las chicas llevaran a cabo actividades de programación, desarrollaran capacidades de liderazgo y un gusto por la resolución de problemas mediante la codificación. Las jóvenes disfrutaron la satisfacción que brinda resolver los desafíos de codificación de code.org y de juegos como Laberintos de <em>Angry Birds</em>. En el juego, usando conceptos de programación, las chicas se divirtieron al encontrar la forma de guiar a las aves que, atravesando un laberinto, debían llegar a los cerdos (ver video del evento a continuación).</p>

<div align="center">
<iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/dCxSAplU5og?ecver=2" width="480" height="360" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div>


<p>Como reconocimiento por su pasión por desarrollar a futuros innovadores en STEM, las <em>Girl Scouts</em>, honraron a Denisse y a Steven Large por conducir el evento Pastelitos y Programación, <em>Coding and Cupcakes</em> que se llevó a cabo en Cerner. El Premio de Innovador de las <em>Girl Scouts</em>, reconoce a los voluntarios que perciben un problema y desarrollan una solución innovadora para fomentar las actividades de escultismo para las chicas, <em>Girl Scouting</em>. Estos eventos familiares contribuyen a favorecer la comunicación entre padres e hijas al participar en eventos de <em>Girl Scouts</em>. Por su pasión y dedicación como voluntarios, Denisse y Steven alientan a cada vez más niñas a participar en las actividades de STEM. ¡Enhorabuena, Denisse y Steven!</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2017-05-11-influencing-the-young-spanish-seaking-female-generation/denisse-steven-award.jpg" title="Denisse and Steven" ></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Influencing the Young, Spanish-speaking Female Generation]]></title>
    <link href="http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/influencing-the-young-spanish-seaking-female-generation/"/>
    <updated>2017-05-11T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/influencing-the-young-spanish-seaking-female-generation</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Outside of work, married couple Denisse Osorio de Large, a Cerner Director in Population Health Development, and Steven Large, a Cerner Senior Director in IP Development, are passionate about creating a younger generation that is passionate about technology and introducing them to the vast world of opportunities in software development. In addition to volunteering in the STEM community, helping organize Cerner’s development conference (DevCon), and speaking at conferences, Denisse and Steven enjoy working with children in the spanish-speaking community.</p>

<p>Last year, Denisse (who is Colombian and a spanish-speaking native) and Steven (who is fluent in spanish) hosted two coding events specifically catered to spanish speaking families in partnership with Girl Scouts. The goals of these events, “Pastelitos y Programación” (“Coding and Cupcakes”), were to provide a safe and inclusive environment for girls to program, grow leadership abilities, and love solving problems with code. Girls enjoyed completing coding challenges from code.org and playing Labyrinths for Angry Birds. In the game, the girls had fun figuring out how to guide birds through a labyrinth to the pigs (see more about the event in the video below) using programming concepts.</p>

<div align="center">
<iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/dCxSAplU5og?ecver=2" width="480" height="360" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div>


<p>In recognition of their passion for developing future innovators in STEM, Girl Scouts honored Denisse and Steven Large for their work in hosting the Pastelitos y Programación (Coding and Cupcakes) at Cerner. The Girl Scouts Innovator Award recognizes volunteers who saw a problem and developed an innovative solution to further Girl Scouting. These family events help bridge the communication gap between parents and girls when it comes to participating in Girl Scout events. With their passion and dedication for volunteering in the community, Denisse and Steven are encouraging more girls to become involved with STEM activities. Congratulations, Denisse and Steven!</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2017-05-11-influencing-the-young-spanish-seaking-female-generation/denisse-steven-award.jpg" title="Denisse and Steven" ></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[One Cerner Style Icons: The Future of Icons at Cerner]]></title>
    <link href="http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/one-cerner-style-icons/"/>
    <updated>2017-04-06T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/one-cerner-style-icons</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One Cerner Style Icons (OCS Icons) are foundational UI elements required to produce a cohesive and consistent User Experience for Cerner Solutions. OCS Icons consist of a comprehensive icon library of platform agnostic assets which can be easily consumed by development teams.</p>

<h3>Why?</h3>

<p>The primary goal of this effort to elevate every aspect of the UI to create the best possible user experience.  In order to do that, it is imperative to develop a system composed of strong design patterns and well-founded user research.  By creating a single repository of platform agnostic icons, we are able to better manage icons and create a framework that makes consuming icons easier and more efficient.  By reducing the number of separate libraries, styles and formats, we ease the burden on implementation for developers.  In addition, we dramatically reduce the amount of effort needed to maintain a host of different asset libraries while producing a higher quality product.  Going open source also facilitates a more seamless process when icons need updated or when styles change and evolve.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2017-04-06-one-cerner-style-icons/one-cerner-style-why.png" title="Why" ></p>

<h3>What?</h3>

<p>OCS Icons are the core iconographic communication vehicle between the functional software and the UI.  The icons are designed on the foundation of a strict icon language consisting of core design principles and uniform style.   Proper implementation requires consumers to be on a code guide and obtain assets by referencing codified Scalable Vector Graphics.  To ensure consistent implementation, icon packages are versioned and carefully managed.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2017-04-06-one-cerner-style-icons/one-cerner-style-what.png" title="What" ></p>

<h3>Who?</h3>

<p>The individuals responsible for One Cerner Style Icons are: James Bray, Seth Claybrook, Brett Jankord, Will Reynolds and Bradley Scott.</p>

<h4>Repository Link</h4>

<p><a href="https://github.com/cerner/one-cerner-style-icons">https://github.com/cerner/one-cerner-style-icons</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Version Databag - a Chef Release Process]]></title>
    <link href="http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/version-databag---a-chef-release-process/"/>
    <updated>2017-04-04T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/version-databag&#8212;a-chef-release-process</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>At Cerner, we use <a href="https://www.chef.io/">Chef</a>. In fact, we&rsquo;re heavily ingrained with Chef in our <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Software_configuration_management">configuration management practices</a>. We deploy services from <a href="http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/deploying-web-services-with-apache-tomcat-and-chef/">Tomcat</a> to <a href="http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/automated-deployment-with-apache-kafka/">Kafka</a> with Chef. Even the first open source project we announced was <a href="http://engineering.cerner.com/2014/01/cerner-and-open-source/">a tool for Chef</a>!</p>

<p>With all of this integration with Chef, we need a simple way to manage all of those versions. This is where the <a href="https://supermarket.chef.io/cookbooks/version_databag">Version Databag cookbook</a> comes in. At a high level, this cookbook allows us to define our versions in a centralized data bag (grouped under conceptual units) and populates the corresponding node attributes required with those versions at runtime. This significantly reduces the effort involved in finding, updating, and maintaining the various versions of things that we have across our Chef configuration.</p>

<p>Because we found it so useful, we decided to open source it! We encourage you to try it and manage Chef versions with it for easier configuration management practices. If you feel that it could be further improved, <a href="https://github.com/cerner/version_databag/issues">let us know</a> (or better yet, submit the improvement yourself!). We&rsquo;re welcome to take enhancements and feedback to improve our processes.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Engineers on the Road for SMART and FHIR (CHC 2016)]]></title>
    <link href="http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/engineers-on-the-road-for-smart-and-fhir/"/>
    <updated>2017-03-24T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/engineers-on-the-road-for-smart-and-fhir</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Over the past few years, Cerner has been developing a standards-based platform on top of our Cerner Millennium® EHR.  Rather than roll our own API, we’ve been using the <a href="http://hl7.org/fhir/overview-dev.html">HL7® FHIR® standard</a>.  For app integration, we’ve been using the <a href="http://docs.smarthealthit.org/">SMART® on FHIR specification</a>.  If you’re not immediately familiar with those acronyms, you’re definitely not alone.</p>

<p>As we were developing the services, we were also fielding questions from 3rd party developers, answering a lot of questions internally, and trying to keep up with the specifications themselves. We knew that we would need to help provide education around our ecosystem, our implementation of the FHIR and SMART standards to developers since the standards are new and evolving.</p>

<p>This need will become much more pressing because <a href="https://www.healthit.gov/providers-professionals/how-attain-meaningful-use">Meaningful Use 3</a> will trigger deployment of our implementations out to most of our Millennium EHRs.  <a href="https://www.cdc.gov/ehrmeaningfuluse/introduction.html">Meaningful Use</a> introduces requirements from the Centers for Medicare and Medicaid (CMS) to modernize the US healthcare infrastructure.  This is nothing new, but we’ve been hard at work to support stage 3, which includes the requirement for patients to access their data via an API.  In order to attest, most of our clients will then require our implementation of the FHIR API.</p>

<p>This past November offered up two exciting opportunities to provide hands-on instruction and support, which we’ll cover in separate posts.  In this first post, we want to highlight the work we did at our annual <a href="https://blogs.cerner.com/blog/CHC16-Summary-UK/">Cerner Health Conference</a>.  We decided that this year’s event would be a great opportunity to offer a small Code Learning Lab &ndash; providing education for some of the APIs that Cerner has available.</p>

<p>The Code Learning Lab was run from November 14th &ndash; 17th in Kansas City with our annual CHC conference. The goal: give developers a hands-on training session with the different APIs that are part of the Cerner Open Developer Experience (<em>code</em>). One of the tracks covered SMART and FHIR specifically, while another went over some of the APIs available with our HealtheIntent and HealtheLife platforms.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2017-03-24-engineers-on-the-road-for-smart-and-fhir/smart-and-fhir-01.jpg"></p>

<p>We saw participation from many of our clients and partners, from both the US and Canada. Over the four days, the lab was in the format of an overview or &ldquo;lecture&rdquo; followed by a longer hands-on lab to put what participants were learning to use. During the labs, our engineers would walk around to check on how everyone was doing, answer questions, and help troubleshoot.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2017-03-24-engineers-on-the-road-for-smart-and-fhir/smart-and-fhir-02.jpg"></p>

<p>We received a lot of comments and excitement from everyone participating around the fact that our engineering team itself was involved in the learning lab. It was also very exciting for the engineering team to watch everyone try out our newer developer tools, read our documentation, and then put it to practice. Not only were the participants able to actually see the data coming back, but there were a lot of conversations that occurred that will help us improve the class (and our tooling) in the future to make the event better. In the end, it was a great experience for everyone involved!</p>

<p>If you’re interested, you can check out some of the presentations and labs that were created for the learning lab here: <a href="https://github.com/cerner/ignite-learning-lab">https://github.com/cerner/ignite-learning-lab</a> and our SMART tutorial: <a href="http://engineering.cerner.com/smart-on-fhir-tutorial/#prerequisites">http://engineering.cerner.com/smart-on-fhir-tutorial/#prerequisites</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[One Cerner Associate's Contributions in the Tech Industry]]></title>
    <link href="http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/micah-whitacre-recognition-blog/"/>
    <updated>2017-03-16T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/micah-whitacre-recognition-blog</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>Background:</h3>

<p>Micah is currently a software architect in Population Health Development in Healthe Intent Development at Cerner. In 2013, Micah Whitacre received committer status on the <a href="https://crunch.apache.org/">Apache Crunch</a> project, and is now a Project Management Committee (PMC) member of the project.</p>

<h3>How has Cerner been been involved in Apache Crunch?</h3>

<p>In 2012 and 2013, Cerner started using this project within several solutions. We also wanted to give back to the community and decided to invest time in helping answer questions and concerns, and overall project needs. We wanted to get involved in small community like <a href="https://crunch.apache.org/">Apache Crunch</a> since it brought great value to our Cerner solutions.</p>

<h3>What does it mean to be receive committer status on Open Source?</h3>

<p>In 2013, I was selected as a committer on <a href="https://crunch.apache.org/">Apache Crunch</a>. In reference to the technical aspect, Apache projects have some form of criteria for when to accept a committer to a project. Election to being a committer is the result of consistent and high quality contributions to the project, through documentation, code, or helping to build the overall community.</p>

<p>Being selected as a committer was an unexpected honor. It&rsquo;s also an additional responsibility for my involvement with the project. I closely watch for questions and make enhancements and functionality code changes. There are fourteen other committers on the project as well.</p>

<h3>What does it mean to be an Apache Crunch PMC?</h3>

<p>After being a committer for over a year, I was selected as a PMC of <a href="https://crunch.apache.org/">Apache Crunch</a>. The goal of a PMC is to set the pace and the direction of the community, as well as facilitate how the community is interacting. PMCs help drive releases and help grow the committee. Some of my other responsibilities also include participating in discussions about voting people into the community, new releases of code, and which functionalities need to get fixed.</p>

<h3>What are your favorite parts about being a committer?</h3>

<p>One of the coolest parts about being a committer is making new connections with larger tech community. It forces you to build new relationships and talk to people you may have not spoken to before. It&rsquo;s cool being able to meet new people who don&rsquo;t work at the company you&rsquo;re working for. I also enjoy being able to look at the project as a whole and figure out the right way to solve something, rather than solving it right now.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve also spoken at ApacheCon twice on <a href="https://crunch.apache.org/">Apache Crunch</a>, which have been awesome opportunities.</p>

<h3>How else are you involved in the tech industry?</h3>

<p>I also like to be involved in our development culture at Cerner, helping improve our internal community and increasing awareness of Cerner in the industry.  I&rsquo;ve been a member of the planning committee and have spoken at our internal conference, DevCon, given internal tech talks at Cerner, and have also spoken at industry conferences like Kafka Summit 2016 and Midwest.io 2014. I&rsquo;ve also written an Engineering Health blog (Scaling People with <a href="https://crunch.apache.org/">Apache Crunch</a>). I am an open source reviewer for Cerner projects, helping review and provide feedback on Cerner open source projects prior to them being published.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Automated Deployment With Apache Kafka]]></title>
    <link href="http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/automated-deployment-with-apache-kafka/"/>
    <updated>2017-02-16T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/automated-deployment-with-apache-kafka</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It&rsquo;s likely not a surprise that Cerner would use <a href="http://kafka.apache.org/">Apache Kafka</a>
as we have used a number of related technologies like <a href="http://engineering.cerner.com/2013/02/composable-mapreduce-with-hadoop-and-crunch/">Apache Hadoop</a>
along with its Map/Reduce, HDFS and even <a href="http://engineering.cerner.com/2013/02/near-real-time-processing-over-hadoop-and-hbase/">Apache HBase</a>.
Our team first started using Apache Kafka in 2014
when Kafka 0.8 first came out. Since then we&rsquo;ve expanded to using Kafka for a
number of different use cases
(<a href="http://blog.cloudera.com/blog/2014/11/how-cerner-uses-cdh-with-apache-kafka/">1</a>, <a href="https://www.confluent.io/kafka-summit-2016-users-ingesting-complex-healthcare-data-with-apache-kafka">2</a>)
and it has become a core piece of Cerner&rsquo;s infrastructure.</p>

<p>Just like the <a href="http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/deploying-web-services-with-apache-tomcat-and-chef/">applications we create</a>,
we also needed to automate the deployment of Kafka to handle the ever growing
amount of operations work and to ensure a high level of consistency with our
environments. <a href="https://www.chef.io/chef/">Chef</a> was an obvious choice for us since
its been our deployment tool of choice for the last few years. We quickly put together a
<a href="https://github.com/cerner/cerner_kafka">cookbook</a> to help us automate the
deployment of the many Kafka clusters here at Cerner. We have
<a href="https://github.com/cerner/cerner_kafka/blob/master/CHANGELOG.md">continued to support and use this cookbook</a>
after open-sourcing it upgrading it to handle newer versions of Kafka (0.9, 0.10),
handle Kerberos authentication, and <a href="https://github.com/cerner/cerner_kafka/issues?q=is%3Aissue%20is%3Aclosed%20">many other improvements</a>.</p>

<p>If you use Apache Kafka, feel free to <a href="https://github.com/cerner/cerner_kafka">try it out</a>
and let us know how it works for you.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Beadledom - Simple Java Framework for Building REST APIs]]></title>
    <link href="http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/beadledom-simple-java-framework-for-building-rest-apis/"/>
    <updated>2017-02-15T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/beadledom-simple-java-framework-for-building-rest-apis</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Beadledom is a framework for building Java based web services. It bundles several open sourced components required for building JAX-RS services.</p>

<h3>Why?</h3>

<p>HealtheIntent, Cerner’s population health management platform, started 3.5 years ago. We went through the process of investigating different technologies for the platform. We decided on using Java for building  services and arrived on a set of libraries that we believed work well together.</p>

<p>The long history of Java has led to an ocean of libraries that are available to Java developers. Picking up the right set of tools is very important to get the job done the right way. The trickiest part is to know what  “the right set of tools” are. This is only the first of many tough decisions that a developer makes during the lifecycle of a project.</p>

<p>If choosing the libraries for a project is a game, then getting them all to play well together is a whole new game. Beadledom not only brings all the awesome java libraries together but also binds them well, making the developer&rsquo;s life easy. It gives a good head start to the developer by letting them start from a strong foundation.</p>

<p>At Cerner we understand how important and tedious these decisions are and we always want to contribute back to the community. So we open sourced Beadledom because it  helped us develop our platform quickly and consistently. We hope that others in the community can also leverage its power.</p>

<h3>What?</h3>

<p>Beadledom uses several open source projects that are widely used and well maintained. Below is a list of a few of the major components that Beadledom uses.</p>

<p>Guice for  gluing  and bootstrapping components;
Jackson for JSON serialization/deserialization;
Resteasy for JAX-RS implementation;
Stagemonitor for Monitoring and metrics;
Swagger for API Documentation;
Apache Commons-Configuration for handling different types of configurations consistently.
Where?
You can find the source code on GitHub.  Please find our documentation at <a href="http://engineering.cerner.com/beadledom/.">http://engineering.cerner.com/beadledom/.</a></p>

<h3>Who?</h3>

<p>Below are the core developers of Beadledom:
John Leacox
Sundeep Paruvu
Nimesh Subramanian
Brian van de Boogaard
Supriya Lal
Here is the complete list of contributors who made Beadledom awesome.</p>

<h3>Cookie Cake Time!</h3>

<p>Cerner takes pride in our open source contributions. When teams contribute to the community Cerner rewards them with a cake. Here is the cookie cake for Beadledom.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2017-02-15-beadledom-simple-java-framework-for-building-rest-apis/beadledom-01.png" title="Beadledom Cookie Cake" ></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[ShipIt VII Day: Winter 2016]]></title>
    <link href="http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/shipit-vii-day-winter-2016/"/>
    <updated>2017-01-18T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/shipit-vii-day-winter-2016</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Cerner’s 7th ShipIt Day took place on December 8th and 9th. ShipIt is a 24-hour hackathon with the
goal of building something awesome, usable, and value-adding within a single day.  The event was
hosted at our DevCenter in the Realization Campus, a large open space that hosts our DevAcademy (to
learn more about our DevAcademy, check out this
<a href="http://engineering.cerner.com/2013/08/devacademy/">earlier post</a>).  We had 18 teams made up of
associates from different Cerner organizations. The DevCenter was stocked with all kinds of snacks,
which of course included a traditional drink: Monster Energy. Participants worked hard all day long
and when dinner came around they were ready to dig in. Good thing we ordered 8 twenty-six inch
pizzas and 40 breadsticks from a local Kansas City favorite, <a href="http://www.pizza51.com/">Pizza 51</a>.
Look how big these pizzas were!</p>

<div align="center">
<table>
  <tr>
    <td><img src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2017-01-18-shipit-vii-day-winter-2016/shipit-01.jpg"></td>
    <td><img src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2017-01-18-shipit-vii-day-winter-2016/shipit-03.jpg"></td>
  </tr>
</table>
</div>


<p>It was predicted we hit a record in Kansas City for the most pizza in an elevator at this time, but
we were not able to get an official count!</p>

<div style="float:left;" >
<img src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2017-01-18-shipit-vii-day-winter-2016/shipit-04.png">
</div>


<p>When getting pizzas of this size, there was a significant amount to fuel the innovation that was
happening. To break it down:</p>

<p>A = πr<sup>2</sup> = π x 132 ≈ 530.93 square inches = 3.68 square feet x 8 = 29.44 square feet of pizza. Which
is larger than a twin bed size of solid pizza, and slightly smaller than a queen bed. A perfect
amount for a ShipIt event! Teams took a break from their work throughout the evening by playing
Nintendo and cheering on the <a href="http://www.chiefs.com/">Chiefs</a>!</p>

<div align="center">
<table>
  <tr>
    <td><img src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2017-01-18-shipit-vii-day-winter-2016/shipit-00.jpg"></td>
    <td><img src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2017-01-18-shipit-vii-day-winter-2016/shipit-07.jpg"></td>
  </tr>
</table>
</div>


<p>There were some impressive projects that came out of ShipIt Day VII. <em>Team GLADoS</em>, made up of Kyle
Harper, Sarah Harper, Snehit Gajjar, and Andy Quangvan took first place, and the coveted Golden
Keyboard, with their impressive idea.</p>

<blockquote><p>This ShipIt, we created a new <a href="https://developer.amazon.com/alexa">Alexa skill</a> called Scribe.
With our new skill we integrated the
<a href="https://www.amazon.com/All-New-Echo-Dot-2nd-Generation/dp/B01DFKC2SO/ref=cp_aucc_ods">Amazon Echo and Echo Dot</a>
smart speakers with <a href="https://code.cerner.com/">Cerner&rsquo;s FHIR implementation</a>. This integration allows
a patient or care provider to access clinical data by simply speaking to the Echo.</p></blockquote>

<p>Judge Sean Griffin was impressed. &ldquo;Really cool, awesome idea. Great innovation! The applicability
towards data entry could definitely be useful.&rdquo;</p>

<div align="center">
<img src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2017-01-18-shipit-vii-day-winter-2016/shipit-08.jpg">
<sub>Team GLADos with the Golden Keyboard</sub>
</div>


<p>Second place went to <em>Team Trogdor</em> (Kyle Lipke, Derek Dobler, Nikki Justice, Mike Harrison,
and Nimesh Subramanain).</p>

<blockquote><p>Troubleshooting errors or misconfigurations in Millennium OAuth can be time consuming. Missing
information or misconfiguration can lead to hours of checking various sources of information. This
web page tool allows us to perform a quick and accurate diagnostic check for what pieces are
available and not available. Built with Ruby on <a href="http://www.sinatrarb.com/">Sinatra framework</a>.
Made to allow for easy additions to various checks that ETS (Emerging Technology Services group)
needs to do.</p></blockquote>

<p>Judge Jim Dwyer noted, &ldquo;This is a great tool to help drive down operational costs and reduce TCO.&rdquo;</p>

<div align="center">
<img src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2017-01-18-shipit-vii-day-winter-2016/shipit-05.jpg">
<sub>Team Trogdor</sub>
</div>


<p>Third place winners, <em>Team 402 Cheeseballs Required</em> (Andy Nelson, Venkatesh Sridharan, Ian Kottman,
Nate Schile, and Anthony Ross) created an application for tracking running mileage for the
<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=w18fgEcMi7w">Healthe Fitness Center</a>.</p>

<blockquote><p>Our goal was to make the process of submitting running milestones for the Cerner Running Club
easier. The current process involved writing down how far you ran in a binder, and then one of the
gym staff checking that binder occasionally to see when you accomplished a milestone so they could
send a prize. We decided to make a web application that would integrate with Strava that would
simplify tracking how far you&rsquo;ve run. <a href="https://www.strava.com/">Strava</a> is a platform that
aggregates data from multiple fitness apps, such as <a href="https://www.fitbit.com/">Fitbit</a> and
<a href="https://buy.garmin.com/en-US/US/cIntoSports-cRunning-p1.html">Garmin</a>.
We used the <a href="https://strava.github.io/api/">Strava API</a> to pull a person&rsquo;s running data so
we could total up their mileage, regardless of what fitness tracker they used. In order to
integrate with Strava&rsquo;s public API we had to have an externally facing application. We decided to
use an <a href="https://aws.amazon.com/ec2/">Amazon EC2</a> instance to do this, since it was easy and cheap.
We used <a href="http://rubyonrails.org/">Rails</a> to create our web app since that was the web framework
we had the most experience in. First, we would ask a person to connect to their Strava account,
and then we pulled their running data and totaled up their mileage. If a person had reached a
milestone they could press a button to send an email to the gym staff that included their
running log, their total mileage, and what milestones they had achieved.</p></blockquote>

<div align="center">
<img class="center" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2017-01-18-shipit-vii-day-winter-2016/shipit-06.jpg">
<sub>Team 402 Cheeseballs Required</sub>
</div>


<p>By Friday at 10 a.m. the participants were ready to present (for the most part). Cerner associates
from different campuses watched the event via livestream and voted for People’s choice. Those
results are as followed&hellip;</p>

<p><strong>Favorite team name</strong>: <em>I Shipped My Pants</em> &ndash; Brandon Inman and Steven Goldberg</p>

<blockquote><p>Improvements made to the existing
<a href="http://techblog.netflix.com/2016/08/vizceral-open-source.html">Vizceral-based implementation</a>
of HealtheIntent Intuition
Engineering.  Improvements made by the team included features to make it easier to switch between
streaming and batch processing, more timely updates of data, and several cosmetic features to
improve user experience and differentiate the tool from other Vizceral apps.  Voice activation was
added as a &ldquo;fun&rdquo; feature.</p></blockquote>

<p><strong>Favorite Presentation</strong>: <em>Guys on FHIR</em> &ndash; Bhaumik Aniruddha, Bhagat Parthiv, Vetri Selvi Vairamutha,
Neil Pfeiffer, Sai Praveen Gampa</p>

<blockquote><p>Our ShipIt project was a NICU SMART App, intended for the NICU unit. The app will be used to get a
live video of the baby inside an incubator alongside the vitals of the baby. This will prevent
anyone from disturbing the sleeping pattern of the newborn. The live feedback can also be viewed
by the parents which will ease the mental tension. The future scope of this project is to hook up
with an app, which can read the facial expression of the baby.</p></blockquote>

<p><strong>Best Project</strong>: <em>RSA (Readmission Security Admission)</em> &ndash; Kristopher Williams, Karthik Nimmagadda, Sai
Inampudi</p>

<blockquote><p>Our project was to create an intuitive dashboard that lets the user visualize the network traffic
for readmission solution&rsquo;s services for a given time period (hour/day/week/month currently). This
dashboard will allow the user to easily and quickly identify abnormal behavior (e.g. service goes
down, or service experiencing a lot of errors) and is designed in such a way as to return results
extremely fast for longer time spans, compared to ad-hoc splunk queries.</p></blockquote>

<div align="center">
<img src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2017-01-18-shipit-vii-day-winter-2016/shipit-02.jpg">
<sub>People’s Choice Winners</sub>
</div>


<p>ShipIt Day continues to be a great way for Cerner associates to work on projects they don’t normally
have time for, meet people in different organizations and learn something new. Participant
Kristopher Williams said:</p>

<blockquote><p>My favorite part of ShipIt Day was being able to work on something entirely different, and in my
case, with a different group of people. Just a fresh change of pace.</p></blockquote>

<p>Thank you to all our participants and a special thanks to our judges Jenni Syed
(<a href="https://twitter.com/JenniSyed">@JenniSyed</a>), Yegor Hanov, Sean Griffin
(<a href="https://twitter.com/trenchguinea">@trenchguinea</a>), and Jim Dwyer
(<a href="https://twitter.com/episodicdata">@episodicdata</a>).</p>

<p>Check out some additional highlights of our event in this video:</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/iqTp0dmLgUk" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>


<p>If you are interested in reading more about previous ShipIt Day events, see these earlier posts:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/fall-2016-shipit-day/">Fall 2016 ShipIt Day</a></li>
<li><a href="http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/spring-2016-shipit-day/">Spring 2016 ShipIt Day</a></li>
<li><a href="http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/shipit-hackathon-mplus/">ShipIt &ndash; 24-hour hackathon for Millennium+ Platform Dev</a></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Alan and Grace: An Origin Story]]></title>
    <link href="http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/alan-and-grace-an-origin-story/"/>
    <updated>2016-11-23T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/alan-and-grace-an-origin-story</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2016-11-23-alan-and-grace-an-origin-story/alan-grace.png" title="Alan and Grace" ></p>

<p>Meet Alan and Grace. These lighthearted, 8-bit characters were nominated in
early 2014 to become the iconic mascots of Engineering at Cerner. Have you ever
wondered who these 80’s video gaming inspired characters on our Engineering
t-shirts are? Why were they chosen as mascots? What do they represent? The
countless hours spent pondering these questions will be no more. Pull up a
chair as we dive into the mystery behind the dynamic duo known as Alan and
Grace.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2016-11-23-alan-and-grace-an-origin-story/shirt-laptop.png" title="Laptop and t-shirt" ></p>

<p>Believe it or not, the enjoyable pair highlighted on a myriad of our engineering
materials were named after two real life innovators: Alan Turing and Grace
Hopper. Alan and Grace were visionaries in their time, championing advances
that shaped the computer science innovations of today. These icons were chosen
based on their contributions to computer science and the moxie they showed while
doing it.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2016-11-23-alan-and-grace-an-origin-story/alan-8bit.png" title="Alan" ></p>

<p>Alan, our spiky haired friend who embodies an 80’s meets hipster vibe, is named
after the English mathematician Alan Mathison Turing (1912-1954). Turing is
known to some as the father of theoretical computer science and artificial
intelligence. Alan had an unquenchable mind and was in constant pursuit of
knowledge, devoting his life to a vocation in science and mathematics as a
computer scientist, mathematician, logician, cryptanalyst, and theoretical
biologist. Among his many contributions is the notable Alan Turing Enigma
machine. The machine was used to help break the enigma code used in German
naval communications during World War II. The concept of the Turing Enigma
machine has become the foundation of the modern theory of computation and
computability. Alan and his Enigma machine have received some recent fame as
featured in the Imitation Game, a 2014 American historical drama-thriller
loosely based on the biography Alan Turing: The Enigma. It can be argued that
computer science would not be what it is today without the mathematical
imagination of Alan Turing. Cue the mic drop now.</p>

<div align="center">
<img class="left" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2016-11-23-alan-and-grace-an-origin-story/alan-turing.jpg" title="Alan" >
<img class="right" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2016-11-23-alan-and-grace-an-origin-story/turing-machine.jpg" title="Turing Machine" >

<sub>Sources: <a href="http://www.alanturing.net/turing_archive/graphics/photos%20of%20Turing/pages/alan1_psd.htm">alanturing.net</a>, <a href="http://worldnews.nbcnews.com/_news/2013/12/23/22025978-queen-pardons-computing-giant-alan-turing-59-years-after-his-suicide">nbcnews.com</a></sub>
</div>


<hr />

<p><img class="center" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2016-11-23-alan-and-grace-an-origin-story/grace-8bit.png" title="Grace" ></p>

<p>Cerner Engineering’s jovial female mascot appears as if she’s ready to take on
the world. The fearless spirit of the mascot encompases the nature of its muse
for whom she was named, Grace Brewster Murray Hopper (1906-1992). Grace Hopper
was an American mathematician, computer programmer, military leader, and a woman
clearly ahead of her time. Grace received a Ph.D. in mathematics, one of the
first women to earn this level of education. Grace’s path to computer science
began while serving in the U.S. Naval Reserve as one of the first to program the
Harvard Mark I computer. Grace went on to create the first compiler for
computer languages leading to COBOL, a widely adapted language that would be
used around the world. But Grace wasn’t finished yet. At the age of 60, she
was recalled to active duty where she standardized communication between
different computer languages. When Grace retired at the age of 79 as a rear
admiral, she was the oldest serving officer in the service. In 1991, Grace was
the first women awarded the National Medal of Technology. Throughout her life,
Grace encouraged young people to learn how to program. Grace’s legacy lives on
through the Grace Murray Hopper Award, the Grace Hopper Celebration of Women in
Computing Conference, the University of Missouri’s computer museum “Grace’s
Place”, and now Cerner’s Engineering mascot. Grace continues to serve as an
inspiration to women in tech everywhere. Was there any other choice?</p>

<div align="center">
<img class="left" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2016-11-23-alan-and-grace-an-origin-story/grace-hopper.jpg" title="Grace Hopper" >
<img class="right" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2016-11-23-alan-and-grace-an-origin-story/grace-hopper-2.jpg" title="Grace Hopper" >

<sub>Sources: <a href="http://www.womenatworkmuseum.org/envision-engineering.html">womenatworkmuseum.org</a>, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grace_Hopper">wikipedia.org</a></sub>
</div>


<p>Alan and Grace represent a beacon of inspiration, providing icons that
encapsulate and promote a culture of innovation, forward thinking, and just
plain fun. The creation of mascots Alan and Grace has been a big win for the
passionate Cerner engineers dedicated to fostering Cerner’s Engineering culture.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2016-11-23-alan-and-grace-an-origin-story/alan-grace-2.png" title="Alan and Grace" ></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Clara Rules Joins Cerner's Open Source]]></title>
    <link href="http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/clara-rules-joins-cerner-open-source/"/>
    <updated>2016-11-11T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/clara-rules-joins-cerner-open-source</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Sometimes a small experiment on the side can grow into something valuable. We at Cerner have long
used forward-chaining rules engines to express and execute clinical knowledge, but we’ve also had to
extend or work around the capabilities of such engines. Engines targeting business users just
weren’t expressive enough to model some of our logic. To meet this need we are making Clara Rules an
open source project driven by Cerner Engineering.</p>

<p>Clara took an unusual path, starting as a minimal implementation of the
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rete_algorithm">Rete algorithm</a> to help my
own understanding. After sharing this with others at Cerner, we started to see an opportunity to
gain the modularity and reasoning advantages of a rules engine, while preserving the expressiveness
and power of a modern programming language. We wanted to combine the best ideas of rules engines
with good software engineering practices. You can see the result of this on the
<a href="http://www.clara-rules.org">Clara Rules home page</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://github.com/mrrodriguez">Mike Rodriguez</a> has been essential in turning Clara from an
experiment into a valuable system to fill a gap for rules engines which are oriented towards
developers. More recently, <a href="https://github.com/WilliamParker">Will Parker</a>
has also made significant contributions to help make Clara fast and reliable. They made it possible for Clara
to help analyze millions of medical records every day. Therefore Mike and Will are joining as the
initial committers to Cerner Engineering’s Clara project. We will welcome other contributors to make
this step in the future.</p>

<p>You can find project <a href="https://github.com/cerner/clara-rules">source code on GitHub</a>, and the
documentation on the <a href="http://www.clara-rules.org">clara-rules.org</a> site.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Fall 2016 ShipIt Day]]></title>
    <link href="http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/fall-2016-shipit-day/"/>
    <updated>2016-11-08T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/fall-2016-shipit-day</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Another ShipIt Day was held on September 8th-9th at the Realization Campus at Cerner. ShipIt is a
24-hour hackathon with the goal of building something awesome, usable, and value-adding within a
single day. This fall marked our sixth ShipIt, which has has grown significantly since our first
event.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2016-11-08-fall-2016-shipit-day/shipit-sign.jpg" title="Announcement" ></p>

<p>The event kicked off in the morning at the auditorium of our Realization campus. At this point,
teams were already formed, instructions were given, and shirts were handed out. This ShipIt day came
with cool new t-shirts for all participants featuring the ShipIt squirrel (<a href="https://www.quora.com/GitHub-What-is-the-significance-of-the-Ship-It-squirrel">inspired by GitHub</a>)!</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2016-11-08-fall-2016-shipit-day/shipit-squirrel-shirt.jpg" title="ShipIt shirt" ></p>

<p>Teams broke out to their work spaces and got to work on their projects. One team, <strong>LearnStack</strong>,
decided to focus their project on associate development. The judges greatly appreciated their
approach to this very real problem, and decided to award them the third place prize.</p>

<p><strong>LearnStack</strong> &ndash; Jake LaCombe, Daniel Stucky, Sujay Sudheendra</p>

<blockquote><p>Developers can get to a struggling point when they try to increase their experience level. Sure,
getting started with any language can be very easy to do. Rails for example has their
<a href="https://www.railstutorial.org/">impressive tutorial from Michael Hartl</a> for getting started
with the framework. However, what happens when you
get done with those beginning steps? What does it take to go from a beginner to an intermediate
Rails developer, and then again from Intermediate to Advanced?</p>

<p>The answer here is LearnStack. LearnStack takes a list of resources that are recommended by other
developers, and rated appropriately based on the experience level of the material. Developers can
easily share resources related to beginner, intermediate, and advanced knowledge of a particular
language, process, framework, or whatever it may be. No need to keep doing endless searches online
to figure out how to get to the next level! Let LearnStack point you to the resources you need!”</p></blockquote>

<p>Another team decided to tackle the time it takes to provision a virtual machine. This team called
themselves, &ldquo;All your base are belong to us,&rdquo; and they were awarded second place.</p>

<p><strong>All your base are belong to us</strong> &ndash; Chris Soukup, Alex Harder, Ben Hemphill</p>

<blockquote><p>The current situation for OS image creation is that it is done infrequently, in an ad-hoc manner,
with little consistency among the various hypervisors. This means that we take the base image and
then use <a href="https://www.chef.io/">Chef</a> to upgrade the image to the desired state. This adds significant
amounts of time to the process of provisioning a virtual machine.</p>

<p>Our project was to use <a href="https://www.packer.io/">Packer</a> to create a generic image with all of the
universal settings that we set with our base OS Chef recipe. This image can then be distributed to all
the hypervisors and made available to consumers. Since the image would be generated regularly, the
provisioning time could be significantly decreased by not having to immediately upgrade the system. Additionally,
since the universal settings are already applied, we save considerable amounts of time on the OS preparation
as well. We took provisioning time for a RedHat 7.2 <a href="https://www.openstack.org/">OpenStack</a> VM from 12 minutes,
50 seconds to 4 minutes, 1 second, a 320% decrease in time!</p>

<p>Future enhancements will allow us to automatically generate these images, distribute them, and make
them available to consumers. This will allow a consuming team to naturally stay current on OS
patches at provisioning time, decrease the human effort in creating these OS images, and provide a
consistent experience for teams across Vagrant, VMWare, OpenStack, EC2, Docker, etc.”</p></blockquote>

<p>For the first time we had a unanimous winner for both the judges and the participant winners. The
<strong>206 Partial Content</strong> team not only won two giant tubs of cheese balls, but also the all important
<a href="http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/shipit-hackathon-mplus/">Golden Keyboard</a> and bragging rights
until the next ShipIt Day. <strong>206 Partial Content</strong> decided to solve a problem to &ldquo;enable solution designers,
engineers, and grandparents to easily create, stage, and process data for testing scenarios required for
verification without being dependent on upstream processing or rules.&rdquo;</p>

<p><strong>206 Partial Content</strong> &ndash; Madhur Sikri, Ian Kottman, Venkatesh Sridharan, Andy Nelson, Brian van de
Boogard</p>

<blockquote><p>Our project was primarily driven by two rock star engineers on our team, Ian Kottman and Brian van
de Boogaard. We coined our project Sinecure, which means a position requiring little or no work but
giving the holder status or financial benefit. The goal of the project was to find a solution to
creating test data more easily and efficiently for anyone on our team to consume.”</p></blockquote>

<p>Thanks to all who participated and congratulations to our winners. Until next time, at ShipIt VII in
December!</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2016-11-08-fall-2016-shipit-day/shipit-winners.jpg" title="Winners" ></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
