<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Engineering Health]]></title>
  <link href="http://engineering.cerner.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://engineering.cerner.com/"/>
  <updated>2018-06-19T16:11:13-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://engineering.cerner.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Cerner]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[SREcon18 Recap]]></title>
    <link href="http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/srerecap/"/>
    <updated>2018-06-19T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/srerecap</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This past spring, I had the pleasure of attending <a href="https://www.usenix.org/conference/srecon18americas">SREcon18</a> in Santa Clara, California. If you have never heard about SREcon or the term SRE then let me diverge for a moment to describe. SRE, or Site Reliability Engineer, was coined by Google employees back in 2003 when a team of software engineers were tasked with running a production environment. It&rsquo;s the new hotness in the technology world, so an internet search will turn up a bunch of topics. If you are interested in learning more, I recommend sticking with the more trusted sources:
* <a href="https://landing.google.com/sre/">Google</a> (an obvious choice)
* <a href="https://landing.google.com/sre/book.html">SRE book</a>
* <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Site_Reliability_Engineering">SRE Wikipedia entry</a></p>

<p>Since SRE concepts have been codified, organized, and documented by the creators, the above resources are easy to explore without getting conflicting information from other entities who have taken the ideas and modified them to fit their organization. There is a lot of excitement in the industry around the SRE concept and there&rsquo;s a lot of overlap between SRE and DevOps. Having been working in this industry for a while now, this is a much-needed evolution in the operations and development roles.</p>

<p>SREcon started in 2014, so it is relatively new and is hosted by <a href="https://www.usenix.org/">Usenix Association</a>. Usenix has been hosting technical conferences since 1975 and one of their tenants is to host vendor-neutral events. I have been to a few vendor hosted conferences over the past few years and they are always heavy on the sales and light on the ideas. The sales aspect of these conferences got to the point where I was burned out and looking for something idea based. SREcon was the complete inverse, heavy on the ideas and light on the sales. It fit my need perfectly. My only complaint, and this is minor, was that most of the speakers selected this year were backed by big name tech companies, i.e. Google, Facebook, LinkedIn, Netflix, etc. A fellow attendee I was talking to mentioned that they enjoyed the company diversity this year over previous years, though. Apparently, the tone of the conference in previous years was Google heavy, i.e. &ldquo;This is the Google Way&rdquo; which is not surprising since that&rsquo;s where it all started. The conference was being held in the heart of Silicon Valley therefore, the proximity made it reasonable to have many presenters come from companies in the valley. I fully expect to see more diversity in the coming years. SREcon19 was announced to be held in Brooklyn, NY, so I would not be surprised if there are many east coast companies represented. Additionally, I attended the SREcon Americas conference. Showcasing another aspect of diversity, there are SREcons in Europe/Middle East/Africa and Asia/Australia, so it&rsquo;s become a world-wide conference.</p>

<p>The idea-sharing phenomenon of SREcon played an important role in my decision to attend, since I&rsquo;m leading an automation development team in CernerWorks℠. CernerWorks is Cerner&rsquo;s managed services organization responsible for hosting, managing, and monitoring our client&rsquo;s systems in order to provide the most reliable, highest performing and cost effective delivery of technology services for healthcare. My team is focused on automation in the client aligned systems management space. That&rsquo;s just a fancy way of saying that our focus is on the non-cloud solutions. We are focusing on solution provisioning, configuration management, and upgrades. The work we are doing aligns well with the tenants of SRE, DevOps and other philosophies that have been discussed in the past few years. I am very interested in these philosophies simply because change is hard, especially when it comes to changes in a culture with an established mentality of doing things a certain way. The technical part of our job is easier in my opinion since technology is always changing.</p>

<p>Some of the more interesting sessions I attended talked about patterns and behaviors that we can learn from other industries. For example, the way that firefighters and other first responders react to incidents and the command structures they put in place outline ways that we can improve how we deal with incidents. Having a plan and structure when engaging with an incident has many benefits. It allows you to define what normal operations for your team look like versus what emergency operations looks like. Determining the chain of command and defining pre-set roles that anyone can fit into can help streamline the time to respond and the emergency command hierarchy of the team. Other industries, such as oil and gas refineries, must have strong contingency plans in place in order to not go boom when things go south. There are a lot of patterns, behaviors, and philosophies that we can learn from almost any industry out there if we open our eyes.</p>

<p>A key topic for the conference is learning from failures and mistakes. The idea of a blameless postmortem was discussed at length in multiple talks and conversations. The need for such a thing stems from our human nature to want to assign blame and fault when dealing with problems. But in many ways this type of behavior causes actions to be hidden out of fear of retribution. A blameless postmortem comes from the idea that learning and preventing is more important than assigning blame. <a href="https://codeascraft.com/">Etsy</a>, for example, has an annual award for the employee who&rsquo;s made the biggest mistake. The culture they are building is one where accidents are a source of learning rather than a source of embarrassment. This is quite an interesting concept.</p>

<p>Working in the technology industry and never having been to Silicon Valley was surreal. Seeing big company names on the side of buildings and realizing those were the corporate headquarters of companies whose software I have interacted with for years was an experience. One of the nights, I took a trip to the Googleplex to walk around the campus. It was a beautiful campus with trees and flowers everywhere and the weather was amazing. The campus was abuzz with people and activity that you would expect to take place at Google late at night. While walking a thought started forming in my mind around the type of work we do at Cerner. A thought that continued to form later at the conference when I spoke with development teams from various big-name tech companies. It was rewarding to talk about how we are using technology to make healthcare better. These conversations would usually end with the team from the big tech company expressing admiration, respect, and praise for the work we are doing. The Googles, Facebooks, Twitters, and the like are doing interesting things, and it&rsquo;s easy to get distracted by those names, but the problems that we are solving have real impact on the lives of our fellow humans and we shouldn&rsquo;t take that for granted.</p>

<p>SREcon18 was worth the trip, but if you couldn&rsquo;t attend this year&rsquo;s, previous years, or future SREcons you don&rsquo;t need to worry about missing out. Usenix has an open access policy which means that slides, videos, and audio of all the talks are available after of the conference. I strongly recommend reviewing the <a href="https://www.usenix.org/conference/srecon18americas/program">program for this year&rsquo;s conference</a> and watching any of the talks that catch your fancy.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Say Hello to the 2018 Summer Interns]]></title>
    <link href="http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/say_hello_to_the_2018_summer_interns/"/>
    <updated>2018-05-24T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/say_hello_to_the_2018_summer_interns</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Throughout the month of May, teams across Cerner’s Engineering space have welcomed 197 software interns to our campuses in Kansas City and Malvern. Ranging from rising seniors in high school to rising seniors in college, these interns will be working alongside Cerner’s full time engineers to enhance and expand upon their current skillsets.</p>

<p>While interning at Cerner, these associates will experience firsthand the look and feel of a day in the life of a full time software engineer. Potential projects include:</p>

<ul>
<li>working with data ETL and web technologies to produce analytical dashboards</li>
<li>working on features and capabilities of our solutions to improve the overall experience of Cerner’s consumer solutions and/or development processes, and</li>
<li>adding functionality to some cloud-based applications to provide more troubleshooting capabilities.</li>
</ul>


<p>The variety in projects interns will be working on allows for work in a robust development ecosystem using tools like JIRA, Crucible, Github and languages like Java, Javascript, and Ruby. Our interns have opportunities to work on real projects with real world impact in the healthcare space.</p>

<p>In addition to their work, interns will attend a variety of culture and networking events like our internal developers conference, <a href="https://engineering.cerner.com/2013/08/devcon">DevCon</a>, a bi-weekly Tech Speakers Series, an intern-only hackathon, and a family day where interns are encouraged to bring their families to see their work environment and projects.
Cerner has welcomed three intern groups in Kansas City and one in Malvern, with one more group to start in Kansas City next week. Stay tuned this summer for an in-depth look at a few of the projects our interns work on.</p>

<table cellpadding="5">
  <tr>
    <td>
      <img class="center" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2018-05-24-say_hello_to_the_2018_summer_interns/interns_1.jpg" width="300">
    </td>
    <td>
      <img class="center" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2018-05-24-say_hello_to_the_2018_summer_interns/interns_2.jpg" width="300">
    </td>
    <td>
      <img class="center" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2018-05-24-say_hello_to_the_2018_summer_interns/interns_3.jpg" width="300">
    </td>
  </tr>
</table>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Code Reviews: There Is a Better Way]]></title>
    <link href="http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/code-reviews-there-is-a-better-way/"/>
    <updated>2018-05-08T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/code-reviews-there-is-a-better-way</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>At Cerner, peer review of code is an important job. We have found it to greatly improve the quality of code and improve a team’s knowledge of the codebase. Through code review discussions, newer engineers are able to learn on valuable areas to question or challenge when something is being changed. While we heavily embrace the practice of peer code review, we also recognize it can make an engineer’s life challenging when you are overwhelmed with code to review. Furthermore, it can be large source of project delay when points of coordination are not managed well. In this blog, we will cover some tactics that you can apply to improve how you approach code reviews.</p>

<h2>Smaller code reviews are better code reviews</h2>

<table cellpadding="5">
  <tr>
    <td>
      <div class='pull-left' markdown="1">
        The first step of making a code review inviting for others to provide feedback, is by making the scope of the review small. This generally requires thought and planning on how to incrementally present code for review, allowing each review to be smaller in size which can be safely included into the codebase in isolation. This can ultimately help morale of a team by avoiding monster-size reviews from being stagnate, and never reaching a point of completion due to amount of work necessary to review or the length of feedback that exists. By having the review small, a laser set of focus can be achieved to promptly and effectively complete the review, providing a positive reinforcement of being able to also complete the work.
      </div>
    </td>
    <td>
      <img class="center" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2018-05-08-code-reviews-there-is-a-better-way/code-review-size.png">
    </td>
  </tr>
</table>


<h2>Have machines filter what code qualifies for review</h2>

<table cellpadding="5">
  <tr>
    <td>
      <div class='pull-left' markdown="1">
        We recently had a &#8220;GitHub Day&#8221; at our Innovations campus, where GitHub and other Cerner engineers shared how to improve your use of source code management. In these presentations, a quote was shared that rang true:
        <blockquote><p>We are more receptive to feedback from pedantic robots than pedantic people.</p></blockquote>
        When it comes to a code review, it is easy to point out simple flaws in the code which relates to formatting or basic anti-patterns in a given language. However, should humans be spending time on these types of issues in a code review? Machines are well suited for testing code through linters and static analysis, where formatting rules and known bad patterns can be quickly identified. By focusing on having your CI system do these types of tests on your code, and failing your build when formatting problems emerge, you now have a filter which blocks a large set of noise from entering into a code review. As a result, humans don’t engage in a code review until the code actually builds (which would encompass both static and dynamic forms of tests). Furthermore, it is easier to receive these minor points from a machine (a bot which is communicating the results of your build), versus having a team member spend time pointing out all the minor things you forgot to check or format correctly. In the end, humans apply their creative mind on discussing deeper topics on the design and intentions of the code, versus getting distracted with noise of simple things that can be addressed earlier by machines.
      </div>
    </td>
    <td>
      <img class="center" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2018-05-08-code-reviews-there-is-a-better-way/code-review-human-bot.png">
    </td>
  </tr>
</table>


<h2>Agreed upon conventions</h2>

<table cellpadding="5">
  <tr>
    <td>
      <div class='pull-left' markdown="1">
        Building upon the previous point, teams should have agreed upon conventions on things like style and code formatting, so that those things can be automatically found (and even fixed with the proper tooling).  This eliminates the propensity for style/formatting comments in code reviews which detract from the actual purpose of finding substantive issues within the code. If you find code styling questions or debates are occurring in the code review, ensure the team comes to an agreement on the convention, and that styling rule gets fed into your linter (ex. CheckStyle, Rubocop, IDE formatters) to avoid it from entering into a code review again. Furthermore, this helps reinforce the “boy scout rule”: Always leave the campground cleaner than you found it. By having your linter now embrace this new formatting rule, existing codebases that you start changing in the future will be invited to be updated as well, versus allowing the drift to continue to occur.
      </div>
    </td>
    <td>
      <img class="center" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2018-05-08-code-reviews-there-is-a-better-way/code-review-conventions.png">
    </td>
  </tr>
</table>


<h2>&ldquo;How I would have done it&rdquo;</h2>

<p>When comments emerge on a code review which are being conveyed as opinions, like “I’d have done it this way,” this can detract the focus of the code review away from correctness and more on personal preferences. In this section we will discuss two challenges when including personal preferences in code reviews: the distractions and how they can be interpreted.</p>

<h3>Distraction on personal preferences</h3>

<p>While personal preferences may help the readability of the code (based on the viewer), it is also important to provide the larger “why” when sharing opinions. When multiple opinions are being shared within the review, it may invite for a larger debate that might simply derail the ultimate focus of the code review. As a result, the code review may languish and not be completed due to the debate of opinions.</p>

<h3>Accidental preference becoming &ldquo;law&rdquo;</h3>

<p>When opinions like this are shared, especially when communicated from someone more senior on the team, their opinion may be viewed as “law”. In that, it is simply accepted by the engineer to apply the change because the source of the opinion carries a large amount of weight in the discussion. However, it is expected that no personal preference would simply be applied without additional thought and reason. When personal preferences are brought up in a review, it is best to capture and understand the “why” versus assuming the opinion is simply true or accepting it as its face value.</p>

<h2>Moderator</h2>

<p>All code reviews should have a moderator for the review to ensure the review doesn’t get off track (discussing items not applicable to the review, circular discussions, personal preference comments, etc).  The moderator isn’t necessarily an engineer reviewing the code, but could be the technical project manager for the project where the code resides.  The moderator is also responsible for ensuring comments are addressed and the review is closed when appropriate.</p>

<h2>Review agility</h2>

<p>Code reviews should be given priority, as the author is being blocked waiting for the review to be completed.  In order to achieve review agility, code reviews must be small (as mentioned above), so that reviewers are able to process the content of the review and provide substantive feedback easily. In order to give reviews priority, your team should actively work to ensure people are planning accordingly when they are assigned to reviews. Based on the expertise on the team, it is not uncommon for some team members to become a bottleneck on the team due to amount of code reviews that are assigned to them. It is important for the team to identify this issue, and ensure the team is growing other team members to shed the load of reviews by building up the expertise.</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>While peer code reviews are a crucial component of our software development process, they also require evaluation on how they can be improved. These are simply a few tactics that can be applied to help improve how you approach code reviews. As with the Agile process, we want to continuously improve how we build software, and by focusing on how to improve this process, you can ultimately improve the quality and delivery time of your software.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[ShipIt XI Day: Spring 2018]]></title>
    <link href="http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/shipit-xi-spring-2018/"/>
    <updated>2018-04-18T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/shipit-xi-spring-2018</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2018-04-18-shipit-xi-spring-2018/shipit-xi-1.png" width="600"></p>

<p>On March 8th and 9th, 17 teams of Cerner associates competed for the Golden Keyboard during our 11th ShipIt Day. During this 24-hour hackathon, associates were challenged to create something innovative, usable, and value-adding. This was the fourth ShipIt held at our new Innovations Campus, leveraging the wonderful collaborative spaces available.</p>

<p>With Shipit XI, we expanded upon a time-honored tradition of this event, the traveling trophy Golden Keyboard. This keyboard, adorned with symbolic trinkets from past winners, provides an opportunity for winning teams to defend the trophy and leave their mark in ShipIt history.</p>

<div align="center">
  <table>
    <tr>
      <td align="center">
        <img class="center" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2018-04-18-shipit-xi-spring-2018/shipit-xi-2.png" width="300">
        <sub>Golden Keyboard</sub>
      </td>
    </tr>
  </table>
</div>


<p>However, we realized as ShipIt grew, the category for winning the &ldquo;People&rsquo;s Choice Award&rdquo; (the favorite as voted by the audience agnostic of the judges’ selection) needed to have something more special to symbolize its importance. As a result, we introduced the Golden Mouse! This trophy, while separate from the Golden Keyboard, is another peripheral that a team can win by vote of their peers. With ShipIt XI, the Golden Mouse is now added to the tradition.</p>

<div align="center">
  <table>
    <tr>
      <td align="center">
        <img class="center" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2018-04-18-shipit-xi-spring-2018/shipit-xi-3.png" width="300">
        <sub>Golden Mouse</sub>
      </td>
    </tr>
  </table>
</div>


<p>This ShipIt featured Reliability as its theme. This theme highlighted the work that is continually done to improve the reliability our systems. Reliability, it is the most fundamental feature! By including this theme, we also introduced a new winning category for best project that improved reliability.</p>

<p>Like all ShipIts, signs of creativity, collaboration, and intense problem solving were abundant all night.</p>

<div align="center">
  <table>
    <tr>
      <td align="center">
        <img class="center" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2018-04-18-shipit-xi-spring-2018/shipit-xi-4.png" width="600">
        <sub>Registration and kick-off</sub>
      </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td align="center">
        <img class="center" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2018-04-18-shipit-xi-spring-2018/shipit-xi-5.png" width="600">
        <sub>Strategy planning</sub>
      </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td align="center">
        <img class="center" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2018-04-18-shipit-xi-spring-2018/shipit-xi-6.png" width="600">
        <sub>Focused concentration</sub>
      </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td align="center">
        <img class="center" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2018-04-18-shipit-xi-spring-2018/shipit-xi-7.png" width="600">
        <sub>Abundant caffeine</sub>
      </td>
    </tr>
  </table>
</div>


<p>In addition to café vouchers for breakfast and lunch, ShipIt XI featured a taco bar for dinner. Participants enjoyed unlimited tacos and delicious churros for dessert!</p>

<div align="center">
  <table>
    <tr>
      <td align="center">
        <img class="center" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2018-04-18-shipit-xi-spring-2018/shipit-xi-8.png" width="300">
      </td>
    </tr>
  </table>
</div>


<p>ShipIt XI also hosted a ping-pong “March Madness” tournament to provide an opportunity for the participants take a break and flaunt their athletic prowess.</p>

<div align="center">
  <table>
    <tr>
      <td align="center">
        <img class="center" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2018-04-18-shipit-xi-spring-2018/shipit-xi-9.png" width="600">
        <sub>The dreaded Jake Kramer power serve</sub>
      </td>
    </tr>
  </table>
</div>


<p>Demos always arrive quicker than anticipated. Ready or not, 9am rolled around and demos were in full swing. Teams were given four minutes to present their projects to a panel of judges, consisting of Julie Schlabach, Kevin Shekleton, Jeff Dittmer, and Chad Todd.  Special thank you to those folks for spending their morning with us and supporting ShipIt Day!</p>

<div align="center">
  <table>
    <tr>
      <td align="center">
        <img class="center" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2018-04-18-shipit-xi-spring-2018/shipit-xi-10.png" width="600">
        <sub>Team SPACES RUNNER – 1st Place</sub>
      </td>
    </tr>
  </table>
</div>


<p>Coming in first place was Team SPACES RUNNER (Ryan Scheidter, Darius Washington, Miguel Fernandez, Aarthi Gunda, and Sundeepa Godavarti).</p>

<p>“Space Runner is a visualization tool to show previously run, currently running, and scheduled to run Apache Spark jobs. It also provides some color coding for jobs that take over the average amount of time of previous runs, along with links to the Spark UI where we can view more details about the job. This tool is being used as a visualization of my team’s (Spaces Platform) dev domain to see what ran at what time, what is running, and what is about to start. This is a huge asset in terms of seeing how the domain is running, when it has too many things scheduled, and when it has free time coming up to manually run a job. This tool takes far less time than manually looking at the frequency jobs are scheduled and determining if the domain is free or overbooked.”</p>

<p>Congratulations SPACES RUNNER!</p>

<div align="center">
  <table>
    <tr>
      <td align="center">
        <img class="center" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2018-04-18-shipit-xi-spring-2018/shipit-xi-11.png" width="600">
        <sub>Team PSA – 2nd Place</sub>
      </td>
    </tr>
  </table>
</div>


<p>Second place went to Team PSA (Aaron Noll, Bryce McDonald, Jesse Gilbert, Bennet Lovejoy, and Snehil Wakchaure).</p>

<p>“Team Patient Safety Analytics (PSA) developed a SMART on FHIR app with the aim of making hospitals safer and more reliable. This goal of this app is to decrease the time required to report patient safety events while also increasing accuracy by 1) Populating basic demographic fields automatically for a report (currently manually entered) and 2) Embedding the app within PowerChart to reduce the number of clicks necessary to create a report. Over time, the app could also enable Cerner to add more value by helping hospitals improve through analysis of their data and comparison against peers while also providing reporting utilities for clients to monitor and improve their processes.”
 
Way to go PSA!</p>

<div align="center">
  <table>
    <tr>
      <td align="center">
        <img class="center" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2018-04-18-shipit-xi-spring-2018/shipit-xi-12.png" width="600">
        <sub>Team Pedantic Beasts – 3rd Place</sub>
      </td>
    </tr>
  </table>
</div>


<p>Team Pedantic Beasts (Robert Ryterski, Paul Dennis, Ian Kottman, and Anthony Ross) took third place.</p>

<p>“MCop is a linter for Marathon app definitions. It statically analyzes definitions for problems such as syntax errors, unstable deployment configuration, and departures from best practices.”</p>

<p>Great job Pedantic Beasts!</p>

<div align="center">
  <table>
    <tr>
      <td align="center">
        <img class="center" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2018-04-18-shipit-xi-spring-2018/shipit-xi-13.png" width="600">
        <sub>Team Reliabilibuddies – Best Reliability Themed Project and People’s Choice: Best Team Name</sub>
      </td>
    </tr>
  </table>
</div>


<p>The winner of the sponsored project theme of “Reliability” was Team Reliabilibuddies (Siri Varma Vegiraju, Nathan Schile, Vu Tran, Lucas Chandler, and Venkatesh Sridharan). Reliabilibuddies also won the people’s choice Best Team Name!</p>

<p>Nicely done Reliabilibuddies!</p>

<div align="center">
  <table>
    <tr>
      <td align="center">
        <img class="center" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2018-04-18-shipit-xi-spring-2018/shipit-xi-14.png" width="600">
        <sub>Team The Centurions – People’s Choice: Best Project</sub>
      </td>
    </tr>
  </table>
</div>


<p>Winning the brand new Golden Mouse for people’s choice Best Project was team The Centurions (Mohan Chamarthy, Sanket Korgaonkar, Saranth Govindaraju, Vamsi Krishna Guntupalli, and Shyam Gopal Rajanna). Congratulations and enjoy your cheeseballs!</p>

<div align="center">
  <table>
    <tr>
      <td align="center">
        <img class="center" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2018-04-18-shipit-xi-spring-2018/shipit-xi-15.png" width="600">
        <sub>Team Whalenado – People’s Choice: Best Presentation</sub>
      </td>
    </tr>
  </table>
</div>


<p>Winning a glorious tub of cheeseballs is Team Whalenado (Mithun Singh, David Crowder, Nick Overfield, and Michael Rzepka) for people’s choice Best Presentation.</p>

<div align="center">
  <table>
    <tr>
      <td align="center">
        <img class="center" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2018-04-18-shipit-xi-spring-2018/shipit-xi-16.png" width="600">
        <sub>Winning teams walked away with some awesome prizes such as wireless headphones, TileMates, Echo Dots, and drones.</sub>
      </td>
    </tr>
  </table>
</div>


<p>ShipIt continues to be a great way for associates to explore new solutions to problems, build relationships within different organizations, and most importantly, enjoy themselves. ShipIt Day XI was a great success. The projects were creative and have potential to bring value Cerner’s associates and clients.</p>

<p>Save the Date: ShipIt Day returns August 9th and 10th! If you are interested in learning more about other ShipIt Days, see these earlier posts:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/shipit-x-day-winter-2017/">ShipIt Day X Winter 2017</a></li>
<li><a href="http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/shipit-ix-day-summer-2017/">ShipIt Day IX Summer 2017</a></li>
<li><a href="http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/shipit-day-viii-spring-2017/">ShipIt Day VIII Spring 2017</a></li>
<li><a href="http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/shipit-vii-day-winter-2016/">ShipIt Day VII Winter 2016</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=iqTp0dmLgUk">ShipIt Day Winter 2016 Highlight Reel</a></li>
<li><a href="http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/fall-2016-shipit-day/">ShipIt Day Fall 2016</a></li>
<li><a href="http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/spring-2016-shipit-day/">ShipIt Day Spring 2016</a></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Cerner and iControl]]></title>
    <link href="http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/cerner-and-icontrol/"/>
    <updated>2018-03-13T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/cerner-and-icontrol</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>At Cerner, we manage our own infrastructure and a big part of that is managing F5 load balancers. If you are a Ruby developer or a network engineer and regularly work with F5s, then I have good news! I&rsquo;ve created a gem that abstracts iControl&rsquo;s REST API. It makes working with the API easy to understand and eases the effort required to automate changes across many devices.</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='ruby'><span class='line'><span class="n">api</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="ss">IcontrolRest</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="ss">:Client</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">new</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="ss">host</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="s1">&#39;1.2.3.4&#39;</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="ss">user</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="s1">&#39;user&#39;</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="ss">pass</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="s1">&#39;pass&#39;</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">verify_cert</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="kp">false</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="o">=&gt;</span> <span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="ss">Icontrol</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="ss">:Client</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="mh">0x007fb953ab7750</span> <span class="vi">@options</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="p">{</span> <span class="o">.</span><span class="n">.</span><span class="o">.</span> <span class="p">}</span><span class="o">&gt;</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>After logging in, one can build a query via an instance method:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='ruby'><span class='line'><span class="n">api</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">get_sys_dns</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="c1"># returns an object like this:</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="o">=&gt;</span> <span class="p">{</span> <span class="s2">&quot;kind&quot;</span>        <span class="o">=&gt;</span> <span class="s2">&quot;tm:sys:dns:dnsstate&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span>
</span><span class='line'>     <span class="s2">&quot;selfLink&quot;</span>    <span class="o">=&gt;</span> <span class="s2">&quot;https://localhost/mgmt/tm/sys/dns?ver=11.5.4&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span>
</span><span class='line'>     <span class="s2">&quot;description&quot;</span> <span class="o">=&gt;</span> <span class="s2">&quot;configured-by-dhcp&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span>
</span><span class='line'>     <span class="s2">&quot;nameServers&quot;</span> <span class="o">=&gt;</span> <span class="o">[</span><span class="s2">&quot;1.2.3.72&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="s2">&quot;1.2.3.73&quot;</span><span class="o">]</span><span class="p">,</span>
</span><span class='line'>     <span class="s2">&quot;search&quot;</span>      <span class="o">=&gt;</span> <span class="o">[</span><span class="s2">&quot;domain.com&quot;</span><span class="o">]</span>
</span><span class='line'>   <span class="p">}</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>The gem builds REST queries given a method delimited by underscores. The first word is the REST method and the following words are the path you&rsquo;d like to send your request to.</p>

<p>For example, if you&rsquo;d like to get the version of the F5, given this <a href="https://devcentral.f5.com/d/icontrol-rest-api-reference-version-120">iControl REST API doc</a></p>

<p>You&rsquo;d call a method that looks like this:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
<span class='line-number'>14</span>
<span class='line-number'>15</span>
<span class='line-number'>16</span>
<span class='line-number'>17</span>
<span class='line-number'>18</span>
<span class='line-number'>19</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='ruby'><span class='line'><span class="n">api</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">get_sys_version</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="c1"># returns an object like this:</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="o">=&gt;</span> <span class="p">{</span> <span class="s2">&quot;kind&quot;</span> <span class="o">=&gt;</span> <span class="s2">&quot;tm:sys:version:versionstats&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span>
</span><span class='line'>     <span class="s2">&quot;selfLink&quot;</span> <span class="o">=&gt;</span> <span class="s2">&quot;https://localhost/mgmt/tm/sys/version?ver=12.1.2&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span>
</span><span class='line'>     <span class="s2">&quot;entries&quot;</span> <span class="o">=&gt;</span> <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="s2">&quot;https://localhost/mgmt/tm/sys/version/0&quot;</span> <span class="o">=&gt;</span> <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>        <span class="s2">&quot;nestedStats&quot;</span> <span class="o">=&gt;</span> <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>          <span class="s2">&quot;entries&quot;</span> <span class="o">=&gt;</span> <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>            <span class="s2">&quot;Build&quot;</span>   <span class="o">=&gt;</span> <span class="p">{</span> <span class="s2">&quot;description&quot;</span><span class="o">=&gt;</span><span class="s2">&quot;0.0.249&quot;</span> <span class="p">},</span>
</span><span class='line'>            <span class="s2">&quot;Date&quot;</span>    <span class="o">=&gt;</span> <span class="p">{</span> <span class="s2">&quot;description&quot;</span><span class="o">=&gt;</span><span class="s2">&quot;Wed Nov 30 16:04:00 PST 2016&quot;</span> <span class="p">},</span>
</span><span class='line'>            <span class="s2">&quot;Edition&quot;</span> <span class="o">=&gt;</span> <span class="p">{</span> <span class="s2">&quot;description&quot;</span><span class="o">=&gt;</span><span class="s2">&quot;Final&quot;</span> <span class="p">},</span>
</span><span class='line'>            <span class="s2">&quot;Product&quot;</span> <span class="o">=&gt;</span> <span class="p">{</span> <span class="s2">&quot;description&quot;</span><span class="o">=&gt;</span><span class="s2">&quot;BIG-IP&quot;</span> <span class="p">},</span>
</span><span class='line'>            <span class="s2">&quot;Title&quot;</span>   <span class="o">=&gt;</span> <span class="p">{</span> <span class="s2">&quot;description&quot;</span><span class="o">=&gt;</span><span class="s2">&quot;Main Package&quot;</span> <span class="p">},</span>
</span><span class='line'>            <span class="s2">&quot;Version&quot;</span> <span class="o">=&gt;</span> <span class="p">{</span> <span class="s2">&quot;description&quot;</span><span class="o">=&gt;</span><span class="s2">&quot;12.1.2&quot;</span> <span class="p">}</span>
</span><span class='line'>          <span class="p">}</span>
</span><span class='line'>        <span class="p">}</span>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="p">}</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="p">}</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="p">}</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>So in practice you could put all this together to do something like audit the versions of F5s in a collection:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='ruby'><span class='line'><span class="o">[</span><span class="s1">&#39;hostname1&#39;</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="s1">&#39;hostname2&#39;</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="s1">&#39;hostname3&#39;</span><span class="o">].</span><span class="n">each</span> <span class="k">do</span> <span class="o">|</span><span class="n">host</span><span class="o">|</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="n">api</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="ss">IcontrolRest</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="ss">:Client</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">new</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="ss">host</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="n">host</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="ss">user</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="s1">&#39;user&#39;</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="ss">pass</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="s1">&#39;pass&#39;</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">verify_cert</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="kp">false</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="n">result</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">api</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">get_sys_version</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="n">version</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">result</span><span class="o">[</span><span class="s1">&#39;entries&#39;</span><span class="o">][</span><span class="err">‘</span><span class="ss">https</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="sr">//</span><span class="n">localhost</span><span class="o">/</span><span class="n">mgmt</span><span class="o">/</span><span class="n">tm</span><span class="o">/</span><span class="n">sys</span><span class="o">/</span><span class="n">version</span><span class="o">/</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="err">’</span><span class="o">][</span><span class="s1">&#39;nestedStats&#39;</span><span class="o">][</span><span class="s1">&#39;entries&#39;</span><span class="o">][</span><span class="s1">&#39;Version&#39;</span><span class="o">][</span><span class="s1">&#39;description&#39;</span><span class="o">]</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="nb">puts</span> <span class="s2">&quot;host: </span><span class="si">#{</span><span class="n">host</span><span class="si">}</span><span class="s2"> | version: </span><span class="si">#{</span><span class="n">version</span><span class="si">}</span><span class="s2">&quot;</span> <span class="k">unless</span> <span class="n">version</span> <span class="o">==</span> <span class="err">‘</span><span class="mi">12</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="err">’</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">end</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>This would print out the hostname and version of any F5s that aren&rsquo;t on version 12.0.0. This is just one example, I encourage you to look through the iControl REST API docs to get a feeling for what&rsquo;s really possible.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[One Year Calling Innovations Home]]></title>
    <link href="http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/one-year-calling-innovations-home/"/>
    <updated>2018-02-28T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/one-year-calling-innovations-home</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One year ago this month, Cerner development associates in Kansas City moved into a new place to call home for their workdays, Innovations Campus. The first two towers that stand on this campus provide 805,000 square feet of workspace for more than 3,000 associates. Eventually, the campus will grow larger, including 16 buildings and 16,000 Cerner associates. As that growth approaches, it is important to reflect on what these first two towers represent for associates and their development careers at Cerner. The investment in this workplace is a testament to Cerner’s dedication to and appreciation of associate values. It is a reflection of who the people at Cerner are and what they strive to be.</p>

<p>Many of the features in the building were designed with input by associates, for associates.  Other spaces and elements of the building were voted on by associates. A Momentum Wall, a series of installations that change and grow with Cerner’s culture and development platforms, capturing architectural history, open source projects and commits, a giant monthly calendar of events, and a continuously changing installation showcasing Cerner’s commitment to usability and solid design. Distinct “Neighborhood Nodes” were designed by committees of development associates to provide opportunities for associate to relax, learn, and create. The game rooms Bowser’s Castle and Flynn’s Arcade are a nod to the sci-fi and gaming culture popular among many development associates at Cerner. The Harry Potter and Lord of the Rings libraries house books and quiet work space for associates to get away and learn. The MakerSpace provides space, machinery and materials for associates to work on personal projects and think about work projects in a different way. Associates voted on various options for workstations and landed on a configurable option that provides flexibility in terms of work space and style. The Assembly provides a space for associates to share and learn, and creates opportunities for ambient conversations for those passing through a meetup or knowledge transfer session. On a normal workday at Innovations you can see how the physical elements embedded in the buildings contribute immensely to our development culture, from the collaborative layout of the campus with unique seating and whiteboards around every corner to unique representations of Cerner’s values and history composed in binary ascii. The functionality and aesthetics of the campus have enhanced the cultural experiences associates have had over the past year. In honor of the one year anniversary in Innovations, we’ve asked a few of our associates for their perspectives on the parts of the campus they interact with daily.</p>

<h4>Associate Reviewer: Ann Dickey, Software Engineer</h4>

<blockquote><p>I love the MakerSpace Neighborhood Node. Not only because it’s given me a chance to learn and use tools I have never used before, but for the networking experience it has turned out to be. I’ve met dozens of associates across Cerner while babysitting a 3D print, or attending the Makerspace learning events the admins host.</p>

<p>We put together a group for ShipIt IX, where we used the MakerSpace to design and create a 3D printed notification template that hooked up with an Arduino and LED light strip we programmed to give the user notifications from their desired apps. ShipIt was a first for all of us, and we wouldn’t have had a project without the availability of the MakerSpace to do 3D printing and soldering. We all had a blast, learned a lot, and plan on doing another ShipIt in the future. Plus, now I have some great embarrassing photos of my team feeding each other ice cream and failing to properly use the outdoor exercise equipment because of the ShipIt scavenger hunt challenge. The funny thing is the MakerSpace is the one neighborhood node I did not vote for when the new Innovations was being built. I had never used a 3D printer, CNC, or laser cutter and, not knowing how, I wasn’t able to imagine a personal use for those tools. But the MakerSpace team put together great tutorials in their training and connected me to resources like Thingiverse and other associates co-using the space that now I am using the space at least once a month to create decorations or make utility pieces for around the house or office. The entire MakerSpace community has been a wonderful addition to my overall experience working here at Cerner. I’ve enjoyed the people, the projects, and the enthusiasm to help each other and share ideas.</p></blockquote>

<p><img class="center" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2018-02-28-one-year-calling-innovations-home/anniversary-1.jpg" width="500">
<sub>The MakerSpace node serves as an associate space for innovation and exploration equipped with Ultimaker 3D printers, a soldering station, a CNC Carvey and an Epilog Laser.</sub></p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2018-02-28-one-year-calling-innovations-home/anniversary-2.jpg" width="500">
<sub>A community of MakerSpace admins host regular workshops for associates to learn new skills or machinery such as this one featuring a laser project.</sub></p>

<h4>Associate Reviewer: Caleb Meyer, Senior Software Engineer</h4>

<blockquote><p>The new Innovations campus shows us that Cerner is a company you can grow with. The old Innovations campus (I’m still refusing to call it Realizations) wasn’t designed for programmers, and certainly not for as many as we have. My team is as collaborative as ever, but now we have space to focus and get good work done. The all wifi floors perfectly represent everyone’s preference to remain wireless (untethered) during the day.</p>

<p>My favorite feature of the campus is the Assembly. I’ve run the Python Developers’ Meetup since its inception across the road (at the former campus), and I remember how ill-suited the game room (8 byte café) was for it. The Assembly is perfect for meetups of any size, and the self-service microphones and projector rock. The DE Tech Talks we’ve had there have all been fantastic, and the external speakers’ Tech Talks are always good as well. When there’s not something going on, the furniture surrounding the Assembly is comfortable, and there’s plenty of outlets for working away from your desk without your battery dying.</p></blockquote>

<div align="center">
  <table>
    <tr>
      <td align="center">
        <img class="center" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2018-02-28-one-year-calling-innovations-home/anniversary-5.jpg" width="375">
      </td>
      <td align="center">
        <img class="center" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2018-02-28-one-year-calling-innovations-home/anniversary-6.jpg" width="375">
      </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td align="center" colspan="2">
        <sub>Spanning two floors in the heart of Innovations, the Assembly is home to many cultural events such as meetups, Tech Talks (be sure to check out our YouTube channel for recordings of our impressive speakers), lightning talks, ShipIt presentations, and more!</sub>
      </td>
    </tr>
  </table>
</div>


<h4>Associate Reviewer: Ryan Grass, Senior Software Engineer</h4>

<blockquote><p>In many ways I feel the new campus is a reflection of the cultural shift Cerner took over half a decade ago to create a fun, creative, and interactive development culture. The cafeteria is practically a food court, offering a range of diverse choices that reflect our many individual associates’ tastes. The work areas are open, and modular, allowing for easy communication between associates; and creativity in customizing your work environment. The many nodes on campus offer creative outlets for innovative minds. Revenue Cycle uses Bowser’s Castle for monthly after work board game meetups. These are not only fun, but great ways to network within our organization. My team has even decided a few times to stay on campus rather than going out for team lunches and play board games over lunch. These have been great opportunities to bond, and become more relaxed around each other.</p></blockquote>

<p><img class="center" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2018-02-28-one-year-calling-innovations-home/anniversary-7.jpg" width="500">
<sub>Classic and Super Classic Nintendo stations are in both of our game rooms, Flynn’s Arcade and Bowser’s Castle. Associates gravitate to these retro games when they need a short break to look at problem differently. Additionally, you’ll find many associates huddled around our foosball tables during lunch.</sub></p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2018-02-28-one-year-calling-innovations-home/anniversary-4.jpg" width="500">
<sub>Pinball is one of the many arcade games we have on-hand in our two game rooms at Innovations. Game of Thrones seems to be a crowd favorite as we wait in anticipation for the final season!</sub></p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2018-02-28-one-year-calling-innovations-home/anniversary-8.jpg" width="500">
<sub>Table tennis is a necessity at Innovations. On a daily basis you can find these tables full of associates looking for some mid-day competition during lunch.</sub></p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2018-02-28-one-year-calling-innovations-home/anniversary-3.jpg" width="500">
<sub>We have two quaint library nodes at Innovations each with a unique theme: Harry Potter and Lord of the Rings. These spaces are designed for associates who need to escape their desks for a change or want to check out the hundreds of books Cerner offers ranging from technical, UX, medical and management.</sub></p>

<p>Innovations has become an integral part of our development culture here in Kansas City. It has also become a showstopper in the Kansas City workplace architecture and development realm as it recently won the <a href="https://www.bizjournals.com/kansascity/news/2018/01/26/2018-capstone-award-winners.html">Special Judges’ recognition for the Kansas City Business Journal’s 2018 Capstone Awards</a>. We are very proud of our newest campus and can’t wait to see how it grows and transforms physically and culturally over the new few years!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[ShipIt X Day: Winter 2017]]></title>
    <link href="http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/shipit-x-day-winter-2017/"/>
    <updated>2018-02-19T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/shipit-x-day-winter-2017</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2018-02-19-shipit-x-day-winter-2017/shipit-x-4.jpg" width="600"></p>

<p>On December 14th and 15th, 18 teams of Cerner associates competed for the Golden Trophy during our tenth ShipIt Day. Being this was our tenth, it was fun to reflect back on how this event started and how much it has grown.</p>

<blockquote><p>It has been great to see ShipIt Days start from small hackathons organically run by individual teams to now an engineering-wide quarterly event that brings together engineers from disparate organizations, allowing for a better cross-pollination of ideas and team members. &ndash; <a href="https://twitter.com/kpshek">Kevin Shekleton</a></p></blockquote>

<table>
  <tr>
    <td>
      <div class='pull-left' markdown="1">
        <img class="center" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2018-02-19-shipit-x-day-winter-2017/shipit-x-6.png" width="200">
      </div>
        This was our third ShipIt Day hosted at our new Innovations campus. It continues to be a great location for ShipIt because of our awesome game rooms and collaboration spaces. As part of this ShipIt, we had a sponsored theme, which focused on building React applications using <a href="https://github.com/cerner/kaiju">Kaiju</a> that are based on Cerner&#8217;s consistent <a href="http://terra-ui.herokuapp.com/home">Terra UI</a> theme. Team members that support these projects were available to help participants if they wished to use these technologies, helping to gain more feedback on the projects, and to expand the exposure of these projects to ShipIt teams. By including this theme, we also introduced a new category for someone to win by using these projects.
    </td>
  </tr>
</table>




<div align="center">
  <table>
    <tr>
      <td align="center">
        <img class="center" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2018-02-19-shipit-x-day-winter-2017/shipit-x-3.jpg" width="375">
        <sub>Shirt for participants.</sub>
      </td>
      <td align="center">
        <img class="center" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2018-02-19-shipit-x-day-winter-2017/shipit-x-8.png" width="672">
        <sub>Whiteboard action happening bright and early.</sub>
      </td>
    </tr>
  </table>
</div>


<p>Teams checked in bright and early for kick-off.  Vouchers to the cafe were provided so participants could fuel their hard work throughout the day. Workflow was constant with lots of collaboration.</p>

<div align="center">
  <table>
    <tr>
      <td align="center">
        <img class="center" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2018-02-19-shipit-x-day-winter-2017/shipit-x-12.png" width="375">
      </td>
      <td align="center">
        <img class="center" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2018-02-19-shipit-x-day-winter-2017/shipit-x-13.png" width="375">
      </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td align="center" colspan="2">
        <sub>Teams planning out their strategy.</sub>
      </td>
    </tr>
  </table>
</div>




<div align="center">
  <table>
    <tr>
      <td align="center">
        <img class="center" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2018-02-19-shipit-x-day-winter-2017/shipit-x-11.jpg" width="500">
        <sub>The Assembly filling up before presentations.</sub>
      </td>
    </tr>
  </table>
</div>


<p>Demos always arrive quicker than anticipated. Ready or not, 9am rolled around and demos were in full swing. Teams got 4 minutes to present their projects to a panel of judges, consisting of Michelle Brush, Robert Farr, Tim Erdel, Chad Moats, and Chuck Schneider.  Special thank you to those folks for spending their morning with us and supporting ShipIt Day!</p>

<h3>Team Delayed Gratification</h3>

<table cellpadding="10">
  <tr>
    <td>
      <div class='pull-left' markdown="1">
        <img class="center" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2018-02-19-shipit-x-day-winter-2017/shipit-x-7.jpg">
      </div>
    </td>
    <td>
      Coming in first place was Team Delayed Gratification (Russ Star, Ben Hemphill, Morgan Patterson).
      
      <blockquote><p>Our ShipIt team, Delayed Gratification, worked to complete  an existing side project called the &#8220;RUSS test,&#8221; aka Really Useful Speed Service. The goal is to allow service owners to make smart decisions about where to  geographically place their services by providing response time, bandwidth, and other key network metrics.</p></blockquote>
      
      Congratulations Team Delayed Gratification! A much deserved win.
    </td>
  </tr>
</table>


<h3>Team ShipIt X Files</h3>

<p><img class="center" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2018-02-19-shipit-x-day-winter-2017/shipit-x-10.jpg" width="500"></p>

<p>Second place went to Team ShipIt X Files (Santosh Manughala, Carlos Salazar, Matt Horn, Seada Ali).</p>

<blockquote><p>Our project was to create an application for discovering related database rows that let&rsquo;s the user quickly navigate back-end data in Millennium, (e.g. look up lots of useful info for a given personnel id, person id, or event id). Each bit of data could be clickable to do a new search on that id (search the person you found on a clinical event in one click). The app displays information so that it is easy to navigate.</p></blockquote>

<p>Way to go, Team ShipIT X Files!</p>

<h3>Team A Near Field Far Far Away</h3>

<p><img class="center" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2018-02-19-shipit-x-day-winter-2017/shipit-x-2.jpg" width="500"></p>

<p>Team A Near Field Far Far Away (Aurko Ghosh, Aaron Kaplan, Vijay Ayilavarapu, Nikhil Agrawal, Neil Pathare) took third place. Their project utilized our MakerSpace!</p>

<blockquote><p>For ShipIt, we assembled a 3D printed light bridge that provides 180% of bright light for the soldering workbench. In addition to assembly, we designed and attempted to implement an RGB LED controller using a Raspberry Pi 3 and mosfet chips. The controller uses both a physical switch, as well as a mobile app to control the lighting. The mobile app is developed using React Native, and communicates wirelessly with the controller via Near Field Communication (NFC).</p></blockquote>

<p>Judge Chuck Schneider noted, &ldquo;I like that they took on a lot of different pieces, which adds to the complexity of the project.&rdquo;</p>

<h3>Team Flying Mongoose</h3>

<p><img class="center" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2018-02-19-shipit-x-day-winter-2017/shipit-x-1.jpg" width="500"></p>

<p>The winners of the sponsored project theme was a veteran team, Flying Mongoose (Mahesh Acharya, Taylor Clay, Cihan Kaynak, Matt Stramel). They were able to start the migration of <a href="https://www.cerner.com/solutions/automated-dispensing-cabinet">Cerner&rsquo;s RxStation</a> to a React application utilizing Terra UI. They were able to utilize Kaiju to build the prototype UI, which had dynamically loaded tables and mock buttons. By using ShipIt to start this transition, they were able to learn a lot of what it would take to make these next steps.</p>

<p>Nicely done Team Flying Mongoose!</p>

<h3>People&rsquo;s Choice Awards</h3>

<p><img class="center" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2018-02-19-shipit-x-day-winter-2017/shipit-x-9.jpg" width="500"></p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Favorite Team Name</strong>: Keep it on the DL (Eric Fung, Ian Kottman, Sam Livingston, Abhi Mahabalshetti, Will Pruyn)</li>
<li><strong>Favorite Project</strong>: A Near Field Far Far Away (Aurko Ghosh, Aaron Kaplan, Vijay Ayilavarapu, Nikhil Agrawal, Neil Pathare)</li>
<li><strong>Favorite Presentation</strong>: If It Doesn’t Ship, You Must Acquit (Steven Goldberg, Ryan Neff, Jason Xu)</li>
</ul>


<p>Winning teams walked away with some awesome prizes. Wireless headphones, TileMates, portable chargers, Echo Dots, drones, Google Cardboards, and Lego tape were all up for grabs.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2018-02-19-shipit-x-day-winter-2017/shipit-x-5.jpg" width="500"></p>

<p>Each ShipIt Day, the projects get more intricate and more creative. The projects presented show off the talent we have. After surveying the participants on their projects, 45% of the projects were identified to improve daily work at Cerner. ShipIt Day remains one of our most popular dev culture events at Cerner.</p>

<p>First time participant, Ted Segal said, &ldquo;I&rsquo;m a new developer, I&rsquo;m still in the <a href="http://engineering.cerner.com/2013/08/devacademy/">DevAcademy</a>, and I really appreciated the chance to learn about tools and ideas that I had not been exposed to yet from more experienced developers.&rdquo;</p>

<p>Veteran participant, Alex Harder said he likes participating in ShipIt Day because he enjoys exploring new technologies and applying them to a problem. ShipIt Day continues to be successful among Cerner associates. Whether you want to work on something you don’t normally have time to, or you’re interested in meeting new people, ShipIt Day is a winner!</p>

<p>Save the Date: ShipIt Day returns March 8th and 9th! If you are interested in learning more about other ShipIt Days, see these earlier posts:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/shipit-ix-day-summer-2017/">ShipIt Day IX Summer 2017</a></li>
<li><a href="http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/shipit-day-viii-spring-2017/">ShipIt Day VIII Spring 2017</a></li>
<li><a href="http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/shipit-vii-day-winter-2016/">ShipIt Day VII Winter 2016</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=iqTp0dmLgUk">ShipIt Day Winter 2016 Highlight Reel</a></li>
<li><a href="http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/fall-2016-shipit-day/">ShipIt Day Fall 2016</a></li>
<li><a href="http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/spring-2016-shipit-day/">ShipIt Day Spring 2016</a></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Cerner Open Sources Its Kafka Utilities]]></title>
    <link href="http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/cerner-open-sources-its-kafka-utilities/"/>
    <updated>2018-02-06T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/cerner-open-sources-its-kafka-utilities</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>At Cerner, we often make use of many open source projects in our infrastructure. I work on a team responsible for Cerner&rsquo;s Ingestion Platform, a critical piece of infrastructure that takes in TBs of data and over a billion messages per day. The platform’s responsibility is then to make this data available for downstream teams to consume. When designing the Ingestion Platform, we felt Apache Kafka was perfect for ingesting and consuming these massive streams of data. We originally built the Ingestion Platform in 2014 and it has grown with Kafka ever since.</p>

<p>Along the way, we’ve become experienced with Apache Kafka and how it works. We know how to monitor it, perform common administrative operations, and more. We’ve even made contributions to Kafka for various improvements [<a href="https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/KAFKA-3297">1</a>][<a href="https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/KAFKA-4687">2</a>][<a href="https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/KAFKA-2434">3</a>] and Apache Crunch, our processing framework, to <a href="https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/CRUNCH-606">add Kafka support</a>. We have also given <a href="https://www.confluent.io/resources/kafka-summit-2016/ingesting-complex-healthcare-data-apache-kafka/">talks</a> about our usage of Apache Kafka at Kafka Summit and we’ve written a <a href="http://blog.cloudera.com/blog/2014/11/how-cerner-uses-cdh-with-apache-kafka/">blog post</a> about it as well.</p>

<p>We are still interested in supporting the Kafka community, and today we hit another milestone as we open source some of our <a href="https://github.com/cerner/common-kafka">utilities for Kafka</a>. This includes:</p>

<ul>
<li>Lightweight wrappers over producer and consumer providing additional functionality</li>
<li>A client to simplify admin operations</li>
<li>A Kafka connect sink for delivering data to another Kafka cluster</li>
<li>Kafka test infrastructure for integration testing</li>
</ul>


<p>Try it and let me know what you think! You can log issues for improvements, or email me your thoughts: <a href="&#109;&#x61;&#105;&#108;&#x74;&#111;&#58;&#x62;&#114;&#x79;&#97;&#x6e;&#x2e;&#98;&#x61;&#117;&#x67;&#x68;&#101;&#x72;&#x40;&#x63;&#x65;&#114;&#x6e;&#101;&#114;&#46;&#99;&#111;&#x6d;&#46;">&#x62;&#114;&#x79;&#97;&#110;&#x2e;&#x62;&#x61;&#117;&#x67;&#104;&#x65;&#x72;&#64;&#x63;&#101;&#x72;&#110;&#101;&#114;&#x2e;&#x63;&#111;&#109;&#x2e;</a> We hope to continue to improve the library and always welcome contributions and ideas from others.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Cerner and the SDLC]]></title>
    <link href="http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/cerner-and-the-sdlc/"/>
    <updated>2018-01-23T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/cerner-and-the-sdlc</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Cerner has a very compelling story that many want to learn from. Cerner’s Agile Champions are regular presenters at local, national, and global conferences. We routinely host calls and site visits for interested companies around the world who want to figure out how we were able to adopt Agile so quickly and sustain it so successfully.</p>

<p>Despite our success, there has been a general feeling at the engineering leadership and Agile Champion tiers that we aren’t getting the benefits from Agile that we once were. We talk Agile well, but have far too many teams that could be classified as &ldquo;<a href="https://www.solutionsiq.com/resource/blog-post/cargo-cult-agile-approach/">cargo cult</a>&rdquo; &ndash; going through the motions rather than having an Agile mindset. We were great teachers, but somehow had gone stagnant in our learning and growth.</p>

<p>Two events have ignited Cerner on a renewed learning journey that has already impacted Cerner in many business areas and allowed Cerner to help shape the future direction of business agility across the globe.</p>

<h3>The Invitation</h3>

<p>Ironically, the first came shortly after delivering a presentation at Agile 2014 that included a section on avoiding cargo cult Agile. <a href="https://twitter.com/asidky">Ahmed Sidky</a>, CEO of ICAgile, invited me to connect for a brief meeting. When our &ldquo;brief meeting&rdquo; stretched over several hours, we knew we had a strong partnership opportunity. Thus, was born the certification of Cerner’s Agile courses against an <a href="https://icagile.com/Overview">independent, internationally recognized curriculum</a> and Cerner as one of ICAgile’s first Member Organizations.</p>

<p>The second came shortly after Agile 2015 while hosting a call for CH Robinson and their delivery lead, <a href="https://twitter.com/jed2van">Vanessa Adams</a>. As the call wrapped up, Vanessa disclosed that she served on the board of directors for a newly formed group under the leadership of Steve Denning and Ahmed Sidky that was bringing together forward looking Agile companies to discover best practices in enterprise agility and share them back into the community. After talking with us, she felt that Cerner was an ideal candidate given our story and our willingness to learn and share.</p>

<p>I was intrigued yet skeptical.</p>

<p>I honestly didn’t know who <a href="https://twitter.com/stevedenning">Steve Denning</a> was so being a part of the &ldquo;Steve Denning Learning Consortium&rdquo; held no appeal. I respected Ahmed as a voice in the Agile community that understood how to address real business issues with an Agile mindset.</p>

<p>Some quick research on Steve exposed his background in the business and banking world. He is an author and regular contributor to Forbes magazine and Harvard Business Review. While he had written books on Agile management and was on the Scrum Alliance board, my mental image was of a business school professor, not a practicing agilist.</p>

<p>I voiced my concerns. Vanessa felt confident they would be resolved and invited us to attend an upcoming visit (May 2016) at Riot Games and Microsoft that would be partially hosted by Ahmed who had joined Riot Games as head of Delivery.</p>

<h3>Converting the Skeptic</h3>

<p>One of the keys to Cerner’s successful transformation was leveraging the idea of <em>Connectors</em>, <em>Mavens</em>, and <em>Salesmen</em> along with <em>Skeptics</em> as articulated by <a href="https://www.fastcompany.com/1799410/connectors-mavens-and-salesmen-how-new-ideas-spread-seeds">Malcolm Gladwell</a> in our early pilot groups so we could address potential issues head on and build momentum. We were especially successful as some of the biggest <em>Skeptics</em> were also <em>Connectors</em> or <em>Mavens</em> and they have been crucial to our broad adoption and continued sustainability. Our results were our best <em>Salesmen</em>.</p>

<p>On Cerner’s first site visit to meet with the SD Learning Consortium, the roles played out again. <a href="http://www.sdlearningconsortium.org/who-we-are/">Microsoft, Riot Games, Ericsson, CH Robinson, Spotify</a>, Steve Denning, and a representative from the <a href="https://www.scrumalliance.org/">Scrum Alliance</a> were all in attendance. Over the four days in LA and Seattle, we got to see inside Riot and Microsoft and see what was working as well as what wasn’t. The open and frank conversations as well as the &ldquo;No BS&rdquo; attitude among all participants was extremely refreshing and productive.</p>

<p>At conferences, messages are polished and even &ldquo;learning&rdquo; (a.k.a. failure) is always painted in the best possible light. This was completely different. Failures that were failures were shared and discussed. Current experiments were both admired and challenged, often by the same individual.</p>

<p>Probably the most significant moment for me was sitting next to <a href="https://twitter.com/joakimsunden">Joakim Sunden</a> from Spotify, who co-authored what I still consider to be the best introductory book on Kanban for software development (<a href="https://www.amazon.com/Kanban-Action-Marcus-Hammarberg/dp/1617291056">Kanban in Action</a>), and having him explain how the Spotify videos were created and what really goes on. (Hint – they are Marketing videos and highlight models that Spotify does not rigidly follow. They don’t know what the Spotify Way is that many talk about.)  Spotify is great, visionary and different, but they aren’t a unicorn or perfect. A future site visit to Spotify solidified that fact and made me respect them even more.</p>

<p>I found that each existing member was a <em>Connector</em> in their organizations, a <em>Maven</em> in terms of enterprise agility, and a healthy <em>Skeptic</em> towards the bulk of commercialized Agile. Ahmed was the <em>Salesman</em>. Steve was a little bit of the professor, but clearly demonstrated an Agile mindset and a vision to change the world of work. I caught his vision. It was refreshing and for the first time in several years, I learned several new things that I could try at Cerner as soon as I got back. The <em>Skeptic</em> was converted.</p>

<h3>Assessing and Applying at Cerner</h3>

<p>As I took a hard look at Cerner after returning from the visit, I realized that our success with things like <a href="http://engineering.cerner.com/2013/08/devcon/">DevCon</a> and the <a href="http://engineering.cerner.com/2013/08/devacademy/">DevAcademy</a> where we were truly industry trend setters had allowed us to be complacent in other areas that the other SDLC members had as strengths. In some cases, entropy was setting in and some of the benefits we realized from going Agile were no longer as prevalent. We weren’t in the danger zone, but some trends were heading in the wrong direction and merited a fresh look.</p>

<p>In other cases, SDLC companies were branching out with experiments in areas like HR, Finance, or Marketing that were bearing fruit. Their success led to a desire to see what we could do at Cerner.</p>

<p>Over the past two years, site visits have been held at Microsoft (Seattle), Ericsson (Stolkholm and Athelone Ireland), Barclays Bank (London), BMW (Munich), Riot Games (LA), Spotify (New York), Vistaprint (Boston), Fidelity Investments (Boston), CH Robinson (Chicago), and Cerner. Without exception, from each set of site visits, at least three action items have been taken by the Cerner attendees to improve Cerner. There is a renewed vigor towards an Agile mindset that had waned over the past 3-4 years.
At the beginning, Shahzad Zafar and I were the only representatives for Cerner. Now we have four Cerner associates at each site visit and have many other associates engage in deep dive conversations on special topics like DevOps, Shadow IT, or HR.</p>

<h3>Learning and Sharing</h3>

<p>Part of the SDLC is to learn from each other and then share those messages back into the broader community. There is deep, rich learning that can be gained from blending large companies like Ericcson with over 100K employees with a mid-tier company like Cerner (20K+), smaller companies like Vistaprint (5k+) and &ldquo;born Agile&rdquo; start-ups like Riot Games.</p>

<p>While each SDLC member has software components as part of the services that we offer to our clients, we operate in different verticals. The lessons we learn are universal and are not limited to a specific market or niche.</p>

<p>At the end of 2016, the SDLC members got together and <a href="http://www.sdlearningconsortium.org/what-we-have-learned/">summarized our learnings</a> from the year in a paper that Steve then presented at the 2016 Drucker Forum.</p>

<p>Personally, I have gone from the Skeptic to a very vocal evangelist, sharing the combined Cerner and SDLC story at the 2016 KC PMI Conference, <a href="http://2016.leanagilekc.com/sessions/the-future-is-here/">2016 LeanAgileKC</a>, 2017 Business Agility Conference, Agile 2017, 2017 Global PMI PMO Symposium as well as 2 of Cerner’s 2017 DevCons. Barclays Bank and Riot Games have been equally as active in sharing the SDLC learnings across the globe.</p>

<p>Steve Denning recently published an <a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/stevedenning/2017/10/15/what-is-agile-the-four-essential-elements/#24b8c3736e85">article in Forbes</a> with the findings that are starting to be cited as the core fundamentals for business agility across the globe with Cerner listed as a prevalent contributor.</p>

<p>Like the Agile Manifesto, the principles are simple, yet powerful:</p>

<ul>
<li>Delighting Customers</li>
<li>Descaling Work</li>
<li>Enterprise-wide Agility</li>
<li>Nurture Culture</li>
</ul>


<h3>The Future</h3>

<p>The SDLC is currently viewed as the leader in business agility practices and is shaping the speakers and agendas for the <a href="http://businessagilityconf.com/">Business Agility Conferences</a> globally. We continue to expand membership to include new companies who meet the criteria of a leader in agility and have a story to tell. Current members have grown to include Barclays Bank, Vistaprint, Fidelity Investments, Target, American Express, and All State are all candidates to join in 2018.</p>

<p>The brightest future is not about the SDLC but about Cerner and what we can accomplish based on learning from other SDLC members. Our 2018 Vision aligns well with the SDLC learnings and several strategies to achieve our vision include models based on what other SDLC members have already proven to be successful.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bad Design Is Bad for Your Health: Why Data Visualization Details Matter]]></title>
    <link href="http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/bad-design-is-bad-for-your-health-why-data-visualization-details-matter/"/>
    <updated>2018-01-04T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/bad-design-is-bad-for-your-health-why-data-visualization-details-matter</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Presentation Abstract by Jody Butts, Sr. User Experience Designer
Given on August 11, 2017 at the UX Australia Conference in Sydney</p>

<p><em>Full presentation audio and slides are available here:</em> <a href="http://www.uxaustralia.com.au/conferences/uxaustralia-2017/presentation/bad-design-is-bad-for-your-health-why-data-visualization-details-matter/">http://www.uxaustralia.com.au/conferences/uxaustralia-2017/presentation/bad-design-is-bad-for-your-health-why-data-visualization-details-matter/</a></p>

<p>The proper design of data visualization details is imperative for accurate and actionable data visualizations and dashboards. In the health care technology industry, even the smallest design detail on a graph of patient data can have a dramatic impact on patient safety and outcomes. For example, auto-adjusting y-axes in vitals graphs across patient charts in the EMR could cause change blindness which impacts the perception of patient data trends.</p>

<h2>Patient Safety</h2>

<p>As a user experience designer for Cerner, a health care IT company, patient safety is the foundation of my work. However, we see startling patient safety statistics around the world today. According to a Johns Hopkins <a href="https://hub.jhu.edu/2016/05/03/medical-errors-third-leading-cause-of-death/">study</a> from 2016, medical error is the third leading cause of death in the United States, following heart disease and cancer. The World Health Organization (WHO) <a href="http://www.who.int/features/factfiles/patient_safety/en/">estimates</a> that in developed countries across the globe, as many as one in ten patients are harmed while receiving hospital care.</p>

<p>Based on research the User Experience team at Cerner has done, there are several challenges the health care industry faces to ensure patient safety. From workflow and communication to external rules and regulation, there is a complex and interconnected web of factors.</p>

<p>While human error is unavoidable, there should be several defensive layers for every system. Despite the training, regulation, and process our health systems have, health care providers are still working in high-risk environments.</p>

<p>Understaffed health systems are flooded by people in need of care. On a bustling hospital floor with alarms going off at all hours, care team members running between patient rooms, and the need to use a computer to document patient data to meet government regulations, it is no wonder that medical error occurs.</p>

<p>Although we cannot ensure software will always work perfectly, we do have responsibility to ensure that the UI and UX layers of our systems are designed to protect our users and enable them to perform their tasks well.</p>

<h2>User Experience at Cerner</h2>

<p>I work for Cerner, a company at the intersection of health care and IT. Cerner technologies support the full continuum of care including clinical, financial, and patient engagement solutions. We have products licensed at more than 25,000 facilities across 35 countries.</p>

<p>As a part of Cerner’s UX team, I spend most of my time designing in the clinical space, working on projects for our main product: the electronic medical record (EMR), mainly used by doctors and nurses. Our technology is subject to a long list of legislation and regulations. Cerner has an entire team dedicated to reviewing standards for each country to ensure we are meeting all health IT requirements.</p>

<p>Our UX team also has training on how these standards impact our designs and research. Accessibility guidelines, patient privacy, and medication safety are just a few examples of regulation themes that guide our work. I focus on the rules that impact data visualizations and incorporate additional research to create safe and usable experiences.</p>

<p>The accurate graphical display of patient data has become my passion over the past two and a half years. Data visualization is a very powerful tool across industries, but I’m biased toward believing that its most amazing applications are in health care technology.</p>

<h2>Data Visualization in Pediatric Health Care</h2>

<p>For many years, the EMR was simply an input tool for charting patient data–most data review was solely displayed in rows and columns. Now we are creating meaningful displays of information for clinicians to support their decisions.</p>

<p>For example, the pediatric growth chart has been used by health care providers to track children’s growth from birth into adulthood for almost 40 years, starting on paper. The WHO and Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) have standards for healthy growth of height, weight, head circumference and more based on age, sex, and so on.</p>

<p>These standards are displayed as percentile lines that create a unique curve for each measure. When patient data is plotted, it becomes easy to identify if a child’s growth is progressing normally, or if there are abnormal patterns. For the first 20 years of an individual’s life, the growth chart is essential for tracking healthy growth progression. It is also an invaluable tool for communication between parents and clinicians.</p>

<p>As I have worked on a redesign of Cerner’s interactive growth chart tools, I have had the opportunity to observe clinicians using the growth chart in hospitals. In a Neonatal Intensive Care Unit (NICU) setting, or neonatal intensive care unit, physicians are making life-saving decisions for premature infants based on this information. For specialists, such as pediatric endocrinologists, the pattern of the trend line is often the first indication of diagnoses such as hypothyroidism. Can you imagine being able to recognize a disease by looking at a line graph?</p>

<h2>Data Visualization Design Details</h2>

<p>In a matter of clicks, we can take tables with thousands of numbers and transform them into graphics that provide immediate insights. From problem solving to storytelling, this information drives action across every industry.</p>

<p>There are countless examples of confusing and even misleading graphs–just try a Google search for “bad data visualizations,” and you’ll see what I mean. This assumed legitimacy is dangerous, especially when the design is sleek and appears trustworthy. The details that lead to accurate and impactful data visualizations fall into three categories: clarity, context, and creativity.</p>

<p>Clarity</p>

<p>Clarity is the foundation of data visualization design. We want to avoid all potential for confusion in order to empower our users to confidently make decisions. To achieve this, we must start with the basics. The title of a visualization should be succinct, yet provide the information needed to understand what data are being viewed and how they are being measured. If additional details are important to include, consider using supporting text below the title.</p>

<p>A dangerous mistake I regularly see while consulting on visualizations and dashboards is improper or missing labels. Do not make users guess what data points are being shown or how they are being measured. All axes in visualizations should be labeled. It is also important to include the unit of measure, which I like to include in parentheses next to the label. </p>

<p>While labels are important, I believe the most powerful element for clear data visualizations is proper scale. A simple mistake I often see is to start the y-axis of a bar graph at a value other than 0. Human eyes interpret the value of a bar to be equal to its length, so when the y-axis does not begin at 0, the values are not interpreted accurately. Similarly, the perception of data measured in percentages is also often skewed by scale. This sometimes occurs because a tool automatically adjusts the scale to fit to the data, but sometimes it is done to manipulate the data display. This <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=E91bGT9BjYk&amp;t=40s">example</a> of an ad from Chevy illustrates the power scale has on perception (starting at 0:45).</p>

<p>Context</p>

<p>Once there is a truthful and clear foundation for data, the following techniques can bring users quicker insights and increase their confidence in data interpretation.</p>

<p>If there is a normal, expected, or ideal range of values for the data, adding a target range is a simple but powerful way to add context. A light shaded region behind the grid lines can allow users to easily identify high and low values. Similar to a target range, a goal line can be added to indicate a discrete value that the plotted data should be achieving. A goal line and target range can be used together as well.</p>

<p>It’s important to mark visualizations and dashboards with the date it was published. I also recommend including the date or date range of the data as well in order to maintain trust and relevancy of your visualization.</p>

<p>Annotations are another simple way to provide your user with context. On-canvas notes and labels should be used sparingly, but can help highlight insights. These can be placed in context of a specific data point, a date or timeframe, etc.</p>

<p>Creativity</p>

<p>Once we have created a clear visualization and provided our user with additional context, we are ready to polish our design. There is great potential for creativity in data visualization, but it can cause more harm than good if done poorly. Let’s look at visual encoding methods, colors, and other visual design details that can enhance your visualization or dashboard.</p>

<p>Qualitative and quantitative data is visually encoded, or translated, through a variety of graphical methods that make up each visualization type. <a href="https://ils.unc.edu/courses/2015_spring/inls541_001/Readings/Cleveland%20and%20McGill%201985%20-%20Graphical%20Perception%20and%20Cleveland1985-Graphical%20Methods%20for%20Analyzing%20Scientific%20Data.pdf">Research</a> has been done on these visual encoding methods, giving us insights for human graphical perception. Statistician William Cleveland and his colleague, Robert McGill, tested the visual encoding methods and ranked them by accuracy of perception. Their findings give us a scientific foundation for data visualization.</p>

<p>Position is the best encoding method for accuracy, followed by length, angle, area, volume, and finally, with color taking the last spot. This means that color is not reliable for communicating data information in a graph. This aligns to the WCAG 2.0 accessibility <a href="https://www.w3.org/WAI/WCAG20/quickref/#visual-audio-contrast-without-color">guidelines</a>, which state that color cannot be used as the only visual means of conveying information, indicating an action, and so on. Second, bar, and line graphs are common for good reason–they are most effective for our brains to accurately understand. Ultimately, it’s always best to try a couple of options and compare their effectiveness.</p>

<p>Use color sparingly. Think of it as a tool for drawing attention to the most important insights. If everything has color, especially on a dashboard, nothing will stand out. Since approximately 10% of the population is color blind, we should avoid using red and green together on a visualization. <a href="http://colororacle.org/">Color Oracle</a> is a great color blindness simulator that you can use to see how your colors appear for users with these vision deficiencies.</p>

<p>Ensure you maintain high contrast between colors by avoiding very light or very dark shades. The <a href="http://colormine.org/delta-e-calculator/">Delta-E calculation</a> measures the distance between two colors. At Cerner, we ensure a difference of at least 3.5.</p>

<p>The best way to test the colors you are using is to print it out in grayscale. Make sure you can still match plotted data to its labels. Better yet, get additional eyes on it. This test ensures that color is not being utilized as the only way to communicate meaning.</p>

<h2>Visualizations are the Key to Understanding Data</h2>

<p>The world is overflowing with big, complex problems, but we also have big, complex data to solve them. This big, complex data exists as numbers that can go on forever. Data visualizations are the key for humans to understand it all. Data must be visualized clearly and effectively to enable professionals across industries to understand it, make decisions, and take action based on it.</p>

<p>We can revolutionize health care and other fields through the way we visualize data. The design details matter. Through clear, contextual, and creative data visualizations, we can drive action that will change the world and even save lives.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[2^5 Coding Competition 2017: 32 Lines or Less]]></title>
    <link href="http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/2-to-the-5th-coding-competition-2017/"/>
    <updated>2017-12-19T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/2-to-the-5th-coding-competition-2017</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>The Competition</h2>

<p>Part of Cerner&rsquo;s engineering culture is to celebrate technology. This past fall, we had our annual celebration for <a href="https://twitter.com/CernerEng/status/908047795768217600">Programmers’ Day</a>. We celebrated the day with great food (taco bar and ice cream) and an evening of trivia.</p>

<table>
<tr valign="top">
<td>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Topping off Programmers&#39; Day with a taco bar and trivia night with <a href="https://twitter.com/geekswhodrink?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@geekswhodrink</a> <a href="https://t.co/pSjqBVBHxK">pic.twitter.com/pSjqBVBHxK</a></p>&mdash; Cerner Engineering (@CernerEng) <a href="https://twitter.com/CernerEng/status/908102894574071808?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">September 13, 2017</a></blockquote>
<script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
</td>
<td>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Happy Programmers&#39; Day! Celebrating with an ice cream social. <a href="https://t.co/bakBeOx20M">pic.twitter.com/bakBeOx20M</a></p>&mdash; Cerner Engineering (@CernerEng) <a href="https://twitter.com/CernerEng/status/908043961599754240?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">September 13, 2017</a></blockquote>
<script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
</td>
</tr>
</table>


<p>With our celebrations, we also like to blend in challenges or activities that can mold desired behaviors. Therefore, as part of Programmers&#8217; Day, we also kicked off a programming competition (our third year of organizing the competition). For 32 days (September 13 &ndash; October 16), associates submitted small snippets of code (32 lines or less) in any language that represented the concept of engineering impact. After 32 days, our panel of judges sorted through the code and assigned a winner to each of the following categories:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Best Representation</strong>:  What captures the concept of &ldquo;engineering impact&rdquo; the best?</li>
<li><strong>Most Obfuscated</strong>: Which code snippet was the most difficult to understand?</li>
<li><strong>Greatest Variety in Languages</strong>:  Which repository contains the most variety in programming languages across submissions?</li>
<li><strong>Most First Hand Submissions</strong>: Which participant submitted the most code that relates to <a href="https://www.firsthandfoundation.org/">First Hand Foundation</a> and its mission to &ldquo;impact&rdquo; others?</li>
</ul>


<p>As with anywhere, engineers at Cerner are busy. Asking them to do something additional, like a coding competition, imposes challenges on participation based on their availability of time. However, we found that by organizing the competition for engineers to explore and share what they are working on, in small and consumable bites of code, helped in keeping it a simple time investment and gained participation. Furthermore, it helped reinforce a routine behavior to continually look and evaluate different technologies and languages.</p>

<p>Just like tweets, by having small code examples being shared, it was easy for others to also learn what they were doing. We facilitated sharing these tweets by making a dashboard which served up crawled results from GitHub. This was achieved by having participants including a specific phase in their code (like a hashtag), which could then be pulled from GitHub’s search and built into a dashboard. This dashboard was based on how we originally achieved this in our earlier <a href="http://engineering.cerner.com/2013/08/the-30-days-of-code-experiment/">30 Days of Code competition</a>.</p>

<h2>The Winners</h2>

<p>Our winners from this year are as follows:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Best Representation</strong>:  <a href="https://github.com/AnEmortalKid/such-interview">Jan Monterrubio</a></li>
<li><strong>Most Obfuscated</strong>: <a href="https://github.com/dbailey31/Cerner">Douglas Bailey</a> <em>(Honorable mention: <a href="https://github.com/joehuck/bash_projects">Joe Huck</a>)</em></li>
<li><strong>Greatest Variety in Languages</strong>: <a href="https://github.com/afrin216/2to5">Afrin Subair</a></li>
<li><strong>Most First Hand Submissions</strong>: <a href="https://github.com/jvarness/cerner-2-to-the-5th">Jake Varness</a></li>
</ul>


<p>Congratulations to the winners and thank you to everyone who submitted code. Until next year!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Announcing Bunsen: FHIR Data With Apache Spark]]></title>
    <link href="http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/announcing-bunsen-fhir-data-with-apache-spark/"/>
    <updated>2017-11-27T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/announcing-bunsen-fhir-data-with-apache-spark</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We&rsquo;re excited to open source <a href="http://engineering.cerner.com/bunsen">Bunsen</a>, a library to make analyzing <a href="http://hl7.org/fhir/STU3/resourcelist.html">FHIR data</a> with <a href="https://spark.apache.org/">Apache Spark</a> simple and scalable. Bunsen encodes FHIR resources directly into Apache Spark&rsquo;s native data structures. This lets users leverage well-defined FHIR data models directly within Spark SQL.</p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s a simple query against a table of FHIR observations that produces a table of
heart rate values:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='python'><span class='line'><span class="n">spark</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">sql</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s">&quot;&quot;&quot;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="s">select subject.reference person_id,</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="s">       effectiveDateTime date_time,</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="s">       valueQuantity.value value</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="s">from observations</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="s">where in_valueset(code, &#39;heart_rate&#39;)</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="s"> &quot;&quot;&quot;</span><span class="p">)</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">show</span><span class="p">()</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Which prints a table like this:</p>

<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th></th>
<th align="left">person_id        </th>
<th align="left">date_time    </th>
<th align="left">value   </th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td align="left">Patient/123      </td>
<td align="left">2016-12-27   </td>
<td align="left">54.0000 </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td align="left">Patient/123      </td>
<td align="left">2017-04-18   </td>
<td align="left">60.0000</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>


<p>Notice that each field in the above SQL is fully defined by the <a href="http://hl7.org/fhir/STU3/observation.html">FHIR Observation model</a>. This is because the table schemas are generated directly from FHIR resource definitions, ensuring these queries exactly match other FHIR-based views of the same data.</p>

<p>Bunsen also provides a collection of helpful functions to make querying data easy. The above query includes the <em>in_valueset</em> user-defined function, allowing users to use code value sets directly in the query. You can see the <a href="http://engineering.cerner.com/bunsen/introduction.html#bring-your-own-value-sets">Bunsen value set documentation</a> for details.</p>

<h3>Scalability and Performance</h3>

<p>Because Bunsen encodes FHIR resources in Apache Spark&rsquo;s efficient binary format, we get all of Spark&rsquo;s scalability and performance advantages. Simple queries across billions of FHIR resources typically return in single-digit seconds in internal clusters. Arbitrary joins and aggregations of complex datasets scale with your Apache Spark cluster. We take advantage of Spark&rsquo;s built-in support for <a href="https://parquet.apache.org/">Apache Parquet</a> to read and write FHIR with an efficient columnar data format that is readable by other systems as well.</p>

<h3>Sophisticated Queries</h3>

<p>Spark SQL offers rich query semantics that can now be used directly over FHIR data models. For instance,
here is a query that builds a timeseries-like table directly from a collection of observations by simply
grouping items by the person and time period. This is just standard Spark SQL wrapped around
our simple valueset-based function.</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
<span class='line-number'>14</span>
<span class='line-number'>15</span>
<span class='line-number'>16</span>
<span class='line-number'>17</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='sql'><span class='line'><span class="k">select</span> <span class="n">subject</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">reference</span> <span class="n">patient_id</span><span class="p">,</span>
</span><span class='line'>       <span class="k">year</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">effectiveDateTime</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="n">obs_year</span><span class="p">,</span>
</span><span class='line'>       <span class="k">month</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">effectiveDateTime</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="n">obs_month</span><span class="p">,</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>       <span class="k">avg</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">if</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">in_valueset</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">code</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="s1">&#39;glucose_level&#39;</span><span class="p">),</span>
</span><span class='line'>              <span class="n">valueQuantity</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">value</span><span class="p">,</span>
</span><span class='line'>              <span class="k">null</span><span class="p">))</span> <span class="n">avg_glucose_level</span><span class="p">,</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>       <span class="k">avg</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">if</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">in_valueset</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">code</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="s1">&#39;bun&#39;</span><span class="p">),</span>
</span><span class='line'>              <span class="n">valueQuantity</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">value</span><span class="p">,</span>
</span><span class='line'>              <span class="k">null</span><span class="p">))</span> <span class="n">avg_bun</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">from</span> <span class="n">observations</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">group</span> <span class="k">by</span> <span class="n">subject</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">reference</span><span class="p">,</span>
</span><span class='line'>         <span class="k">year</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">effectiveDateTime</span><span class="p">),</span>
</span><span class='line'>         <span class="k">month</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">effectiveDateTime</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">order</span> <span class="k">by</span> <span class="n">patient_id</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">obs_year</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">obs_month</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Typical queries may aggregate many other types of data and join to conditions, allergies, or other tables
to build a more complete report. All of this can be done interactively over billions of records.</p>

<h3>Java Usage</h3>

<p>Bunsen uses the <a href="http://hapifhir.io/">HAPI FHIR</a> library to represent data in object form. Java users can convert their objects from the HAPI to Spark-native structures and back with a few lines of code. Here&rsquo;s an example:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='java'><span class='line'><span class="n">FhirEncoders</span> <span class="n">encoders</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">FhirEncoders</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="na">forStu3</span><span class="o">().</span><span class="na">getOrCreate</span><span class="o">();</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="n">List</span><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="n">Condition</span><span class="o">&gt;</span> <span class="n">conditionList</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="c1">// A list of org.hl7.fhir.dstu3.model.Condition objects.</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="n">Dataset</span><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="n">Condition</span><span class="o">&gt;</span> <span class="n">conditions</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">spark</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="na">createDataset</span><span class="o">(</span><span class="n">conditionList</span><span class="o">,</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="n">encoders</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="na">of</span><span class="o">(</span><span class="n">Condition</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="na">class</span><span class="o">));</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="c1">// Query for conditions based on arbitrary Spark SQL expressions</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="n">Dataset</span><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="n">Condition</span><span class="o">&gt;</span> <span class="n">activeConditions</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">conditions</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="o">.</span><span class="na">where</span><span class="o">(</span><span class="s">&quot;clinicalStatus == &#39;active&#39; and verificationStatus == &#39;confirmed&#39;&quot;</span><span class="o">);</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Users can also leverage Spark&rsquo;s built-in functionality to write these datasets to tables and query these tables later.</p>

<h3>Using and Contributing</h3>

<p>Bunsen is available under the Apache 2.0 license. The initial release targets <a href="https://spark.apache.org/releases/spark-release-2-1-0.html">Apache Spark 2.1</a> and <a href="https://www.hl7.org/fhir/STU3/index.html">FHIR STU3</a>, and support for additional versions will emerge over time.</p>

<p>Check out Bunsen&rsquo;s <a href="http://engineering.cerner.com/bunsen">documentation</a> and <a href="https://github.com/cerner/bunsen">GitHub Repository</a> for more on using or contributing to the project.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Celebrating World Usability Day at Cerner]]></title>
    <link href="http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/celebrating-world-usability-day-at-cerner/"/>
    <updated>2017-11-14T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/celebrating-world-usability-day-at-cerner</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>World Usability Day is celebrated worldwide on the second Thursday in November every year. Across the globe, organizations host events and use this day to provide education on how to make products easier to use and simpler to access, as well as to celebrate progress in this pursuit.</p>

<p>The World Usability Day theme for 2017 was &ldquo;Inclusion.&rdquo; Inclusive design considers the range of abilities, language and other forms of human difference when creating a solution. Designing with these in mind from the start can create a better suited product for everyone.</p>

<p>Cerner&rsquo;s Kansas City-based User Experience (UX) team celebrated by hosting a day filled with five speaker sessions and an afternoon workshop for Cerner associates on November 9, in the Innovations Campus event space. Following the theme, the speakers covered topics such as accessibility and universal design.</p>

<p>Lauren Bock, User Experience Designer on the UX team, kicked off the day with a presentation on <em>Universal Design: The Equality of Experience</em>. Lauren explained how designing only for the &ldquo;average user,&rdquo; or including only the minimum accessibility requirements, can result in something designed for no one. We each have unique needs and designing products, services and experiences designed in a way that honors those needs can result in a better outcome for everyone. She shared how designing universally from the beginning not only makes a better product, but does so for a larger number of users.</p>

<p>Following the keynote, Dr. Ben Wilkerson, Physician Executive for Cerner&rsquo;s Population Health organization, shared his take on why <em>Healthcare Software is Failing at the Box Office</em>. In his talk, Dr. Wilkerson drew comparisons between healthcare software and the movie industry. He highlighted how healthcare software can take cues from films in the way that production teams spend the majority of time in research, preparation, and planning, before the costly filming step. Dr. Wilkerson also compared the different roles of the production team to those designing software at Cerner and how they can work together to create a compelling result.</p>

<p>In the last session for the morning, Scott Wilmarth, Senior User Experience Designer on the UX team, shared his personal and real-world story on the importance of accessibility in <em>Retinas, Accessibility, and More Stuff I Learned About on the Way to Get Thai Food</em>. After an unexpected loss of vision in one of his eyes, Scott has become an accessibility advocate, sharing his story with development teams, Cerner Health Conference attendees and others at Cerner. Scott shared the impact of accessibility and shared ways for designers, developers and project teams at Cerner to integrate accessibility into their processes. He explained that designing for accessibility is not just required, but the right thing to do. Accounting for different abilities in design can ultimately create better products for all users.</p>

<p>After lunch, Michael Turman, the Senior Strategist for the Reference Data Management team, gave his perspective on why <em>We&rsquo;re Going to Need a Bigger Boat</em> when designing our solutions at Cerner. Coming from the Cerner Consulting organization, Michael highlighted the importance of the post-development, implementation and maintenance steps of Cerner software with our clients. He provided tips for teams to design for these user bases and with implementation in mind. He explained that by designing for users both upstream and downstream in the development process we can create better experiences.</p>

<p>Dr. Jeff Wall, Director of the Physician Strategy and Medical Specialties organization, concluded the speaking sessions with his talk <em>Designing the Physician Workflow: Technical vs. Adaptive considerations for success</em>. Dr. Wall summarized it perfectly, &ldquo;change is hard.&rdquo; How do we help users effectively handle change as we constantly improve our healthcare software? He explained that when designing software for our users, we must be considerate of adaptive challenges, making sure to distinguish between technical changes and changes to human behavior. With years of experience as a clinician, Dr. Wall explained methods for Cerner teams to prepare for and introduce change to our users.</p>

<p>The last activity for the day was a Virtual Reality Workshop sponsored by the Cerner Labs team, who focus on the investigation of emerging technologies and how to use those to create new ways of engaging with data. Workshop participants were able to experience a scenario using Virtual Reality (VR) headsets. Small groups led by UX team members replayed the scenario and used the technique of Journey Mapping to lay out the course of the experience, ultimately discovering areas of opportunity for improvement for the scenario. Groups reconvened and shared each of their maps to learn from each other.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2017-11-14-celebrating-world-usability-day-at-cerner/ux-vr.jpg"></p>

<p>The day concluded with a public evening meet-up hosted in partnership with the User Experience Professionals Association of Kansas City, a local non-profit organization focused on UX. Attendees were invited to tour the User Experience Lab where the Human Factors Research team conducts usability tests and other research studies. This tour was followed by a design challenge where attendees broke out into teams and collaborated on creating quick solutions to design prompts focused on inclusive design.</p>

<p>Just around the corner from the User Experience Lab at the Innovations campus is a hand-drawn installation of epic proportion about World Usability Day. These 20 ft. long, 10 ft. tall installations of content are created and drawn by UX team members, and will rotate every quarter. Located next to the glass wall is an interactive puzzle also put together by the UX team, highlighting User Experience Vice President, Paul Weaver’s definition of UX: &ldquo;UX is the nexus between the user and the machine; a combination of design and research that works to perfect human-computer interaction.&rdquo;</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2017-11-14-celebrating-world-usability-day-at-cerner/ux-glass-wall.jpg"></p>

<p><em>Photos by Lai Xu and Kelsey Daly</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Accessibility and Usability: On the Road to Great UX]]></title>
    <link href="http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/accessibility-and-usability-on-the-road-to-great-ux/"/>
    <updated>2017-10-09T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/accessibility-and-usability-on-the-road-to-great-ux</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In 2010, a group of designers from Columbus, Ohio set out to create a grassroots, cross-discipline, and creative conference. Since that first event, Midwest UX has been an ongoing tradition that attracts innovative ideas and provides an opportunity for regional professions to engage in discussion with other professionals. Last year, Amber Wilks and Dr. Becca Green were invited to take their talk from DevCon 2016 on the road to Midwest UX. On October 20, 2016, they presented Accessibility &amp; Usability: The Equality of Experience in Louisville, KY.</p>

<p>At Midwest UX, the talk covered all of the great content from DevCon enhanced by examples of how accessibility specifically affects our solutions used by our consumer market or clinical staff. Each point covered demonstrated how UX and development work together to achieve an accessible software solution and the importance of crafting equally awesome experiences for all of our users. When people talk about accessibility, there are some common myths that go along with the topic. So the talks starts off by covering three myths of accessibility that have impacted the health care community, and Cerner in particular.</p>

<p>The first myth covered was that project teams look at accessibility as a minefield they must cross to achieve accessible software. The truth is that it is simply a blend of legislation and regulation that aims to eliminate barriers in technology for people with disabilities. In fact there are two main forms of standards used in the U.S. to define accessible content, Section 508 and W3&rsquo;s Web Content Accessibility Guidelines. While they serve similar purposes, there are some very key differences. They different in terms of the technology they cover, the organization of the guidelines, and their application. However, they are just a small part of a landscape of legislation and regulation that make up accessibility.</p>

<p>The second myth covered the assumption that accessibility is all about screen readers and alt tags. In reality, screen readers are just a small subset of assistive technologies. Low-vision or blind users only make up a small slice of all U.S. citizens with disabilities. There are a variety of assistive technologies to aid every type of disability. The third and final myth we covered is specific to the healthcare industry; that clinicians aren&rsquo;t disabled so accessibility isn&rsquo;t a priority for our users. The truth is that clinicians are not immune to disabilities. In fact, a study in the British Journal of General Practice that found that the proportion of male doctors with color vision deficiency was at 8%, in line with the percentage of the general population.</p>

<p>As the guidelines for accessibility have evolved, so has the organization of these guidelines such that they can now be organized into 4 tenant principles: perceivable, operable, understandable, and robust.</p>

<h3>Perceivable</h3>

<p>Information and UI components must be presented in ways users can perceive. In other words, information can&rsquo;t be invisible. We do that by making information distinguishable and by providing alternative forms of content.</p>

<p>To make information distinguishable, the foundations involve color math and text zoom. To create distinguishable information using color there are two mathematical calculations that can be used to ensure the content is both legible and discernible. To ensure the content is legible, Cerner follows WCAG&rsquo;s (Web Content Accessibility Guidelines) color contrast guidelines include Guideline 1.4.3, which states that &ldquo;the visual presentation of text and images of text has a contrast ration of at least 4.5:1.&rdquo; To check if your information is legible, the WCAG recommends using the WebAIM Color Contrast Checker. This tool simply requires that you enter in your text, or foreground, color and background color and it will tell you to what degree you meet the contrast guidelines.</p>

<p>The second calculation ensures users can perceive changes in the content. While this calculation is not part of accessibility guidelines, we leverage the calculation as a baseline metric for interaction indications (i.e., hovers, click states, icons, etc.). This numerical value starts at 0 and the higher the number, the greater the difference between two colors. We recommend a minimum value of 3.5, which represents an obvious difference.</p>

<p>The other part of having distinguishable content is allowing for text zooming. In the U.S. alone, 8.1 million people have a vision disability. In March 2013, WebAIM conducted a survey of users with low vision, which found that the bulk of accessible technologies used by these individuals included some form of text resizing. Text zooming is a method used to scale text up and down while retaining the screen formatting and layout. A successful text zoom is when the content can be resized up to 200% and everything on the screen scales uniformly and scroll bars are provided if needed.</p>

<p>The second part of providing perceivable content is to provide content that supports all the senses. A video may require a paired audio supplement. An audio file may require a written transcript. Just like the transcript we provided with our talk. While people with vision disabilities are a small slice of the population, those with hearing disabilities make up a larger portion and are more likely to be employed. So it&rsquo;s far more likely that a user would need supplemental text than they would be using a screen reader.</p>

<p>One of the most common ways to provide alternative content is through captioning. Captioning is the transcription of speech and important sound effects. Not to be confused with subtitling which is a written translation of dialogue.</p>

<h3>Operable</h3>

<p>UI components and navigation must be operable. In other words, the UI cannot require an interaction that a user cannot perform. Most assistive technologies used by people with disabilities emulate how a keyboard functions. So a good rule of thumb is that if it can be navigated with a keyboard, then it is accessible. Operability is about giving the user control with controls to pause, stop, and hide moving, blinking, or scrolling content.</p>

<h3>Understandable</h3>

<p>Information and the operation of the user interface must be understandable. In other words, the content and operation cannot be beyond a user&rsquo;s understanding. Users consume content in a variety of ways and we must be flexible to accommodate all of the different ways they might access information. Therefore, it&rsquo;s important to ensure that content is housed in a structured framework to facilitate navigation.</p>

<p>As part of the talk, an example of the experience a screen reader user might have while navigating a well known and popular website is presented. This set of videos demonstrates some of the common problems found with navigation such as duplicate links, ambiguous link names, and long navigation. The results of an automated accessibility tool are presented to highlight that not only are automated tools important for assessing accessibility but that it also requires a manual component.</p>

<h3>Robust</h3>

<p>Content must be robust enough that it can be interpreted reliably by a wide range of user agents. In other words, user must be able to access the content as technologies advance. Since there are a lot of different types of assistive technology, as these technologies change, so does the landscape of accessibility. Being future friendly isn&rsquo;t as hard as keeping up with technology. It&rsquo;s actually as easy as sticking to &ldquo;the basics.&rdquo;</p>

<ul>
<li>Write valid code</li>
<li>Optimize navigation</li>
<li>Stick to standards</li>
<li>Stay away from known hazards</li>
</ul>


<p>The key to crafting equally compelling experiences for all is the concept of Universal Design. Universal design is the design and composition of buildings, products, and services so they can be accessed, understood, and used by all people. It&rsquo;s an inclusive approach to design. When you design for the average person, you&rsquo;re actually designing for no one. We are each unique and have different needs. We want to encourage you to not think of accessibility as a flat, one-size-fits-all solution but instead as a multifaceted, configurable space. It&rsquo;s more than just what&rsquo;s on the screen though. It&rsquo;s about the environment and the users in that environment.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Jwala Joins Cerner's Open Source]]></title>
    <link href="http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/jwala-joins-cerner-open-source/"/>
    <updated>2017-09-27T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/jwala-joins-cerner-open-source</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>Introducing Jwala, a Resource Manager for the Apache Community</h3>

<p><a href="http://tomcat.apache.org/">Apache Tomcat</a> and <a href="https://httpd.apache.org/">Apache httpd</a> are hardened, scalable, and reliable open-source solutions. Widely adopted, these solutions are commonly used to host and load-balance Java applications.</p>

<p>Configuring and managing a small set of elements is relatively easy, but once you start scaling out your application and platform, things get complicated. Questions such as &ldquo;How do I update the heap or database pool-size across hundreds of Java Virtual Machines (JVMs)?&rdquo; arise. Although commercial solutions exist to solve this and other similar problems, an open-source solution was not available &ndash; until now.</p>

<p>Originally designed and developed to accommodate Cerner&rsquo;s complex topologies, Jwala was developed to automate deploying our web applications here at Cerner. Now Cerner is donating Jwala as open source. Making contributions to development communities is an important part of Cerner&rsquo;s engineering culture. We love it when we&rsquo;re able to give back to the community, and we&rsquo;re sure you&rsquo;ll love Jwala!</p>

<p>A Cerner platform based on Apache Tomcat and Apache httpd, Jwala enables the configuration, deployment, and management of logical groups of Tomcat JVMs load-balanced by Apache web servers.</p>

<p>With Jwala you can configure, deploy, and manage your large-scale Tomcat and Apache httpd topology at an enterprise scale. You can create and persist definitions of Group instances that include web applications, JVMs, web servers, and other resources, and expose them through a RESTful interface, Jwala&rsquo;s REST API, to perform management operations on the group.</p>

<p>Jwala utilizes a defined file system structure and Secure Shell (SSH) agents on each machine to manage running Tomcat instances on remote servers. Jwala&rsquo;s application deployment model knows how to request current status from each Tomcat and httpd instance. Jwala also is able to update each instance as changes are made to the configuration and allows maintenance operations to be executed from a central console. Last but not least, Jwala maintains an audit log of all the operations or changes performed on any of its managed resources.</p>

<p>So, if you are someone in development, operations, or management looking for an easier way to configure and manage a large Tomcat topology, <a href="https://github.com/cerner/jwala">check out Jwala</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Engineers Overseas for SMART and FHIR (FHIR DevDays 2016)]]></title>
    <link href="http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/engineers-overseas-for-smart-and-fhir/"/>
    <updated>2017-09-21T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/engineers-overseas-for-smart-and-fhir</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In a <a href="http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/engineers-on-the-road-for-smart-and-fhir/">previous post</a>, we discussed the need to provide education around our ecosystem and implementation of the <a href="http://hl7.org/fhir/overview-dev.html">FHIRⓇ</a> and <a href="http://docs.smarthealthit.org/">SMARTⓇ</a> standards for developers and how we did so at our annual Cerner Health Conference. That same week, we were also a part of <a href="http://www.fhirdevdays.com/">FHIR DevDays</a>, which included a track entitled &ldquo;Apps in the EHR.&rdquo; We worked alongside track participants who were seeking to integrate their apps in a variety of EHRs, including Cerner.</p>

<p>FHIR DevDays is a conference put on by <a href="http://fhir.furore.com/">Furore</a> in Amsterdam. This year, over 250 participants from all over the world gathered to attend tutorials given by FHIR community leaders in the mornings and participate in hands-on sessions in the afternoons.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2017-09-21-engineers-overseas-for-smart-and-fhir/Devdays_2016.jpg"></p>

<p>Cerner co-led the &ldquo;Apps in the EHR&rdquo; track. This track was comprised of roughly 20 people from across France, Germany, Ireland, Israel, Italy, Netherlands, Norway, Spain, Switzerland, the United Kingdom, and the United States. <a href="https://twitter.com/JoshCMandel">Josh Mandel</a> kicked things off with a tutorial on <a href="http://smarthealthit.org/">SMART</a> and how to <a href="http://docs.smarthealthit.org/">get started</a> building cross-vendor applications. Afterward, we met with track participants to show them how to get plugged into Cerner&rsquo;s sandbox and ecosystem. We started out by covering our <a href="https://code.cerner.com/">documentation launchpoint</a>, registering applications in our <a href="https://code.cerner.com/developer/smart-on-fhir">code console</a>, and going over our <a href="http://fhir.cerner.com/">technical documentation</a>. For those who didn&rsquo;t come to the conference with an existing application to work on, we provided a <a href="http://engineering.cerner.com/smart-on-fhir-tutorial">tutorial</a>. With those tools in hand, they were ready to get to work!</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2017-09-21-engineers-overseas-for-smart-and-fhir/hands-on.jpg"></p>

<br />


<p><img class="center" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2017-09-21-engineers-overseas-for-smart-and-fhir/hands-on2.png"></p>

<p>Over the course of the three afternoons, we assisted people as they used SMART and FHIR for the first time, but also people with experience in FHIR who were looking to get their technical and business questions answered about integrating with Cerner.
Several of the projects were plugged into multiple sandboxes. The developers shared that once their app was working in one sandbox, it was easy to plug into others, which is exactly how it should be!</p>

<p>When we gave our closing presentation, we actually had some technical difficulties loading up the slides. Little did we know that <a href="https://twitter.com/grahamegrieve">Grahame Grieve</a>, the original architect of FHIR, snapped a picture and would use it shortly in his <a href="https://vimeo.com/192190127">closing keynote</a> on FHIR’s future.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2017-09-21-engineers-overseas-for-smart-and-fhir/closing-keynote.jpg"></p>

<p><a href="https://twitter.com/fhir_furore/status/799626324927053824">With this image on screen</a>, he stated: &ldquo;[to us:] Well done. [to the rest of the audience:] Next time somebody in your acquaintance tells you that certain vendors aren&rsquo;t invested in interoperability, I want you to think about this. That&rsquo;s part of what the FHIR community is about, alright? Cerner and Epic on the stage together. It&rsquo;s not special anymore, even. It&rsquo;s great!&rdquo;</p>

<p>FHIR DevDays is Europe&rsquo;s biggest FHIR conference and many attendees don&rsquo;t typically make it to the tri-annual HL7 Working Group Meetings that focus on the formation and evolution of the specification. We were pleased to be a part of that gathering and to work alongside people interested in engaging with Cerner. But, we were also encouraged by the comments Grahame and others gave as they expressed appreciation that Cerner would be present and show our interest and dedication to the standard. We look forward to being back at DevDays 2017 this November to lead tracks on SMART &amp; FHIR and CDS Hooks.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[ShipIt IX Day: Summer 2017]]></title>
    <link href="http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/shipit-ix-day-summer-2017/"/>
    <updated>2017-09-11T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/shipit-ix-day-summer-2017</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2017-09-11-shipit-ix-day-summer-2017/shipit-day-ix-6.jpg"></p>

<p>There is no better way to end summer than with ShipIt Day! We kicked off our ninth ShipIt Day on August 10th, with more than 75 Cerner associates signed up. Nineteen different teams worked for 24 hours straight to complete their projects. For those unfamiliar with the event, ShipIt Day is a 24 hour hackathon for internal associates to create something innovative, usable, and value-adding. This was the second ShipIt held at our new <a href="https://www.bizjournals.com/kansascity/news/2017/02/10/get-a-sneak-peek-inside-cerner-s-new-innovations.html">Innovations Campus</a>. Associates love using our new campus for ShipIt because of the game rooms and collaboration spaces! One new addition to this quarter’s ShipIt Day was the scavenger hunt. Participants were given a list of crazy tasks to accomplish within the 24 hours. Some tasks included spoon feeding a fellow team member, completing the obstacle courses around the outdoor walking trail, and finding binary codes around campus and decoding them. Shoutout to the winners of the scavenger hunt: the Jumpy Woodchucks team!</p>

<div align="center">
  <img class="center" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2017-09-11-shipit-ix-day-summer-2017/shipit-day-ix-1.jpg">
  <sub>Teams were given lots of snacks and drinks to keep them fueled for the next 24 hours.</sub>
</div>




<div align="center">
  <img class="center" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2017-09-11-shipit-ix-day-summer-2017/shipit-day-ix-3.jpg">
  <sub>Collaboration is key to a successful project.</sub>
</div>


<p>For dinner, we brought in some of the biggest pizzas Kansas City has to offer from Pizza 51. By dinner time the participants were ready to chow down and give their brains a break. Dinner entertainment included <em>School of Rock</em> and <em>Futurama</em>.</p>

<div align="center">
  <img class="center" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2017-09-11-shipit-ix-day-summer-2017/shipit-day-ix-11.jpg">
  <sub>Chaos ensued as everyone runs to grab some pizza!</sub>
</div>




<div align="center">
  <img class="center" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2017-09-11-shipit-ix-day-summer-2017/shipit-day-ix-2.jpg">
  <sub><i>School of Rock</i> was played during dinner.</sub>
</div>


<p>Associates stayed overnight and worked around the clock to ensure their projects would be complete by presentation time. However, sometimes you just need a nap.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2017-09-11-shipit-ix-day-summer-2017/shipit-day-ix-4.jpg"></p>

<p>Presentation day is always an exciting one. After 24 hours of hard work, the teams have 4 minutes to show off their product to their peers and a panel of rock-star judges. A special thank you to Brian Wallace, Amon Woolridge, and Greg Whitsitt for judging this round.</p>

<div align="center">
  <table>
    <tr>
      <td align="center">
        <img class="center" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2017-09-11-shipit-ix-day-summer-2017/shipit-day-ix-9.jpg">
        <sub>We always start presentation day off with bagels for breakfast from Panera.</sub>
      </td>
      <td align="center">
        <img class="center" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2017-09-11-shipit-ix-day-summer-2017/shipit-day-ix-12.jpg">
        <sub>The Prize Table.</sub>
      </td>
    </tr>
  </table>
</div>


<h3>Team Bravo Avocado</h3>

<p>ShipIt Day IX teams brought their A game. The projects get more intricate and more impressive each time around. ShipIt Day is a great way to show off the talent we have at Cerner. Team Bravo Avocado, made up of Thomas Clay, Jacob Zimmerman, Jan Monterrubio, Max Schroeder, and Elisha Boozer took first place! Judges were impressed by their live demo and humorous presentation style.</p>

<blockquote><p>Our project was an enhancement for Millennium Java services that removes certain required pieces of server implementation by adding custom annotations. Consumers will no longer have the same restrictions from traditional service generation (i.e. defining a generation file, method naming), because the annotation processor will generate that for them. Also, the framework can bind the structured request/reply objects to an annotated object of their choice. These annotations remove lots of redundant code and gives consumers more time to focus on what matters.</p></blockquote>

<div align="center">
  <img class="center" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2017-09-11-shipit-ix-day-summer-2017/shipit-day-ix-8.jpg">
  <sub>Team Bravo Avocado with the Golden Keyboard.</sub>
</div>


<h3>Team E=MC Hammer</h3>

<p>Second place went to team E=MC Hammer, made up of Kyle Lipke, Nimesh Subramanian, James Boyd, Mahesh Sampekatte, and Megan McConnell.</p>

<blockquote><p>For ShipIt IX, our team E=MC Hammer built a tool that looks up and publishes Millennium OAuth keys. This tool was created to be an easy-to-use, easy-to-search, and updateable source of truth for all those that request and use Millennium OAuth keys. We set up an api that hosts only the data we wish to present, in a read-only &ldquo;MAP&rdquo; so users understand the structure of the data. We had a blast on the project and would recommend attending a ShipIt day yourself!</p></blockquote>

<p>Judge Greg Whitsitt noted that their project was:</p>

<blockquote><p>&hellip;applicable across teams, solves a problem many face. A great idea and great execution.</p></blockquote>

<div align="center">
  <img class="center" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2017-09-11-shipit-ix-day-summer-2017/shipit-day-ix-7.jpg">
  <sub>Team E=MC Hammer.</sub>
</div>


<h3>Team Jumpy Woodchucks</h3>

<p>Team Jumpy Woodchucks, made up of Hans Perera, Nathaniel Owen, Ann Dickey, James Thomas, and Pramoth Murali took third place. Their project was Chamberlain:</p>

<blockquote><p>Light notification system for all your notification needs that decorates your desk. This system currently supports alerts for Microsoft Outlook, Crucible, and Millennium domain health. Designed to be highly customizable and a project for teams to learn about electronics and use of Makerspace.</p></blockquote>

<p>Judges commented that this project was what the heart of ShipIt Day is all about.</p>

<div align="center">
  <img class="center" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2017-09-11-shipit-ix-day-summer-2017/shipit-day-ix-5.jpg">
  <sub>Team Jumpy Woodchucks.</sub>
</div>


<h3>People&rsquo;s Choice Awards</h3>

<p>We had a packed house for ShipIt Day presentations. Associates could watch live in the Assembly or catch it on the livestream website.  One of the best parts of ShipIt Day is letting the audience join in on the fun and vote for their favorite team name, best presentation, and favorite project. Congratulations to the following teams&hellip;</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Favorite Team Name</strong>: 🌝 &ndash; Venkatesh Sridharan, Ian Kottman, Anthony Ross, Karthik Nimmagadda, and Abhi Mahabalshetti</li>
<li><strong>Favorite Project</strong>: Message Therapist &ndash;  Siddhartha Dutta, Ashish Nair, Noah Benham, and James Lawson</li>
<li><strong>Best Presentation</strong>: Bravo Avocado &ndash; Thomas Clay, Jacob Zimmerman, Jan Monterrubio, Max Schroeder, and Elisha Boozer</li>
</ul>


<div align="center">
  <img class="center" src="http://engineering.cerner.com/assets/2017-09-11-shipit-ix-day-summer-2017/shipit-day-ix-10.jpg">
  <sub>The Assembly during presentations.</sub>
</div>


<h3>Summary</h3>

<p>Each ShipIt Day, we see a handful of ShipIt &ldquo;veterans.&rdquo; It is always interesting to hear our associates take on the 24 hour event. Ian Kottman, a software engineer on the Population Health Genomics team, has a lot to say about his experience participating in ShipIt Day.</p>

<blockquote><p>I recently got to take part in one of my favorite events at Cerner: ShipIt Day. This was my fourth ShipIt and I was excited about the project my team had come up with. My team had named ourselves 🌝, which is one of the team member&rsquo;s favorite emoji. We planned to add a UI to a tool we created last ShipIt to manage access to Cerner&rsquo;s Makerspace. Our primary goal this time around was to have fun and win the coveted cheeseballs.</p>

<p>In the short 24 hours we had our team went through all of the stages of a typical software project: design, implementation, realization we overestimated, shedding unneeded features, and finally getting something working. Partway through the day we ran into issues getting Chrome to run in a Docker container and there was a brief incident involving internationalization breaking our error page, but after many whiteboard sessions and late night sodas we completed a working product. We even managed to have time for a few hours of sleep before the presentations. When it was all said and done we had accomplished our goal: we won cheeseballs for best team name! All in all, we had an excellent time collaborating and developing a tool that will be used for a long time to come. I&rsquo;m already thinking about what to work on next ShipIt&hellip;</p></blockquote>

<p>ShipIt continues to be a great way for associates to work on something they haven’t had a chance to work on, build relationships within different organizations, and most importantly, enjoy themselves. ShipIt Day IX was a great success. The projects were creative and have potential to be built upon and used in Cerner’s everyday work flow. We are already looking forward to our next ShipIt Day in December!</p>

<p>If you are interested in learning more about other ShipIt Days, see these earlier posts:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/shipit-day-viii-spring-2017/">ShipIt Day VIII Spring 2017</a></li>
<li><a href="http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/shipit-vii-day-winter-2016/">ShipIt Day VII Winter 2016</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=iqTp0dmLgUk">ShipIt Day Winter 2016 Highlight Reel</a></li>
<li><a href="http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/fall-2016-shipit-day/">ShipIt Day Fall 2016</a></li>
<li><a href="http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/spring-2016-shipit-day/">ShipIt Day Spring 2016</a></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Continuous Delivery for DC/OS With Spinnaker]]></title>
    <link href="http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/continuous-delivery-for-dcos-with-spinnaker/"/>
    <updated>2017-09-08T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/continuous-delivery-for-dcos-with-spinnaker</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last fall our team (<a href="https://github.com/mtweten">Mike Tweten</a>, <a href="https://github.com/TrevinTeacutter">Trevin Teacutter</a>, and <a href="https://github.com/zsura">Zameer Sura</a>) started working on the problem of automating <a href="https://mesosphere.com/product/">DC/OS</a> deployments in a way that wouldn&rsquo;t require multiple teams to duplicate effort and tie themselves directly to DC/OS APIs.  While DC/OS certainly makes the act of deploying an application much easier than anything we&rsquo;ve used previously, there are still many different ways you could choose to layer on deployment strategies and integrate with continuous delivery systems. Additionally, there may be lots of teams with very similar needs in this space and there are certainly more efficient uses of their time than making them all solve the same problems.  Furthermore, while DC/OS is a good choice today we need to make sure that we don’t become locked in and can change our mind in the future without a big impact to those teams.</p>

<p>Being an engineering team, naturally our first approach was to try to write a service to manage a simple set of deployment strategies with an API that we could reimplement over other resource schedulers (like <a href="https://kubernetes.io/">Kubernetes</a>) in the future.  However, after producing a prototype we really started to grasp that we were taking on a much bigger task than we should.  Our API could handle some basic pre-built deployment workflows, but if it wasn&rsquo;t flexible enough for teams we&rsquo;d need to continue to adapt it.  In addition, we would still have to work out how it would integrate with CI/CD tools like <a href="https://jenkins.io/">Jenkins</a>, and we&rsquo;d have to do a lot of that work again each time we wanted to support another resource scheduler as a deployment target.</p>

<p>At this point we decided to take a deeper look at <a href="https://www.spinnaker.io/">Spinnaker</a>, a continuous delivery platform that was open-sourced by Netflix.  It had originally been developed to orchestrate AWS deployments and had expanded to other providers like Azure, OpenStack, and more recently Kubernetes was added as the first container based deployment target.
Spinnaker allows for building deployment pipelines that can be triggered by things like Github commits or Jenkins builds and can then run stages to do things like start other Jenkins jobs, deploy new versions of an application, scale up or down applications, and disable old application versions.  With these capabilities we would be able to use Spinnaker to provide a consistent deployment abstraction while still providing the flexibility to handle deployment workflows that we didn&rsquo;t build ourselves.</p>

<p>The only minor problem was that it didn&rsquo;t support DC/OS, our preferred deployment target. After taking some time to dive in and get familiar with the details it quickly became apparent that adding support for DC/OS would be much easier than continuing to build our own system, especially since we had already become familiar with the DC/OS APIs while developing our prototype.  Not only would we then gain the flexibility to allow more deployment strategies than we originally anticipated, but it would also buy us integration with Jenkins and the ability to convert pipelines over to Kubernetes without much effort.  We checked with the Spinnaker community to make sure that no one was already working on DC/OS support and also with <a href="https://mesosphere.com/">Mesosphere</a> (the company behind DC/OS) to make sure they weren&rsquo;t planning to do it.  When both of those came back negative we began working on the project in earnest, with the goal of building something that would benefit not only Cerner but also the entire Spinnaker and DC/OS communities.</p>

<p>This was the first time that any of us had tried to contribute significant changes to an established open-source project so there was some adjustment and learning along the way.  We initially created our fork of the necessary repositories to our internal Github with the plan to finish the project before making anything visible publicly. Instead, we found that we wanted to more easily be able to share things with Mesosphere since they had agreed to give us any guidance we might need.  It also became apparent that it was too easy to commit things like config that referenced internal resources, or comments that referred to our own <a href="https://www.atlassian.com/software/jira">JIRA</a> issues.  If we kept going that way we were only going to make more work for ourselves cleaning those things up when it came time to submit our changes.  By moving our development to repos in <a href="https://github.com/cerner">Cerner&rsquo;s Github organization</a> we were able to solve both of these problems at once.</p>

<p>In spite of moving our code into the public Github we still maintained an insular development approach, determined to get everything just right before submitting a perfect polished gem to the upstream project.  In hindsight, we should have been less concerned about trying to get everything right all at once and submitted more incremental changes.  We thought it would be easier for everyone not to have to deal with our messy work in progress, but after our first pull request for one of the services ended up with over 130 files and a history of 100+ commits we realized that it&rsquo;s too much to expect the maintainers to review so much at once, especially when they may not be that familiar with DC/OS.  Ultimately, they wanted us to carve up that massive patch anyway so it would have been less work for us to do it from the start.</p>

<p>After completing this effort we&rsquo;ve found that we get even more benefit from Spinnaker than we initially expected.  Spinnaker also helps us manage deployments to multiple DC/OS clusters, use <a href="https://github.com/Netflix/chaosmonkey">Chaos Monkey</a> to test the resiliency of our applications, and even to deploy DC/OS itself on AWS. We&rsquo;re pleased to announce that our contribution has been accepted by the Spinnaker maintainers and is now <a href="https://www.spinnaker.io/community/releases/versions/1-3-0-changelog">available for anyone to use</a>.  The Spinnaker community has been great to work with and helped us by answering questions and inviting us to participate in the discussions with other companies that have contributed major functionality to Spinnaker.  This is an exciting opportunity to contribute something back to the open-source community and we can&rsquo;t wait to see where it goes from here.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Structure Matters: How Cerner Handled Too Much Health Data in HBase]]></title>
    <link href="http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/structure-matters-how-cerner-handled-too-much-health-data-in-hbase/"/>
    <updated>2017-08-28T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/structure-matters-how-cerner-handled-too-much-health-data-in-hbase</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>Background</h3>

<p>In order to manage the health of populations, Cerner builds data-driven solutions built on top of its <em>HealtheIntent</em>&#8480; platform. The platform transforms and standardizes data across disparate health systems. The data is then used in algorithms that aid healthcare providers and hospitals in managing and monitoring health both at a person and population level.</p>

<p>The Reference Record is one of the core components of the HealtheIntent platform. It represents the data known about a person&rsquo;s health from a particular source of healthcare information. Downstream components in the platform aggregate information across multiple reference records to understand the full picture of a person&rsquo;s health.</p>

<p>To create the record, the system performs both batch and stream processing. Some sources send the data to HealtheIntent once a day or once a month. That data is processed in batch, using Hadoop MapReduce jobs. For sources that send the data as streams of updates in near real time, we rely on a homegrown near real time framework that sits on top of Apache Storm. Both the pipelines persist their processed data in HBase tables.</p>

<p>For the data processed in batch, we write all the data about the person from a given source to the HBase table as one HBase row. We refer to this as a wide table. The HBase Rowkey is the source identifier followed by the person identifier: <code>/source:&lt;id&gt;/person:&lt;id&gt;</code>. Each row could have multiple columns, one per each healthcare entity like allergy, medication, procedure, etc. Another thing to note is this table is salted for better distribution of data across regions. That means a given person&rsquo;s data will be in a single region since it&rsquo;s all in one row, but the data for a given source will be distributed across the HBase cluster.</p>

<p>For streaming sources, we use a different table approach. We have a tall table, where each healthcare entity is written separately. The Rowkey in this approach would be built from the source identifier, person identifier, entity type, and then individual entity identifier. This allows the system to manage the information flowing from the stream more efficiently.</p>

<p>To make sure that the consumers of the record don&rsquo;t have to know whether the data is coming from a streaming or batch source system, we offer a Crunch-based extract API that is capable of reading from either table structure. The API provides a single, consistent representation of the data.</p>

<p>The purpose of this post is to discuss what happened when a single person in our system received a little too much healthcare over the course of her fake life.</p>

<h3>The Investigation</h3>

<p>We were bringing a new source of healthcare data onto the HealtheIntent platform using our batch processing pipeline. In the midst of this work, a small number of MapReduce jobs started failing. Our failure monitoring triggered and notified us that something wasn&rsquo;t right.</p>

<p>We turned to the logs to investigate the failures. We saw this (not very informative) message:</p>

<blockquote><p>Task attempt_xxxx failed to report status for 601 seconds. Killing!</p></blockquote>

<p>Our first assumption was that the issue was related to memory, but we profiled the job and found that the heap utilization looked fine.</p>

<p>Querying across all the logs, we were able to see two key pieces of information. One, a job was more likely to fail if it was reading from a particular source of data, and two, failures were correlated with alerts on slow response times in HBase. Drilling deeper into our logs, we were able to find that sure enough, we were timing out trying to read from a particular region in HBase.</p>

<p>The next obvious step was to look at region metrics. We found the region had grown in size to 115 GB on a cluster configured to have a max region size of 10 GB. More logs showed the table had stopped compacting and splits weren&rsquo;t working due to a 30 GB row in the table.</p>

<p>At this time, anything trying to read that row was failing, but some large writes were still succeeding. There would be attempts to bulk load new data to the region, but the loads would invariably fail due to the large row. When the job ran again, it would attempt to write the same data, over and over. Occasionally during these attempts, some of the data would get written to the region. This process piled more and more data onto the region, and the region wouldn&rsquo;t split.</p>

<p>As the region was growing, the situation got worse. As previously mentioned, we salt the row keys to distribute data across the cluster. Jobs interested in other source data were also reading from this region, so we started seeing failures in other jobs. Then in the midst of our investigation, we saw more HBase region servers start failing. Then HBase bulk loads in other MapReduce jobs were also failing. We knew we had to get rid of the row and split the region.</p>

<p>As some team members worked on a plan to deal with the row, others moved on to answering the question, &ldquo;How did this one row get so big that the bulk loads started failing?&rdquo;</p>

<p>With healthcare data, it&rsquo;s possible to imagine diseases that might lead someone to have so many encounters and activity within a single healthcare system that we could get to a gigabyte of health data about a person. However, we had never seen anything near this large before. It was a pretty significant outlier.</p>

<h3>Getting Rid of the Alternative Fact</h3>

<p>We decided to delete the person&rsquo;s data. However, the person had grown so large, this proved difficult. (The naive approach to deleting a row in HBase failed spectacularly.) Splitting was also not possible.</p>

<p>We needed a better plan. First, all reads and writes to the region had to stopped. This meant suspending all jobs that any potential to read or write. Since several teams depended on our data for their processing, we started by notifying all our downstream consumers. Then we stopped all reads and writes to the affected region. We copied the affected Hfiles to a new table. This allowed compaction (and as a result, deletion) to succeed. Cleaning up this one bad record brought the region size down to 2 GB from 200 GB. As part of this process, the table was disabled and the compacted Hfiles from the fixed region were copied back to the old table before it was re-enabled.</p>

<h3>Damage</h3>

<p>When we stopped all the jobs loading into that table, we had a stale data period for downstream processing. Reports that needed the data showed old information during the length of the incident investigation and mitigation. The good news is that our near real-time algorithms such as our Sepsis alerts and readmissions risk assessments were built on top of the stream processing system which was not impacted by this incident.</p>

<h3>Prevention</h3>

<p>In our postmortem for the incident, we reviewed what we could have done better before, during, and immediately following the situation. A quick win for us was to add HBase region size monitoring &amp; alerting. It is still reactive, but would help us react faster and minimize the duration of the event.</p>

<p>Ultimately, the root of the problem is that we have an approach that encourages a lot of data to accumulate in a single row. We had a design flaw. While this patient was outside the realm of anything we&rsquo;d seen before, it wasn&rsquo;t outside the realm of possibility. To quote an oldie, but goodie from Frederick Brooks, &ldquo;Our first response should be to reorganize the modules&#8217; data structures.&rdquo;</p>

<p>This event made us realize our batch and streaming representations of the data need to converge. That is the path we&rsquo;re now taking which will introduce its own set of challenges, but we&rsquo;re confident this will land us in a more stable, scalable place.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Managing Splunk's Knowledge]]></title>
    <link href="http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/managing-splunk-knowledge/"/>
    <updated>2017-07-14T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://engineering.cerner.com/blog/managing-splunk-knowledge</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When we first were given access to <a href="https://www.splunk.com/">Splunk</a> we were excited about all the functionality it could provide our team to help us monitor and debug our applications. We created alerts to email us if our applications are logging errors, dashboards to show health or metrics of our services, and field extractions as well as tags to make searching easier. As we created more and more of these Splunk knowledge objects we started to have issues. For regulatory and validation concerns, we have several Splunk instances that represent different environments. This required us to copy and paste or duplicate the Splunk knowledge object we created in one environment to all the others. This became very tedious and we saw all sorts of problems. Objects were only copied to some Splunk instances, updates were sometimes lost, and permissions weren&rsquo;t consistent or someone would forget to make their object publically viewable. We set out to look for a solution.</p>

<p>After we couldn&rsquo;t find anything that could easily help us we created a tool called <a href="https://github.com/cerner/splunk-pickaxe">splunk-pickaxe</a>. splunk-pickaxe is a Ruby gem that provides a command-line interface for synchronizing a directory or repository of Splunk knowledge objects written as files to a Splunk instance. So now when a developer creates a new Splunk object, they would create and test it in our Splunk dev instance and then open a pull request to our Splunk Github repository with the object&rsquo;s configuration or contents . Other developers review the changes before it gets merged and automatically pushed out to all our Splunk instances using our splunk-pickaxe tool and <a href="https://jenkins.io/">Jenkins</a> our continuous integration engine. This simplified things and provided consistency on these Splunk changes. We were also able to more effectively review the Splunk objects for efficient and proper Splunk usage.</p>

<p>The tool grew in popularity at Cerner and currently supports many Splunk objects:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://docs.splunk.com/Documentation/Splunk/6.6.2/Viz/Aboutthismanual">Dashboards</a></li>
<li><a href="https://docs.splunk.com/Documentation/Splunk/latest/Alert/Aboutalerts">Alerts</a></li>
<li><a href="https://docs.splunk.com/Documentation/Splunk/6.6.2/Report/Aboutreports">Reports</a></li>
<li><a href="http://docs.splunk.com/Documentation/Splunk/6.6.2/Knowledge/ExtractfieldsinteractivelywithIFX">Field Extractions</a></li>
<li><a href="http://docs.splunk.com/Documentation/SplunkCloud/6.6.0/Knowledge/TagandaliasfieldvaluesinSplunkWeb">Tags</a></li>
<li><a href="http://docs.splunk.com/Documentation/Splunk/6.6.2/Knowledge/Abouteventtypes">Event Types</a></li>
</ul>


<p>Check out the <a href="https://github.com/cerner/splunk-pickaxe#getting-started">Getting Started</a> section to try it out and feel welcome to <a href="https://github.com/cerner/splunk-pickaxe#contributing">contribute</a> any ideas or improvements.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
