<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>ux on Engineering Health</title>
    <link>https://engineering.cerner.com/tags/ux/</link>
    <description>Recent content in ux on Engineering Health</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>Copyright © 2020</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 04 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://engineering.cerner.com/tags/ux/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Bad Design is Bad for Your Health: Why Data Visualization Details Matter</title>
      <link>https://engineering.cerner.com/blog/bad-design-is-bad-for-your-health-why-data-visualization-details-matter/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://engineering.cerner.com/blog/bad-design-is-bad-for-your-health-why-data-visualization-details-matter/</guid>
      <description>Presentation Abstract by Jody Butts, Sr. User Experience Designer Given on August 11, 2017 at the UX Australia Conference in Sydney
Full presentation audio and slides are available here: http://www.uxaustralia.com.au/conferences/uxaustralia-2017/presentation/bad-design-is-bad-for-your-health-why-data-visualization-details-matter/
The proper design of data visualization details is imperative for accurate and actionable data visualizations and dashboards. In the health care technology industry, even the smallest design detail on a graph of patient data can have a dramatic impact on patient safety and outcomes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Celebrating World Usability Day at Cerner</title>
      <link>https://engineering.cerner.com/blog/celebrating-world-usability-day-at-cerner/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://engineering.cerner.com/blog/celebrating-world-usability-day-at-cerner/</guid>
      <description>World Usability Day is celebrated worldwide on the second Thursday in November every year. Across the globe, organizations host events and use this day to provide education on how to make products easier to use and simpler to access, as well as to celebrate progress in this pursuit.
The World Usability Day theme for 2017 was &amp;ldquo;Inclusion.&amp;rdquo; Inclusive design considers the range of abilities, language and other forms of human difference when creating a solution.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Building a Unified UI Component Library: Lessons Learned</title>
      <link>https://engineering.cerner.com/blog/building-a-unified-ui-component-library/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://engineering.cerner.com/blog/building-a-unified-ui-component-library/</guid>
      <description>Cerner is building an open source, mobile-first user interface component library for healthcare applications. Pulling years of experience and lessons learned across multiple teams together, we are creating something great. We are very excited to bring this solution to the public and to be contributing back to the community!
We didn’t simply decide to create this library, we started with segmented UI libraries focused on different aspects of the company which had smaller isolated needs.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>