<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Frank Rydzewski on Engineering Health</title>
    <link>https://engineering.cerner.com/authors/frank-rydzewski/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Frank Rydzewski on Engineering Health</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>Copyright © 2021</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 11 Nov 2013 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://engineering.cerner.com/authors/frank-rydzewski/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>2013 Software Intern Hackfest</title>
      <link>https://engineering.cerner.com/blog/software-intern-hackfest/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Nov 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://engineering.cerner.com/blog/software-intern-hackfest/</guid>
      <description>Providing opportunities for students to gain experience in software development and grow the skills necessary to excel in their careers after graduation is a top priority for Cerner Engineering. Our annual Software Intern Program gives students insight into the design, implementation, testing, deployment, and maintenance of large-scale software projects, which are often beyond the scope of the typical academic experience.
In 2013, we had a total of 224 interns across all business segments with 107 placed into the Software Intern Program to grow their experience as Software Engineers.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>DevCon</title>
      <link>https://engineering.cerner.com/blog/devcon/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Aug 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://engineering.cerner.com/blog/devcon/</guid>
      <description>This past June, 2,500 associates from across Cerner came together for DevCon, our internal developers conference. Now in its 3rd year, DevCon is a two-day, engineering-led conference that was created to bring together Cerner associates involved in all aspects of development and technology. DevCon is organized and run like many other developer conferences, complete with a call for papers and a talk selection committee. This year, we had 80 talks covering a wide array of topics such as big data, user experience and design, DevOps, and mobile development.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
