<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Dennis Patterson on Engineering Health</title>
    <link>https://engineering.cerner.com/authors/dennis-patterson/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Dennis Patterson on Engineering Health</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>Copyright © 2020</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 21 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://engineering.cerner.com/authors/dennis-patterson/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Engineers Overseas for SMART and FHIR (FHIR DevDays 2016)</title>
      <link>https://engineering.cerner.com/blog/engineers-overseas-for-smart-and-fhir/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://engineering.cerner.com/blog/engineers-overseas-for-smart-and-fhir/</guid>
      <description>In a previous post, we discussed the need to provide education around our ecosystem and implementation of the FHIRⓇ and SMARTⓇ standards for developers and how we did so at our annual Cerner Health Conference. That same week, we were also a part of FHIR DevDays, which included a track entitled &amp;ldquo;Apps in the EHR.&amp;rdquo; We worked alongside track participants who were seeking to integrate their apps in a variety of EHRs, including Cerner.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Engineers on the Road for SMART and FHIR (CHC 2016)</title>
      <link>https://engineering.cerner.com/blog/engineers-on-the-road-for-smart-and-fhir/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://engineering.cerner.com/blog/engineers-on-the-road-for-smart-and-fhir/</guid>
      <description>Over the past few years, Cerner has been developing a standards-based platform on top of our Cerner Millennium® EHR. Rather than roll our own API, we’ve been using the HL7® FHIR® standard. For app integration, we’ve been using the SMART® on FHIR specification. If you’re not immediately familiar with those acronyms, you’re definitely not alone.
As we were developing the services, we were also fielding questions from 3rd party developers, answering a lot of questions internally, and trying to keep up with the specifications themselves.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>