<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>culture on Engineering Health</title>
    <link>https://engineering.cerner.com/tags/culture/</link>
    <description>Recent content in culture on Engineering Health</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 03 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://engineering.cerner.com/tags/culture/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>ShipIt from Anywhere: Our Lessons on Going Virtual</title>
      <link>https://engineering.cerner.com/blog/shipit-from-anywhere-lessons-learned/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://engineering.cerner.com/blog/shipit-from-anywhere-lessons-learned/</guid>
      <description>ShipIt Days are Cerner Engineering&amp;rsquo;s 24-hour hackathons where associates are empowered to brainstorm, plan, build, and present a project of their choice. This quarterly event is something associates enjoy by taking a break from their normal routine and focusing on a problem that they seek to achieve within a short time period (one day). The enjoyment of these projects often come from just working on something different, working with other colleagues, and applying their passions to an area they have been desiring to solve.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>DevAcademy Six Years Later</title>
      <link>https://engineering.cerner.com/blog/devacademy-six-years-later/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://engineering.cerner.com/blog/devacademy-six-years-later/</guid>
      <description>Cerner hires a lot of software engineers. In fact, we have hired over 1,600 engineers since our early career onboarding program, DevAcademy, went live almost six years ago. In particular, we use DevAcademy to onboard early career software engineers.
DevAcademy is a three part onboarding program built by engineers for engineers. The first part of DevAcademy is DevEssentials which covers a lot of the basics new engineers need to know about development ecosystems in our development environment.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ShipIt XIV</title>
      <link>https://engineering.cerner.com/blog/shipit-xiv/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://engineering.cerner.com/blog/shipit-xiv/</guid>
      <description>It is winter time in Kansas City, which also included our fourteenth edition of ShipIt, our routine hackathon competition we host at Cerner Engineering. Although the snowy weather may have kept participants between the warm walls of our Innovations Campus, the winter storm did not disturb the initiative and enthusiasm of the fourteen participating teams. Check out the video below to hear from ShipIt Day participants and supporters as to why ShipIt Day has become an engineering-wide program that supports Cerner’s development culture.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>DevCon: A tech conference for engineering, by engineering</title>
      <link>https://engineering.cerner.com/blog/devcon-recap/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://engineering.cerner.com/blog/devcon-recap/</guid>
      <description>In 2010 a group of Cerner engineers went to their leadership with an idea: a Cerner tech conference just for the internal development community, built and run from the ground up. The idea for a conference like this had been brewing at Cerner for several years. It was seen as an opportunity to create a large scale, sharing and learning experience for associates in Cerner&amp;rsquo;s technical workforces.
From the beginning, buy-in from leadership was essential for the conference to succeed.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2^5 Coding Competition 2018</title>
      <link>https://engineering.cerner.com/blog/2-to-the-5th-coding-competition-2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://engineering.cerner.com/blog/2-to-the-5th-coding-competition-2018/</guid>
      <description>At Cerner, associates are always encouraged to develop tools and methods to improve their productivity. With this year&amp;rsquo;s theme being &amp;ldquo;Engineering Productivity,&amp;rdquo; Cerner&amp;rsquo;s fourth annual 2^5 Coding Competition provided associates another opportunity to dive into this subject and get involved in Cerner&amp;rsquo;s development culture.
As usual, this year&amp;rsquo;s 2^5 Coding Competition was kicked off alongside Programmer&amp;rsquo;s Day festivities on September 13th. The competition lasts 32 days, and associates are encouraged to submit code every day.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ShipIt XIII</title>
      <link>https://engineering.cerner.com/blog/shipit-xiii/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://engineering.cerner.com/blog/shipit-xiii/</guid>
      <description>What does it take to be awarded the ShipIt Day Golden Keyboard?    ShipIt Day XIII concluded last week after an intense 24-hours of brainstorming, building, and presenting. Various projects were completed by Cerner associates across twelve diverse organizations. ShipIt Day XIII&amp;rsquo;s projects were some of the most technically advanced this competition has ever seen.
Awarding the Golden Keyboard is no easy job for our judges. Back in 2014, the trophy was created to provide the winning team with a memento that was unique and grew with the competition.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Our DevCulture Team: Connecting Communities &amp; Empowering Teams to Invent the Future</title>
      <link>https://engineering.cerner.com/blog/devculture-team/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://engineering.cerner.com/blog/devculture-team/</guid>
      <description>The tech industry is constantly evolving; for better or worse, there&amp;rsquo;s no way around it. Now, more than ever, having a culture that fosters collaboration, empowers associates, and supports innovation is vital to a company&amp;rsquo;s success in the face of such constant change. However, an effective culture must be grown organically while being supported by senior leadership. At Cerner, we recognize the challenges involved in growing an effective, rewarding, and fun culture.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ShipIt XII</title>
      <link>https://engineering.cerner.com/blog/shipit-xii/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://engineering.cerner.com/blog/shipit-xii/</guid>
      <description>This month we held our quarterly hackathon event- called ShipIt Day. We would like to thank all the participants for making ShipIt Day XII a huge success. With 75 participants, we had associates representing 13 different organizations across Cerner. These associates were given 24-hours to meet the requirements of this hackathon which included making something that was innovative, usable, and value-adding. As the clock ticked down, our associates worked in their teams to complete a project while taking some time to enjoy the fun activities happening throughout ShipIt day.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ShipIt XI Day: Spring 2018</title>
      <link>https://engineering.cerner.com/blog/shipit-xi-spring-2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://engineering.cerner.com/blog/shipit-xi-spring-2018/</guid>
      <description>On March 8th and 9th, 17 teams of Cerner associates competed for the Golden Keyboard during our 11th ShipIt Day. During this 24-hour hackathon, associates were challenged to create something innovative, usable, and value-adding. This was the fourth ShipIt held at our new Innovations Campus, leveraging the wonderful collaborative spaces available.
With Shipit XI, we expanded upon a time-honored tradition of this event, the traveling trophy Golden Keyboard.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>One Year Calling Innovations Home</title>
      <link>https://engineering.cerner.com/blog/one-year-calling-innovations-home/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://engineering.cerner.com/blog/one-year-calling-innovations-home/</guid>
      <description>One year ago this month, Cerner development associates in Kansas City moved into a new place to call home for their workdays, Innovations Campus. The first two towers that stand on this campus provide 805,000 square feet of workspace for more than 3,000 associates. Eventually, the campus will grow larger, including 16 buildings and 16,000 Cerner associates. As that growth approaches, it is important to reflect on what these first two towers represent for associates and their development careers at Cerner.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ShipIt X Day: Winter 2017</title>
      <link>https://engineering.cerner.com/blog/shipit-x-day-winter-2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://engineering.cerner.com/blog/shipit-x-day-winter-2017/</guid>
      <description>On December 14th and 15th, 18 teams of Cerner associates competed for the Golden Trophy during our tenth ShipIt Day. Being this was our tenth, it was fun to reflect back on how this event started and how much it has grown.
 It has been great to see ShipIt Days start from small hackathons organically run by individual teams to now an engineering-wide quarterly event that brings together engineers from disparate organizations, allowing for a better cross-pollination of ideas and team members.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2^5 Coding Competition 2017: 32 lines or less</title>
      <link>https://engineering.cerner.com/blog/2-to-the-5th-coding-competition-2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://engineering.cerner.com/blog/2-to-the-5th-coding-competition-2017/</guid>
      <description>The Competition Part of Cerner&amp;rsquo;s engineering culture is to celebrate technology. This past fall, we had our annual celebration for Programmers’ Day. We celebrated the day with great food (taco bar and ice cream) and an evening of trivia.
Topping off Programmers&amp;#39; Day with a taco bar and trivia night with @geekswhodrink pic.twitter.com/pSjqBVBHxK
&amp;mdash; Cerner Engineering (@CernerEng) September 13, 2017  Happy Programmers&amp;#39; Day! Celebrating with an ice cream social. pic.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ShipIt IX Day: Summer 2017</title>
      <link>https://engineering.cerner.com/blog/shipit-ix-day-summer-2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://engineering.cerner.com/blog/shipit-ix-day-summer-2017/</guid>
      <description>There is no better way to end summer than with ShipIt Day! We kicked off our ninth ShipIt Day on August 10th, with more than 75 Cerner associates signed up. Nineteen different teams worked for 24 hours straight to complete their projects. For those unfamiliar with the event, ShipIt Day is a 24 hour hackathon for internal associates to create something innovative, usable, and value-adding. This was the second ShipIt held at our new Innovations Campus.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ShipIt VIII Day: Spring 2017</title>
      <link>https://engineering.cerner.com/blog/shipit-day-viii-spring-2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://engineering.cerner.com/blog/shipit-day-viii-spring-2017/</guid>
      <description>ShipIt Day VIII was held on April 20 and 21st. Seventeen teams made up of internal associates had just 24 hours to create something innovative, usable, and value-adding. This quarter&amp;rsquo;s ShipIt Day was held at our new Innovations Campus in the Link Conference Center. We were excited to get to utilize the space for this event. Another awesome addition to this quarter&amp;rsquo;s ShipIt Day was our new game rooms.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ShipIt VII Day: Winter 2016</title>
      <link>https://engineering.cerner.com/blog/shipit-vii-day-winter-2016/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://engineering.cerner.com/blog/shipit-vii-day-winter-2016/</guid>
      <description>Cerner’s 7th ShipIt Day took place on December 8th and 9th. ShipIt is a 24-hour hackathon with the goal of building something awesome, usable, and value-adding within a single day. The event was hosted at our DevCenter in the Realization Campus, a large open space that hosts our DevAcademy (to learn more about our DevAcademy, check out this earlier post). We had 18 teams made up of associates from different Cerner organizations.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fall 2016 ShipIt Day</title>
      <link>https://engineering.cerner.com/blog/fall-2016-shipit-day/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://engineering.cerner.com/blog/fall-2016-shipit-day/</guid>
      <description>Another ShipIt Day was held on September 8th-9th at the Realization Campus at Cerner. ShipIt is a 24-hour hackathon with the goal of building something awesome, usable, and value-adding within a single day. This fall marked our sixth ShipIt, which has has grown significantly since our first event.
   The event kicked off in the morning at the auditorium of our Realization campus. At this point, teams were already formed, instructions were given, and shirts were handed out.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>RailsConf 2016 Recap</title>
      <link>https://engineering.cerner.com/blog/railsconf-2016-recap/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 May 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://engineering.cerner.com/blog/railsconf-2016-recap/</guid>
      <description>At Cerner, we love Ruby and Rails and use it prominently in our cloud based solutions. When we found out RailsConf 2016 was going to be held in the hometown of Cerner&amp;rsquo;s headquarters in Kansas City, Missouri, we were excited for the opportunity to support the conference by attending as well as being a sponsor and hosting one of the official after parties.
   RailsConf 2016 took place in the heart of downtown Kansas City.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Spring 2016 ShipIt Day</title>
      <link>https://engineering.cerner.com/blog/spring-2016-shipit-day/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://engineering.cerner.com/blog/spring-2016-shipit-day/</guid>
      <description>ShipIt Day is an all day, all night hackathon with the goal of building something awesome, usable, and value-adding within the given 24 hours. This Spring marked our fifth ShipIt Day, with participation and reach growing with each event.
We kicked off the event at 10 AM on Thursday, when teams broke out and got to work and stopped only for food and caffeine. Many stayed until a few hours after dinner arrived, several stayed all night and took naps in their workspace, and a few worked through the whole night.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cerner and the Apache Software Foundation</title>
      <link>https://engineering.cerner.com/blog/cerner-and-the-apache-software-foundation/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://engineering.cerner.com/blog/cerner-and-the-apache-software-foundation/</guid>
      <description>At the beginning of this year, we announced that Cerner became a bronze-level sponsor of the non-profit Apache Software Foundation (ASF). Many of the open source projects we use and contribute to are under the ASF umbrella, so supporting the mission and work of the ASF is important to us.
We&amp;rsquo;re happy to announce that Cerner has now increased our sponsorship of the ASF to become a silver-level sponsor. Open source continues to play an integral role in both our architecture and engineering culture.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ShipIt - 24-hour hackathon for Millennium&#43; Platform Dev</title>
      <link>https://engineering.cerner.com/blog/shipit-hackathon-mplus/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jul 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://engineering.cerner.com/blog/shipit-hackathon-mplus/</guid>
      <description>At the end of March, some of our teams held their first 24-hour hackathon, titled ShipIt: Millennium+ Services FedEx Day. We had 41 participants, in 15 teams working on 15 unique projects. The idea was inspired by several teams spending a few hours every so often to work on different projects. After reading about Atlassian’s hack days, we decided to hold one.
The event was initially announced early in February, to give teams time to work this into their project plans.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sponsoring the Apache Software Foundation</title>
      <link>https://engineering.cerner.com/blog/sponsoring-the-apache-software-foundation/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://engineering.cerner.com/blog/sponsoring-the-apache-software-foundation/</guid>
      <description>Open source plays an integral role within engineering at Cerner. In addition to using open source software throughout our architecture, we recently released a few projects back to the community via our Github organization.
Today, we’re happy to announce that Cerner is now a sponsor of the non-profit Apache Software Foundation (ASF). The ASF is home to several projects that are essential components in many of our systems. We’ve blogged previously about several of these projects: Hadoop, HBase, Crunch, Maven, and Storm.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cerner and Open Source</title>
      <link>https://engineering.cerner.com/blog/cerner-and-open-source/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://engineering.cerner.com/blog/cerner-and-open-source/</guid>
      <description>(This post was written by Nathan Beyer, Bryan Baugher and Jacob Williams.)
The use of open source software has become nearly ubiquitous in contemporary software development and it is no different for us, here at Cerner. We have been using open source software, directly and indirectly, for decades. Over the past decade, we’ve grown in maturity both in our use of open source software as well as our participation in open source communities.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cerner Tech Talks</title>
      <link>https://engineering.cerner.com/blog/cerner-tech-talks/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://engineering.cerner.com/blog/cerner-tech-talks/</guid>
      <description>We are always looking for ways to share knowledge and learn new things within engineering at Cerner. Whether that be through meetups, lunch &amp;amp; learns, conferences, or DevCon, we have a variety of outlets available to us.
Today, we’re announcing a new program we recently launched: Cerner Tech Talks.
Cerner Tech Talks brings in great speakers for talks that would be of interest to engineers at Cerner. These talks will be held periodically and will vary widely in their content.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2013 Software Intern Hackfest</title>
      <link>https://engineering.cerner.com/blog/software-intern-hackfest/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Nov 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://engineering.cerner.com/blog/software-intern-hackfest/</guid>
      <description>Providing opportunities for students to gain experience in software development and grow the skills necessary to excel in their careers after graduation is a top priority for Cerner Engineering. Our annual Software Intern Program gives students insight into the design, implementation, testing, deployment, and maintenance of large-scale software projects, which are often beyond the scope of the typical academic experience.
In 2013, we had a total of 224 interns across all business segments with 107 placed into the Software Intern Program to grow their experience as Software Engineers.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project Lead the Way</title>
      <link>https://engineering.cerner.com/blog/project-lead-the-way/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Sep 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://engineering.cerner.com/blog/project-lead-the-way/</guid>
      <description>Improving the state of healthcare through innovation requires investing in others to join you on the journey; not just for today, but for the decades to come.
   Project Lead the Way has established the Computer Science and Software Enginering course that teaches computational thinking to high school students, and it will pilot in 60 schools across the country this fall. Providing exposure to a wide variety of computational and computer science concepts, students can program a story or game in Scratch, write a mobile application for Android, and learn about knowledge discovery and data mining, computer simulation, cybersecurity, GUI programming, web development, version control, and agile software development.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>DevCon</title>
      <link>https://engineering.cerner.com/blog/devcon/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Aug 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://engineering.cerner.com/blog/devcon/</guid>
      <description>This past June, 2,500 associates from across Cerner came together for DevCon, our internal developers conference. Now in its 3rd year, DevCon is a two-day, engineering-led conference that was created to bring together Cerner associates involved in all aspects of development and technology. DevCon is organized and run like many other developer conferences, complete with a call for papers and a talk selection committee. This year, we had 80 talks covering a wide array of topics such as big data, user experience and design, DevOps, and mobile development.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>DevAcademy</title>
      <link>https://engineering.cerner.com/blog/devacademy/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Aug 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://engineering.cerner.com/blog/devacademy/</guid>
      <description>When I graduated from college, I thought I understood what it meant to develop software in the real world. It required process. It required troubleshooting. It required quality. However, to me, process meant waterfall. Troubleshooting meant trying a few things and then asking for help. Quality meant manual testing.
Agile methods were not unheard of when I graduated in 2001. My professors noted that iterative development was better than waterfall; they just only taught waterfall.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The 30 Days of Code Experiment</title>
      <link>https://engineering.cerner.com/blog/the-30-days-of-code-experiment/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Aug 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://engineering.cerner.com/blog/the-30-days-of-code-experiment/</guid>
      <description>In software development, we solve problems. As we solve these problems, we build connections in our minds of how to look at a problem, relate it to previous problems and solutions, and re-apply past approaches and techniques.
These behavior habits build dogmatic ways of thinking and limit design choices to selective technologies we’ve used in the past. As we all know, you have to continually learn new technologies and different ways of thinking to stay current in the ever-changing landscape of software development.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>FIRST Robotics Championship Competition in St. Louis</title>
      <link>https://engineering.cerner.com/blog/first-robotics-championship-competition-in-st-louis/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Apr 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://engineering.cerner.com/blog/first-robotics-championship-competition-in-st-louis/</guid>
      <description>Cerner places a high value on talent development programs offering students the experience to build practical and tangible skills for the modern work environment. As part of this focus, Cerner supports FIRST Robotics, a competition providing experience in software engineering, where students learn to deal with complexity, time constraints, quality, and technical communications. Sound familiar? I wish they had this program when I was a kid!
High school students from Kansas City will be testing their minds, willpower, and teamwork in this global robotics championship competition April 24-27 in St Louis, Missouri.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why Engineering Health?</title>
      <link>https://engineering.cerner.com/blog/why-engineering-health/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Feb 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://engineering.cerner.com/blog/why-engineering-health/</guid>
      <description>Hello and welcome to a public face for Cerner Engineering, by Cerner Engineering associates, to talk about engineering, technology, and all of the other awesome things we do.
Cerner has been recognized as a visionary company, transforming the delivery of healthcare around the world. Improving the health of individuals and the delivery of care is an extremely large, complex, ever-changing problem. Along with the efforts of our strategists and consultant organizations, solving this problem takes a ton of smart folks in our Engineering and CernerWorks Hosting organizations, who are free to play with, adopt, and embrace new technologies and ways of working.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://engineering.cerner.com/culture/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://engineering.cerner.com/culture/</guid>
      <description>Transforming Healthcare      We love solving the hard problems that no one else wants to tackle. We embrace polyglot programming, distributed systems, and open source. We also know that it&#39;s important to allow engineers to take a step back and try new things. That&#39;s why we host periodic hackathons, meetups, tech talks, and an annual internal two-day developers conference in addition to attending, sponsoring, and speaking at industry conferences.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
