<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>CSS on Engineering Health</title>
    <link>https://engineering.cerner.com/tags/css/</link>
    <description>Recent content in CSS on Engineering Health</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 13 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://engineering.cerner.com/tags/css/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Building a Unified UI Component Library: Lessons Learned</title>
      <link>https://engineering.cerner.com/blog/building-a-unified-ui-component-library/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://engineering.cerner.com/blog/building-a-unified-ui-component-library/</guid>
      <description>Cerner is building an open source, mobile-first user interface component library for healthcare applications. Pulling years of experience and lessons learned across multiple teams together, we are creating something great. We are very excited to bring this solution to the public and to be contributing back to the community!
We didn’t simply decide to create this library, we started with segmented UI libraries focused on different aspects of the company which had smaller isolated needs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Difficult Debugging: Learning From Utter Nonsense</title>
      <link>https://engineering.cerner.com/blog/difficult-debugging/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://engineering.cerner.com/blog/difficult-debugging/</guid>
      <description>Preface As software engineers we invest time into thinking about the problems we are trying to solve every day. Sometimes the problems we face are small or simple. Other times they are large and complex. Either way, we can usually draw from our experience to find a path forward.
While coding, we run into a lot of different bugs. Often, they are simple typos or a misuse of an API. These problems do not bog us down very much, and they are quick and easy to fix.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
