<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Melanie Carpenter on Engineering Health</title>
    <link>https://engineering.cerner.com/authors/melanie-carpenter/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Melanie Carpenter on Engineering Health</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 08 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://engineering.cerner.com/authors/melanie-carpenter/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Fall 2016 ShipIt Day</title>
      <link>https://engineering.cerner.com/blog/fall-2016-shipit-day/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://engineering.cerner.com/blog/fall-2016-shipit-day/</guid>
      <description>Another ShipIt Day was held on September 8th-9th at the Realization Campus at Cerner. ShipIt is a 24-hour hackathon with the goal of building something awesome, usable, and value-adding within a single day. This fall marked our sixth ShipIt, which has has grown significantly since our first event.
   The event kicked off in the morning at the auditorium of our Realization campus. At this point, teams were already formed, instructions were given, and shirts were handed out.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Spring 2016 ShipIt Day</title>
      <link>https://engineering.cerner.com/blog/spring-2016-shipit-day/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://engineering.cerner.com/blog/spring-2016-shipit-day/</guid>
      <description>ShipIt Day is an all day, all night hackathon with the goal of building something awesome, usable, and value-adding within the given 24 hours. This Spring marked our fifth ShipIt Day, with participation and reach growing with each event.
We kicked off the event at 10 AM on Thursday, when teams broke out and got to work and stopped only for food and caffeine. Many stayed until a few hours after dinner arrived, several stayed all night and took naps in their workspace, and a few worked through the whole night.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
